<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="liberty.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="lby.00030">
   <teiHeader>

      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from "Social Liberty and Free Agency: Some Ambiguities in
               Mill's Conception of Freedom"</title>
            <title level="m" type="monograph">
               <hi rend="italic">J.S. Mill On Liberty in Focus</hi>
            </title>
            <title level="c" type="chapter"/>
            <date type="original" value="1991">1991</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author name="Smith">G.W. Smith</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
               <name>Stacey Berry</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>lby.00030</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century
               Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, the Center for Digital research in the Humanities. Permission to
                  reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the
                  originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project"> This excerpt from G.W. Smith's "Social Liberty and Free Agency:
               Some Ambiguities in Mill's Conception of Freedom" is transcribed from pages 247-251
               of <hi rend="italic">J.S. Mill On Liberty in Focus</hi>, edited by John Gray and G.W.
               Smith. Published by Routledge, 2000. </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
               <title level="a">Social Liberty and Free Agency</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">J.S. Mill</hi> On Liberty <hi rend="italic">in
                     focus</hi></title>
               <author>G.W. Smith</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>Routledge </publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London </pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>1991 </date>

               <idno type="ISBN"> </idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

            <keywords>
               <term id="commentary" type="genre">commentary</term>
               <term id="british" type="place">British</term>
               <term id="individual" type="topic">individual</term>
               <term id="liberalism" type="topic">liberalism</term>
               <term id="mill" type="topic">Mill</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-09-01">01 September 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Mike Page and Linda Pratt</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>terms into document</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-07-21">21 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header redo and Related Files</item>
         </change>

         <change>
            <date value="2005-06-01">01 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Stacey Berry</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Transcribed, Encoded</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head type="main">SOCIAL LIBERTY AND FREE AGENCY: Some ambiguities in Mill's conception of
            freedom</head>
         <head type="sub">CONDITIONAL FREEDOM AND THE PRINCIPLE OF LIBERTY</head>

         <p>Before examining the adequacy of Mill's position as a solution to the traditional
            problems of freedom and determinism, let us consider the implications of construing the
            liberty invoked in the principle along these lines. The idea is positive in four main
            respects:</p>
         <list>
            <item n="1">It involves what Berlin holds to be a crucial element in all positive
               versions of freedom &#8212; that of self-mastery or self-determination.</item>
            <item n="2">Rather than mere absence of impediments to action, it is a matter of the
               possession of abilities and powers for self-development.</item>
            <item n="3">Self-development is clearly for Mill a prized achievement&#8212;there is
               nothing 'value-neutral' about the notion, as there is about freedom <hi rend="italic"
                  >qua</hi> uncoerced satisfaction of wants, whatever they might be for.</item>
            <item n="4">The impediments to self-mastery explicitly mentioned by Mill are
               'internal' rather than 'external'&#8212;psychological defects of character such
               as weakness of will or subjection to habit, not coercion by others. On the other
               hand, it remains negative in two important respects:</item>
         </list>
         <list>
            <item n="1">The actual achievement of self-mastery is not a condition of freedom. The
               conformist, the lazy, even the vicious, may still on this definition be free. Mill
               insists that we may 'yield to temptation' and remain free&#8212;just so long as
               we could resisit, if we wished. Freedom thus remains basically liberal in that it is
               a matter of enjoying opportunities rather than of actual positive achievements.</item>
            <item n="2">Because the actual attainment of Mill's ideal of personality development is
               not presented as a necessary condition of freedom, he manages to sustain a
               distinction, often held particularly dear by orthodox liberals, between
               liberty&#8212;the opportunity to do something arising from the possession of the
               requisite powers&#8212;and what makes freedom useful or valuable: the actual
               doing or achieving of that thing.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Clearly, the dichotomoy of <hi rend="italic">either</hi> negative <hi rend="italic"
            >or</hi> positive freedom is simply misleading when applied to such a notion. Yet
            conditional freedom is precisely the idea at work when Mill makes the points he does
            about the value of a sphere of 'self-regarding' action, as it captures just those
            persons whom he is usually understood particularly to want to protect, namely those who
            may be presumed to be capable of forming their own personalities, and who may also be
            taken to want to do to so, but who are likely to feel inhibited by the prospect of
            social disapproval from expressing themselves in the way in which they feel they need to
            do. These likely exponents of individuality are to be guaranteed 'liberty of action,'
            that is to say, the Principle of Liberty ensures them a sphere of freedom within which
            they may, if they wish, take the opportunity to exercise their powers of
            self-development by practising 'experiments in living', where these do not harm others.
            This conception of freedom also squares with liberty <hi rend="italic">qua</hi> 'letting
            people alone to pursue their <hi rend="italic">own</hi> good in their <hi rend="italic"
               >own</hi> way', (p. 33) as well as with the orthodox liberal view of the proper
            function of the state, with which Mill is usually associated, that is, as protecting or
            conserving a freedom which individuals are presumed already to possess.</p>
         <p>However, though the conditional notion of free agency undoubtedly represents the core of
            Mill's understanding of liberty, additional complexities ar revealed by considering the
            implications of a common criticism of his Compatibilist solition to the problem of
            freedom and determinism. It is often argued that, strictly speaking, Mill has no right
            to a notion of freedom as self-development because his empiricist theory of personal
            identity, which resolves the self into a Humean 'bundle of impressions', cannot account
            for the possibility of an enduring self maintaining a persisting identity through a
            series of developmental changes. Mill is in fact rather less dogmatic about
            associationism, at least as far as its implications for self-identity are concerned,
            than is sometimes represented. But it cannot be denied that this represents a void at
            the centre of his philosophical system, in that his official epistemology commits him to
            precisely that attenuated conception of personality which gives plausibility to the
            standard liberal notion of freedom as non-frustration of wants. For, if the self is
            nothing more than a bundle of perceptions and desires, nothing more than their
            unhindered satisfaction can properly be demanded in the name of liberty. However, the
            criticism which raises philosophically more promising issues for Mill is connected not
            so much with his theory of personal identity as with his ideal of personal autonomy. It
            is contended that the basic flaw in Mill's theory of freedom lies in his admission that
            'the will to alter our own character is given us, not by any effort of ours, but by
            circumstances we cannot help: it comes to us from external causes, or not at all'. An
            admission that any clear-minded determinist can scarecely avoid, yet the fallacy seems
            manifest: if we cannot <hi rend="italic">actually</hi> determine our character unless we
               <hi rend="italic">actually desire</hi> to do so, and if the desire for self-mastery
            cannot (as Mill admits) be self-induced, are we not all ultimately heteronomously
            motivated, and hence by his own criterion unfree?</p>
         <p>Mill makes no direct response to this challenge, and perhaps there is none to be made,
            though there may be more to his position than some critics have been prepared to allow.
            There is something of an irony here, however, in that the deficiencies of his answer to
            Owen at the purely metaphysical level point him in a potentially very fruitful direction
            in his social philosophy. It is simply that, if the desire for self-reform cannot be
            self-induced, the external (i.e. social) circumstances which either stimulate or inhibit
            its occurance take on crucial significance for the individual's actual engagement in the
            process of self-development&#8212;even if this latter cannot, in strict metaphysical
            terms, lay claim to being a fully or genuinely autonomous condition of character. Though
            there is no explicit evidence that Mill clearly registers the implications of his
            position, the way in which he treats Owenite social fatalism as a real threat to freedom
            (and not simply as a misguided intellectual position) suggests that he implicitly slides
            from taking the desire for self-development as merely a hypothetical requirement of
            freedom to invoking it categorically, at least in the sense that anyone prevented from
            conceiving the wish for self-reform is to be classed with those whose desire is
            frustrated as being unfree <hi rend="italic">tout court</hi>. The context of this vital
            elision is to be found in Mill's comments upon the deplorable effect, as he sees it, of
            swallowing Owen's account of human impotence. One the one hand, it might 'depress' or
            'paralyse' the will of someone who already wants to engage in character self-reform, as
            do uncontrollable impulses and inveterate habits. But it can also prevent someone who
            could reform himself if he wished from even desiring to do so, by encouraging him
            falsely to think that he could not succeed even if he tried. On a strict construal of
            Mill's original condition formulation the former is, of course, unfree whereas the
            latter remains free. Mill, however, treats them as being essentially similar: in both
            cases individuals who might othewise successfully amend their own characters are
            prevented from so doing by the influence of a false ideology. Though the impediments to
            self-reform operate by way of different psychological routes, they originate in the same
            social phenomenon and eventuate in the same effect. Hence Mill's implicit elision of two
            conditions which, according to his preliminary account of conditional freedom, are quite
            distinct.</p>
         <p>By implicitly broadening the concept in this way Mill is, of course, enabled to embrace
            a far wider set of social circumstances as possible threats to liberty than could his
            liberal predecessors. It cannot, however, be over-emphasized that Mill's mind remains
            far from clear as to the precise logical contours and implications of the revolutionary
            idea of freedom which he develops as a response to social fatalism &#8212; a fact
            which, as we shall see, bears important consequences for an understanding of the central
            doctrine of <hi rend="italic">On Liberty</hi>. Nevertheless, Mill in effect is operating
            with a three-factor conception of freedom, one positive, two negative. 'Complete
            freedom', as he calls it, presupposes:</p>
         <list>
            <item n="(a)">Possession of the capacity to alter one's character, if one wishes.</item>
            <item n="(b)">Absence of impediments upon the exercise of this capacity when one does
               not wish to exercise it.</item>
            <item n="(3)">Absence of conditions inhibiting the occurance of the desire so to
            do.</item>
         </list>
         <p>The logical kernal of the idea lies in (a), and it is developed by Mill in response to
            Owen's social fatalism and offered as a form of modified Compatibilism as a solution to
            the metaphysical problem of 'free will'. When considering the kinds of constraints
            &#8212; (b) &#8212; upon the exercise of powers of self-development, Mill
            alludes in the <hi rend="italic">Logic</hi> to internal psychological defects of
            character; but external impediments are mentioned in connection with the threat of
            Owenite fatalism, and everything Mill says in <hi rend="italic">On Liberty</hi> about
            the dangers of coercive public opinion to freedom implies that he takes external
            constraints as relevant too. But it is in regard to (c) that Mill's worries about the
            peculiarly modern threat to freedom really take form. And it is this condition which
            bears fundamentally upon the Principle of Liberty in the essay.</p>

         <div type="file references">
            <list>
               <item> </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
