<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="liberty.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="lby.00051">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from "An Address to the American Colonization Society"</title>
<date type="original" value="1829">1829</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
<author name="Garrison">William Lloyd Garrison</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>lby.00051</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 94-96 and 99 of <hi rend="italic">Against Slavery: An Abolitionist Reader</hi>, edited by Mason Lowance.  Published by Penguin, 2000.
</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


<bibl>
               <title level="a">An Address to the American Colonization Society</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Against Slavery: An Abolitionist Reader</hi></title>
               <author>William Lloyd Garrison</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>Penguin
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>2000


</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
             <term id="history" type="genre">history</term>
<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
<term id="emancipation" type="topic">emancipation</term>
           </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-08-31">31 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Mike Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>proofreading and terms</item>
</change>
<change>
  <date value="2005-07-21">21 July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Header redo and Related Files</item>
</change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-06-15">15 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Encoding</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
	<div><p>Fifty-three years ago, the Fourth of July was a proud day for our country.  It clearly and accurately defined the rights of man; it made no vulgar alterations in the established usages of society; it presented a revelation adapted to the common sense of mankind; it vindicated the omnipotence of public opinion over the machinery of kingly government; it shook, as with the voice of a great earthquake, thrones which were seemingly propped up with Atlantean pillars; it gave an impulse to the heart of the world, which yet thrills to its extremities.</p>
	<p>It may be profitable to inquire, whether piety which founded, and the patriotism which achieved our liberties, remain unimpaired in principle, undiminished in devotion.  Possibly our Samson is sleeping in the lap of Delilah, with his locks shorn and his strength departed.  Possibly his enemies have put out his eyes, and bound him with fetters of brass, and compelled him to grind in the prison-house; and if, in his rage and blindness, he find the pillars of the fabric, woe to those for whose sport he is led forth!</p>
	<p>For many years, the true friends of their country have witnessed the return of this great jubilee with a terror, that no consolation could remove, and with a grief, that no flattery could assuage.  They have seen, that, instead of being distinguished for rationality of feeling and purity of purpose, it has exhibited the perversion of reason and the madness of intemperance.  Patriotism has degenerated into mere animal indulgence; or, rather, into the most offensive personalities.  Liberty has gone hand in hand with licentiousness&#8212;her gait unsteady, her face bloated, her robe bedraggled in the dust.  It seems as if men had agreed, by common consent, that an act, which on any other day, would impeach a fair reputation, on this, should help enlarge that reputation.  The love of country has been tested by the exact number of libations poured forth, the most guns fired, the greatest number of toasts swallowed, and the loudest professions of loyalty to the Union, uttered over the wine-cup.</p>
	<p>Indeed, so dear is Liberty to many, that they cannot make too free with her charms; they owe her so much, that they owe the Most High nothing.  It would shock their sensibility, and tarnish their reputation as patriots, to be caught at a religious celebration of our national anniversary.  The day, they argue, should be properly appreciated; and, unless a man gets gloriously inebriated, either at home or in the streets, at his own or a public table, in digesting his own good sayings or those of others&#8212;unless he declaims roundly in praise of freedom, and drinks perdition to tyrants&#8212;it shows that he is either a monarchist or a bigot...</p>
	<p>It is this fatal delusion, which so terrifies men of reflection and foresight; which makes the Christian shudder at the prospect before us, and the Patriot weep in despair; which, unless the mercy of God interpose, seals the doom of our country...</p>
	<p>I speak not as a partisan or an opponent of any man or measures, when I say, that our politics are rotten to the core.  We boast of our freedom, who go shackled to the polls, year after year, by tens, and hundreds, and thousands!  <hi rend="italic">We</hi> talk of free agency, who are the veriest machines&#8212;the merest automata&#8212;in the hands of unprincipled jugglers!  <hi rend="italic">We</hi> prate of integrity, and virtue, and independence, who sell our birthright for office, and who, nine times in ten, do not get Esau's bargain&#8212;no, not even a mess of pottage!  Is it republicanism to say, that the majority can do no wrong?  Then I am not a republican.  Is it aristocracy to say, that the people sometimes shamefully abuse their high trust?  Then I am an aristocrat.  Rely upon it, the republic does not bear a charmed life:  our prescriptions, administered through the medium of the ballot-box&#8212;the mouth of the political body&#8212;may kill or cure, according to the nature of the disease, and our wisdom in applying the remedy.  It is possible that a people may bear the title of freemen, who execute the work of slaves.  To the dullest observer of the signs of the times, it must be apparent, that we are rapidly approximating to this condition...(Lowance 94-96)</p></div>
	<div>
	<p>Every Fourth of July, our Declaration of Independence is produced, with a sublime indignation, to set forth the tyranny of the mother country, and to challenge the admiration of the world.  But what a pitiful detail of grievances does this document present, in comparison with the wrongs which our slaves endure!  In the one case, it is hardly the plucking of a hair from the head; in the other, it is the crushing of a live body on the wheel; the stings of the wasp contrasted with the tortures of the inquisition.  Before God, I must say, that such a glaring contradiction, as exists between our creed and practice, the annals of six thousand years cannot parallel.  In view of it, I am ashamed of my country.  I am sick of our unmeaning declamation in praise of liberty and equality; of our hypocritical cant about the unalienable rights of man.  I could not, for my right hand, stand up before a European assembly, and exult that I am an American citizen, and denounce the usurpations of kingly government as wicked and unjust; or, should I make the attempt, the recollection of my country's barbarity and despotism would blister my lips, and cover my cheeks with burning blushes of shame...(Lowance 99)</p></div> 


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>