<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="liberty.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="lby.00058">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">Letter to Edward Coles</title>
            
<date type="original" value="1814">1814</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
<author name="Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>lby.00058</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 641-42 of the 1944 Modern Library edition of <hi rend="italic">The Life and Selected Writings of Thomas Jefferson</hi>, edited by Adrienne Koch and William Peden. 
</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


<bibl>
               <title level="a">Letter to Edward Coles&#8212;August, 25, 1814
</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Life and Selected Writings of Thomas Jefferson</hi></title>
               <author>Thomas Jefferson</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>Random House</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>1944

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
              <term id="history" type="genre">history</term>
<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
<term id="emancipation" type="topic">emancipation</term>
<term id="americanrevolution" type="topic">American Revolution</term>
<term id="jefferson" type="topic">Jefferson</term>
           </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-08-23">23 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Term and File-link coding</item>
</change>
<change>
  <date value="2005-07-22">22 July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Header redo and Related Files</item>
</change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-06-17">17 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Encoding</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
	<head>To Edward Coles</head>
	
	<dateline>Monticello, August 25, '14</dateline>


	<salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
	<p>Your favour of July 31, was duly received, and was read with peculiar pleasure.  The sentiments breathed through the whole do honor to both the head and heart of the writer.  Mine on the subject of slavery of negroes have long since been in possession of the public, and time has only served to give them stronger root.  The love of justice and love of country plead equally the cause of these people, and it is a moral reproach to us that they should have pleaded it so long in vain, and should have produced not a single effort, nay I fear not much serious willingness to relieve them &amp; ourselves from our present condition of moral &amp; political reprobation.  From those of the former generation who were in the fulness of age when I came into public life, which was while our controversy with England was on paper only, I soon saw that nothing was to be hoped.  Nursed and educated in the daily habit of seeing the degraded condition, both bodily and mental, of those unfortunate beings, not reflecting that that degradation was very much the work of themselves &amp; their fathers, few minds have yet doubted but that they were as legitimate subjects of property as their horses and cattle.  The quiet and monotonous course of colonial life has been distributed by no alarm, and little reflection on the value of liberty.  And when alarm was taken at an enterprize on their own, it was not easy to carry them to the whole length of the principles which they invoked for themselves.  In the first or second session of the Legislature after I became a member, I drew to this subject the attention of Col. Bland, one of the oldest, ablest, &amp; most respected members, and he undertook to move for certain moderate extensions of the protection of the laws to these people.  I seconded his motion, and, as a younger member, was more spared in the debate; but he was denounced as an enemy of his country, &amp; was treated with the grossest indecorum.  From an early stage of our revolution other &amp; more distant duties were assigned to me, so that from that time till my return from Europe in 1789, and I may say till I returned to reside at home in 1809, I had little opportunity of knowing the progress of public sentiment here on this subject.  I had always hoped that the younger generation receiving their early impressions after the flame of liberty had been kindled in every breast, &amp; had become as it were the vital spirit of every American, that the generous temperment of youth, analogous to the motion of their blood, and above the suggestions of avarice, would have sympathized with oppression whereever found, and proved their love of liberty beyond their own share of it.  But my intercourse with them, since my return has not been sufficient to ascertain that they had made towards this point the progress I had hoped.  Your solitary but welcome voice is the first which has brought this sound to my ear; and I have considered the general silence which prevails on this subject as indicating an apathy unfavorable to every hope.  Yet the hour of emancipation is advancing, in the march of time....</p>
<div type="file references">
	<list>
		<item>
		<xptr n="lby.00057" type="same author"/>	      
		<xptr n="lby.00056" type="same author"/>
		<xptr n="lby.00059" type="same author"/>
		<xptr n="lby.00060" type="same author"/>
		</item>
		</list>
		</div>
	      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>