<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="liberty.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="lby.00025">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">"A Song of Liberty"</hi></title>

<date type="original" value="1793">c. 1793</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
<author name="Blake">William Blake           
</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>lby.00025</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 194-95 of the Penguin edition of William Blake's <hi rend="italic">Complete Poems</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


<bibl>
               <title level="a"></title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">A Song of Liberty</hi></title>
               <author>William Blake</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Penguin
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
London

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1977

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
             <term id="poetry" type="genre">poetry</term>
<term id="british" type="place">British</term>
<term id="radicalism" type="topic">radicalism</term>
<term id="frenchrevolution" type="topic">French Revolution</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-09-02">02 September 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Mike Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>terms into document</item>
</change>
<change>
  <date value="2005-07-21">21 July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Header redo and Related Files</item>
</change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-06-02">02 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Encoding</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
	<lg type="poem">
	<l>The Eternal Female groand! it was heard over all the Earth:</l>
	<l>Albions coast is sick silent; the American meadows faint!</l>
	<l>Shadows of Prophecy shiver along by the lakes and the rivers and mutter across the ocean?  France rend down thy dungeon;</l>
	<l>Golden Spain burst the barriers of old Rome;</l>
	<l>Cast thy keys O Rome into the deep down falling, even to eteernity down falling,</l>
	<l>And weep</l>
	<l>In her trembling hands she took the new born terror howling:</l>
	<l>On those infinite mountains of light now barr'd out by the atlantic sea, the new born fire stood before the starry king!</l>
	<l>Flag'd with grey brow'd snows and thunderous visages the jealous wings wav'd over the deep.</l>
	<l>The speary hand burned aloft, unbuckled was the shield, forth went the hand of jealousy among the flaming hair, and hurl'd the new born wonder thro' the starry night.</l>
	<l>The fire, the fire, is falling!</l>
	<l>Look up! look up! O citizen of London enlarge thy countenance; O Jew, leave counting gold! return to thy oil and wine; O African! black African! (go winged thought widen his forehead.)</l>
	<l>The fiery limbs, the flaming hair, shot like the sinking sun into the western sea.</l>
	<l>Wak'd from his eternal sleep, the hoary element roaring fled away:</l>
	<l>Down rushd beating wings in vain the jealous king; his grey brow'd councellors, thunderous warriors, curl'd veterans, among helms, and shields, and chariots[,] horses, elephants:  banners, castles, slings and rocks,</l>
	<l>Falling, rushing, ruining! buried in the ruins, on Urthona's dens.</l>
	<l>All night beneath the ruins, then their sullen flames faded emerge round the gloomy king,</l>
	<l>With thunder and fire: leading his starry hosts thro' the waste wilderness he promulgates his ten commands, glancing his beamy eyelids over the deep in dark dismay,</l>
	<l>Where the son of fire in his eastern cloud, while the morning plumes her golden breast.</l>
	<l>Spurning the clouds written with curses stamps the stony law to dust, loosing the eternal horses from the dens of night, crying</l>
	<l>Empire is no more! and now the lion &amp; wolf shall cease</l>

	</lg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>