<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00057</field>
      <field name="title">Letter to Colonel William Duane</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">jefferson</field>
      <field name="text">To Colonel William DuaneMonticello, March 28, 1811....The last hope of human liberty in this world rests on us.  We ought,
         for so dear a state, to sacrifice every attachment and every enmity.  Leave the President free to choose his own coadjutors,
         to pursue his own measures, and support him and them, even if we think we are wiser than they, honester than they are, or
         possessing more enlarged information of the state of things.  If we move in mass, be it ever so circuitously, we shall attain
         our object; but if we break into squads, every one pursuing the path he thinks most direct, we become an easy conquest to
         those who can now barely hold us in check.  I repeat again, that we ought not to schismatize on either men or measures.  Principles
         alone can justify that.  If we find our government in all its branches rushing headlong, like our predecessors, into the arms
         of monarchy, if we find them violating our dearest rights, the trial by jury, the freedom of the press, the freedom of opinion,
         civil or religious, or opening on our peace of mind or personal safety the sluices of terrorism, if we see them raising standing
         armies, when the absence of all other danger points to these as the sole objects on which they are to be employed, then indeed
         let us withdraw and call the nation to its tents.  But while our functionaries are wise, and honest, and vigilant, let us
         move compactly under their guidance, and we have nothing to fear.  Things may here and there go a little wrong.  It is not
         in their power to prevent it.  But all will be right in the end, though not perhaps by the shortest means.... 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>