<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00061</field>
      <field name="title">Poetical Tributes to the Memory of Abraham Lincoln</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">lincoln</field>
      <field name="topic">civilwar</field>
      <field name="text">By S.G.W. BenjaminLet the nation weep,As they bear the martyr,To his last, long sleep!Ay, let the nation weep!Another such
         as heWe nevermore shall seeThis side eternity.Ay, let the nation weep,And let the slow bells tollFor the noblest soulThat
         ever dwelt in man,Or ever led the vanOf Freedom's hosts to victory,And rang the charge of Liberty.Well may the nation weepAnd
         shudder at the strokeThat all their slumbering wrath awoke.What wretch so impious as to dareTo smite the leader of the people's
         choice,Or seek to harm a single hairOf him whose heart, whose hand, whose voice,Were all employed to work the nation's good,And
         stop the flow of fratricidal blood?Perchance he did not seemSo great to those who deemA traitor or a NeroMay still appear
         a hero,If he but wear a classic faceOr ape the superficial graceThat marks the scion of a titled race;Not such was he for
         whom we mourn;From wealth or rank he was not born,Nor heir to patrimonial landsTilled by the bondman's weary hands;His was
         the celestial beautyOf a soul that does its duty;Noble patriot, husband, father,He did not strive to gatherThe laurels of
         a wild ambition,That only yield a vain fruition.To benefit mankind—this was his aim,To labor and to live unstained with blame—He
         died without a blot upon his name.Let all the weary and oppressed,From North and South and East and West,For whom his great
         heart yearned,For whom his spirit burned,To give the sufferings rest,Let all arise with lamentation,And with his own beloved
         nationBequeath the fameOf Lincoln's name—A heritage of veneration—To the remotest generation.Ay, let the nation weep,While
         the slow bells toll,And the cannon rollFor the funeral knollOf his mighty soul!Ye cannot break the slumber deepThat wraps
         his limbs in quiet sleep;He cannot hearThe crowds that treadAround his bier,Nor see the tears they shed;For he nevermore shall
         dwellAmong the people that he loved so well;Let the nation's sorrow have its wayFor him who was the nation's stay.Our hearts
         are sad, our eyes are dim;We hoped long years of rest for him,To enjoy the peace for which he wrought,The peace with his own
         life-blood bought.But he has rest,Among the blest,And with the Christ he loved.Enough—his work was done,The victor's crown
         was won,And God himself removedThe patriot-martyr to his home.Enough—his task was done;For us remains to guard his tomb;To
         bid the willow waveAround the sacred graveOf him who loosed the slave,And weave the fameOf Lincoln's nameWith that of Washington;While
         kingdoms crumble, old and hoary,In a world where all is transitory,They shall ever shine, twin stars of glory,With undimmed
         splendor, in our nation's story.By G. MartinWhile swells the unusual wail,In heart-gusts, o'er the murdered man,His life,
         my wounded soul, unveil,His entrance and his exit scan;For as in Timnath Samson drewSweets from the noble lion dead,So may
         a living soul renewIts vigor from the martyr's bed.Dimly within the western woods,Where Indiana smiles, we seeA peasant boy,
         whose thoughtful moodsStill bear him onward hopefullyWith heart benevolent and blythe,Which aches but at another's pain,He
         wields the axe, the hoe, the scythe,Singing the glad songs of freedom's reign.And when to manhood grown, fall taught,By rushing
         flood and winged wind,What freedom meant, one holy thoughtRuled paramount within his mind.That thought was—justice to the
         slave,Leading to words and acts sublime,And musings how he yet might saveHis country from her shameful crime.At length a statesman,
         rough, but true,Anon Columbia's chosen chief,He stands, and in the world's broad viewDeclares his purpose, firm and brief.The
         hour of trial hastens fast—Rebellion's roar, and battle's shock;He meets the suffocating blast,And stands unmoved, a granite
         rock.Seven crimson seasons o'er him roll,And treason, rampant, stands at bay;But with a calm, unshrinking soul,In heaven he
         trusts, and leads the way.In patriarchal tones he speaks,And from a million swarthy limbsThe chains fall off—oppression shrieks—And
         liberty sings glorious hymns.And as the bellowing strife prevails,The star-led world looks on amazed;But right, oft baffled,
         never quails,The rebel crew reel backward, crazed.And in the dust their banner lies,Trampled and torn—no more to shameThe
         light of the eternal skiesWith slavery's accursed name.His country's saved, his work achieved,He boasted not of what he'd
         done,But rather, in his goodness grievedFor all sad hearts beneath the sun.For even his most malignant foes,Blind perverts!
         whom he sought to saveFrom ruin's toppling crash; their woesHe pitied, and their faults forgave.And now his genial spirits
         seekTheir wonted channel—war's fierce rageHad surged against his pallid cheek,And multiplied the signs of age.A moment's respite
         from the storm,A little rest from goading care,His people fain to see his formWhere mirth and music thrill the air.Beside
         him smiles his loving wife,Leaning upon the honored manWhose life to her is more than life,Who feels as only woman can.Guileless
         himself, he could not thinkThat treason's foulest whelp had powerTo push him off from earth's dim brinkIn such a place, at
         such an hour.Behind him glares the demon eye,Behind him moves the demon hand,A quick, sharp sound—a start, a cry!Then gleams
         aloft the hellish brand.'Tis done! his venerable headSinks peacefully—his soul departs;The honest President is dead,And with
         him die all human hearts.Go, student of the vanished years,Compare the democratic sage,Whose exit leaves the world in tears,With
         the crowned sons of every age.His humble birth with theirs compare,His labor 'gainst their leisure weigh;Mark well how, shunning
         every snare,He kept the straight and narrow way.Draw thence this lesson—honest worth,That brightens more the more 'tis tried,Will
         triumph yet o'er all the earth,And take the place of pomp and pride.And also—the assassin's handMay smite the body, not the
         truthThat in the body bears command—For virtue wears immortal youth.By Belle F—.But later from town and villageA joyous pæan
         rose,And many a voice caught up the strain,"We're vanquishing our foes!"A key-note 'twas of Liberty,Of Freedom near at hand,And
         every patriot heart was thrilledThroughout our storm-tossed land.Then glad hearts flung our banner outTo float upon the breeze;And
         brighter seemed each star and stripe,Waving o'er land and seas.The olive branch began to twineAround the deadly spear,And
         Hope sang out in bugle notes"Redemption draweth near!"Alas, alas, for human hopes!A breath—a word—a blow—And hearts but yesterday
         elate,To-day are plunged in woe.A nation's songs to dirges turn;Our banners sables wear;And every loyal heart is touched,For
         all the sorrows share.All, all, who love the truth and right,Who love humanity,Who ever mourn when good men die,Must mourn
         for such as he.We need not name the man, whose deedsEach loyal heart has thrilled;And none but traitors fail to mournA heart
         so noble, stilled.O God! 'tis hard to feel Thy handHath dealt this heavy blow;Yet Thou art at the helm, and safeOur bark will
         onward go.Thou'st led our ship through many a storm,Through many a bloody sea;It strikes a rock to-day, O God!And none can
         help, save Thee.The President's DreamBy Benjamin Franklin TaylorAthwart the troubled waters swiftly sailingThou saw'st the
         phantom vessel cleave its way:Around its path the wandering winds were wailing,And white around it flashed the angry spray.Alas!
         it flitted o'er a troubled oceanWhere withering winds swept wildly as it past,And urged it onward with unquiet motion,Tossed
         by the tempest long—but moored at last.'Twas but the emblem of the swiftly glidingAnd waning hours of thy imperilled life,The
         briefness of thy glorious day betiding,Thou pilot on the sea of freedom's strife!Thou too wert battling with the tempest's
         power:Thine too a pathway o'er a stormy deep;But now the port is gained, no storm-clouds lower,The bark is safe—oh! faithful
         pilot, sleep!As the swift ships that on the far-off watersWax dim and vanish—so we pass awayFrom life's sad ocean—so earth's
         sons and daughtersFade like the shadows of the dying day;But thou, our chief! hast left a noble storyOf truth and triumph
         for our sons to tell,Thy vanished bark hath left a wake of gloryTo follow thee along time's ocean swell.Thou wert the vessel
         first God's message bringing,Glad news of freedom to Columbia's strand,From Afric's sons the tyrant's fetters wringing,"Proclaiming
         liberty throughout the land."Oh, now no blot of slavery shall stain us!Henceforth we stand, a commonwealth all free!Thou wert
         the first that blessed boon to gain us,Oh, martyr on the shrine of liberty!Thy bark hath faded from earth's gloomy water;Safe
         moored where never clouds nor storms arise,Far from these billowy wastes all red with slaughter,Thy post is won—the haven
         of the skies.Thy sail is furled amid celestial islands,"Neath fadeless sunlight and eternal day;Why should we mourn that to
         those glorious skylands,From troubled shores, the swift ship fled away?Not unto thee—to us—belongs the sighing,The wail of
         anguish and the falling tear!Not unto thee—to us—the pang—the dyingOf proud hopes sinking withered by the bier.Ours the wild
         dirge—the shrouded flag—the weeping—The death-bell tolling from the sombre dome;Thine, the loved form in stilly grandeur sleeping,The
         crown of glory, and the heavenly home. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>