<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00069</field>
      <field name="title">from The Progress of Liberty</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="text">HAIL, LIBERTY SUBLIME! hail godlike pow'r,Coëval with the skies, to earth new born;Thou parent of delight, thou source refin'dOf
         human energy!  Thou fountain vastFrom whose immortal stream the soul of manImbibes celestial fervour!  But for thee,O! best
         and noblest attribute of God!Who would the coil endure of mortal woe,The frowns of fortune, or the taunts of prideFloat with
         the gale, or buffet with the storm;Who labour thro' the busy dream of time,War with oppression, or resist the base;Opposing
         ever, and by each oppos'd,To count succeeding conflicts; and to die?Hail, LIBERTY! legitimate of Heav'n!Shall the poor AFRICAN,
         the passive slave,Born in the bland effulgence of broad day,Cherish'd by torrid splendours, while aroundThe plains prolific
         teem with honey'd storesOf Afric's burning soil; shall such a wretchSink prematurely to a grave obscure,No tear to grace his
         ashes?  Or suspire,To wear submission's long and goading chain,To drink the tear, that down his swarthy cheekFlows fast, to
         moisten his toil-fever'd lip,Parch'd by the noontide blaze?  Shall he endureThe frequent lash, the agonizing scourge,The day
         of labour, and the night of pain;Expose his naked limbs to burning gales;Faint in the sun, and wither in the storm;Traverse
         hot sands, imbibe the morbid breeze,Wing'd with contagion, while his blister'd feet,Scorch'd by the vertical and raging beam,Pour
         the swift life-stream?  Shall his frenzied eyes,Oh! worst of mortal miseries! beholdThe darling of his soul, his sable love,Selected
         from the trembling, timid throngBy the wan tyrant, whose licentious touchSeals the dark fiat of the slave's despair!Humanity!
         from thee the suppliant claimsThe meed of retribution!  Thy pure flameWould light the sense opake, and warm the springOf boundless
         ecstacy; while NATURE'S lawsSo violated, plead, immortal-tongu'd,For her dark-fated children; lead them forthFrom bondage
         infamous!  Bid reason ownThe dignities of MAN, whate'er his clime,Estate, or colour.  And, O! sacred TRUTH!Tell the proud
         lords of traffic, that the breastThrice ebon-tinted, bears a crimson tide,As pure, as clear as Europe's sons can boast.Then,
         LIBERTY, extend thy thund'ring voiceTo Afric's scorching climes, o'er seas that boundTo bear the blissful tidings, while all
         earthShall hail HUMANITY!  THE CHILD OF HEAV'N!....REASON, pow'r sublime!Accept the strain spontaneous from the MUSE,Which
         nurs'd on Albion's cliffs, delights to singOf LIBERTY, and thee, her ALBION'S boast.And tho' no flight sublime shall grace
         her toil,No classic lore expand her thinking mind,Prophetic inspiration, rapt, shall pourThis mystic oracle.  The pendent
         globeShall greet, with pæans loud, the sacred claimTo Britain's sons, by REASON ratified;And when the God of nature, "trumpet-tongu'd,"Shall
         check the fiery steeds that hurl the carOf shouting vict'ry, time shall trace her courseOn the proud tablet of eternal fame;And
         nature, tow'ring 'mid the wrecks of war,Shall bless her BRITISH shores, which grandly liftTheir rocky bulwarks o'er the howling
         main,Firm and invincible, as BRITAIN'S sons,The sons of REASON!  UNAPPALL'D and FREE! 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>