<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00014</field>
      <field name="title">Childe Harold's Pilgrimage</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">individual</field>
      <field name="topic">italy</field>
      <field name="text">Canto IV.Yet, Freedom! yet thy banner, torn, but flying,Streams like the thunder-storm against the wind;Thy trumpet voice,
         though broken now and dying,The loudest still the tempest leaves behind;Thy tree hath lost its blossoms, and the rind,Chopp'd
         by the axe, looks rough and little worth,But the sap lasts,—and still the seed we findSown deep, even in the bosom of the
         North;So shall a better spring less bitter fruit bring forth.There is a stern tower of other days,Firm as a fortress, with
         its fence of stone,Such as an army's baffled strength delays,Standing with half its battlements alone,And with two thousand
         years of ivy grown,The garland of eternity, where waveThe green leaves over all by time o'erthrown;—What was this tower of
         strength? within its caveWhat treasure lay so lock'd, so hid?—A Woman's grave.But who was she, the lady of the dead,Tomb'd
         in a palace? Was she chaste and fair?Worthy a king's—or more—a Roman's bed?What race of chiefs and heroes did she bear?What
         daughter of her beauties was the heir?How lived—how loved—how died she? Was she notSo honour'd—and conspicuously there,Where
         meaner relics must not dare to rot,Placed to commemorate a more than mortal lot?Was she as those who love their lords, or
         theyWho love the lords of others? such have beenEven in the olden time, Rome's annals say,Was she a matron of Cornelia's mien,Or
         the light air of Egypt's graceful queen,Profuse of joy—or 'gainst it did she war,Inveterate in virtue? Did she leanTo the
         soft side of the heart, or wisely barLove from amongst her griefs?—for such the affections are.Perchance she died in youth:
         it may be, bow'dWith woes far heavier than the ponderous tombThat weigh'd upon her gentle dust, a cloudMight gather o'er her
         beauty, and a gloomIn her dark eye, prophetic of the doomHeaven gives its favourites—early death; yet shedA sunset charm around
         her, and illumeWith hectic light, the Hesperus of the dead,Of her consuming cheek the autumnal leaf-like red.Perchance she
         died in age—surviving all,Charms, kindred, children—with the silver grayOn her long tresses, which might yet recall,It may
         be, still a something of the dayWhen they were braided, and her proud arrayAnd lovely form were envied, praised, and eyedBy
         Rome—But whither would Conjecture stray?Thus much alone we know—Metalla died,The wealthiest Roman's wife: Behold his love
         or pride!I know not why—but standing thus by threeIt seems as if I had thine inmate known,Thou Tomb! and other days come back
         on meWith recollected music, though the toneIs changed and solemn, like the cloudy groanOf dying thunder on the distant wind;Yet
         could I seat me by this ivied stoneTill I had bodied forth the heated mindForms from the floating wreck which Ruin leaves
         behind;And from the planks, far shatter'd o'er the rocks,Built me a little bark of hope, once moreTo battle with the ocean
         and the shocksOf the loud breakers, and the ceaseless roarWhich rushes on the solitary shoreWhere all lies founder'd that
         was ever dear:But could I gather from the wave-worn storeEnough for my rude boat, where should I steer?There woos no home,
         nor hope, nor life, save what is here.Then let the winds howl on! their harmonyStill henceforth be my music, and the nightThe
         sound shall temper with the owlets' cry,As I now hear them, in the fading lightDim o'er the bird of darkness' native site,Answering
         each other on the Palatine,With their large eyes, all glistening gray and bright,And sailing pinions.—Upon such a shrineWhat
         are our petty griefs?—let me not number mine.Cypress and ivy, weed and wallflower grownMatted and mass'd together, hillocks
         heap'dOn what were chambers, arch crush'd, column strownIn fragments, chocked up vaults, and frescos steep'dIn subterranean
         damps, where the owl peep'd,Deeming it midnight:—Temples, baths, or halls?Pronounce who can; for all that Learning reap'dFrom
         her research hath been, that these are walls—Behold the Imperial Mount! 'tis thus the mighty fallby.There is the moral of
         all human tales;'Tis but the same rehearsal of the past,First Freedom, and then Glory—when that fails,Wealth, vice, corruption,—barbarism
         at last.And History, with all her volumes vast,Hath but one page,—'t is better written here,Where gorgeous Tyranny hath thus
         amass'dAll treasures, all delights, that eye or ear,Heart, soul could seek, tongue ask—Away with swords! draw near,Admire,
         exult—despise—laugh, weep,—for hereThere is such matter for all feeling:—Man!Thou pendulum betwixt a smile and tear,Ages and
         realms are crowded in this span,This mountain, whose obliterated planThe pyramid of empires pinnacled,Of Glory's gewgaws shining
         in the vanTill the sun's rays with added flame were fill'd!Where are its golden roofs? where those who dared to build?Tully
         was not so eloquent as thou,Thou nameless column with the buried base!What are the laurels of the Cæsar's brow?Crown me with
         ivy from his dwelling-place.Whose arch or pillar meets me in the face,Titus or Trajan's? No—'t is that of Time:Triumph, arch,
         pillar, all he doth displaceScoffing; and apostolic statues climbTo crush the imperial urn, whose ashes slept sublime,Buried
         in air, the deep blue sky of Rome,And looking to the stars: they had contain'dA spirit which with these would find a home,The
         last of those who o'er the whole earth reign'd,The Roman globe, for after none sustain'd,But yielded back his conquests:—he
         was moreThan a mere Alexander, and, unstain'dWith household blood and wine, serenely woreHis sovereign virtues—still we Trajan's
         name adore.Where is the rock of Triumph, the high placeWhere Rome embraced her heroes? where the steepTarpeian? fittest goal
         of Treason's race,The promontory whence the Traitor's LeapCured all ambition. Did the conquerors heapTheir spoils here? Yes;
         and in yon field below,A thousand years of silenced factions sleep—The Forum, where the immortal accents glow,And still the
         eloquent air breathes—burns with Cicero!The field of freedom, faction, fame, and blood:Here a proud people's passions were
         exhaled,From the first hour of empire in the budTo that when further worlds to conquer fail'd;But long before had Freedom's
         face been veil'd,And Anarchy assumed her attributes;Till every lawless soldier who assail'dTrod on the trembling senate's
         slavish mutes,Or raised the venal of baser prostitutes.Then turn we to her latest tribune's name,From her ten thousand tyrants
         turn to thee,Redeemer of dark centuries of shame—The friend of Petrarch—hope of Italy—Rienzi! last of Romans! While the treeOf
         freedom's wither'd trunk puts forth a leaf,Even for thy tomb a garland let it be—The forum's champion, and the people's chief—Her
         new-born Numa thou—with reign, alas! too brief.Egeria! sweet creation of some heartWhich found no mortal resting-place so
         fairAs thine ideal breast; whate'er thou artOr wert,—a young Aurora of the air,The nympholepsy of some fond despair;Or, it
         might be, a beauty of the earth,Who found more than common votary thereToo much adoring; whatsoe'er thy birth,Thou wert a
         beautful thought, and softly bodied forth.The mosses of thy fountain still are sprinkledWith thine Elysian water-drops; the
         faceOf thy cave-guarded spring, with years unwrinkled,Reflects the meek-eyed genius of the place,Whose green, wild margin
         now no more eraseArt's works; nor must the delicate waters sleep,Prison'd in marble, bubbling from the baseOf the cleft statue,
         with a gentle leapThe rill runs o'er, and round, fern, flowers, and ivy, creep,Fantastically tangled: the green hillsAre clothed
         with early blossoms, through the grassThe quick-eyed lizard rustles, and the billsOf summer-birds sing welcome as ye pass;Flowers
         fresh in hue, and many in their class,Implore the pausing step, and with their dyesDance in the soft breeze in a fairy mass;The
         sweetness of the violet's deep blue eyes,Kiss'd by the breath of heaven, seems colour'd by its skies.Here didst thou dwell,
         in this enchanted cover,Egeria! thy all heavenly bosom beatingFor the far footsteps of they mortal lover;The purple Midnight
         veil'd that mystic meetingWith her most starry canopy, and seatingThyself by thine adorer, what befel?This cave was surely
         shaped out for the greetingOf an enamour'd Goddess, and the cellHaunted by holy Love—the earliest oracle! 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>