<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00059</field>
      <field name="title">Letter to Jospeh C. Cabell</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">jefferson</field>
      <field name="topic">individual</field>
      <field name="topic">napoleon</field>
      <field name="text">To Joseph C. CabellMonticello, February 2, 1816....No, my friend, the way to have good and safe government, is not to trust
         it all to one, but to divide it among the many, distributing to every one exactly the functions he is competent to.  Let the
         national government be entrusted with the defence of the nation, and its foreign and federal relations; the State governments
         with the civil rights, laws, police, and administration of what concerns the State generally; the counties with the local
         concerns of the counties, and each ward direct the interests within itself.  It is by dividing and subdividing these republics,
         from the great national one down through all its subordinations, until it ends in the administration of every man's farm by
         himself; by placing under every one what his own eye may superintend, that all will be done for the best.  What has destroyed
         liberty and the rights of man in every government which has ever existed under the sun?  The generalizing and concentrating
         all cares and powers into one body, no matter whether of the autocrats of Russia or France, or of the aristocrats of a Venetian
         senate.  And I do believe that if the Almighty has not decreed that man shall never be free, (and it is a blasphemy to believe
         it,) that the secret will be found to be in the making himself the depository of the powers respecting himself, so far as
         he is competent to them, and delegating only what is beyond his competence by a synthetical process, to higher and higher
         orders of functionaries, so as to trust fewer and fewer powers in proportion as the trustees become more and more oligarchical.
         The elementary republics of the wards, the county republics, the State republics, and the republic of the Union, would form
         a gradation of authorities, standing each on the basis of law, holding every one its delegated share of powers, and constituting
         truly a system of fundamental balances and checks for the government.  Where every man is a sharer in the direction of his
         ward-republic, or of some of the higher ones, and feels that he is a participator in the government of affairs, not merely
         at an election one day in the year, but every day; when there shall not be a man in the State who will not be a member of
         some one of its councils, great or small, he will let the heart be torn out of his body sooner than his power be wrested from
         him by a Caesar or a Bonaparte.  How powerfully did we feel the energy of this organization in the case of embargo?  I felt
         the foundations of the government shaken under my feet by the New England townships.  There was not an individual in their
         States whose body was not thrown with all its momentum into action; and although the whole of the other States were known
         to be in favor of the measure, yet the organization of this little selfish minority enabled it to overrule the Union.  What
         would the unwieldy counties of the Middle, the South, and the West do?  Call a county meeting, and the drunken loungers at
         and about the court-houses would have collected, the distances being too great for the good people and the industrious generally
         to attend.  The character of those who really met would have been the measure of the weight they would have had in the scale
         of public opinion.  As Cato, then, concluded every speech with the words, "Carthago delenda est," so do I every opinion, with
         the injunction, "divide the counties into wards."  Begin them only for a single purpose; they will soon show for what others
         they are the best instruments.  God bless you, and all our rulers, and give them the wisdom, as I am sure they have the will,
         to fortify us against the degeneracy of our government, and the concentration of all its powers in the hands of the one, the
         few, the well-born or the many. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>