<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00070</field>
      <field name="title">from "Rhetorical Missiles and Double-Talk: Napoleon, Wordsworth, and the Invasion Scare of 1804"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">commentary</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">napoleon</field>
      <field name="topic">radicalism</field>
      <field name="topic">frenchrevolution</field>
      <field name="text">1."As the French Revolution disintegrated into the Napoleonic Wars and Napoleon seemed poised to invade all of Europe, internal
         debates in Great Britain over governmental reform and social justice gave way to a largely univocal nationalistic rhetoric
         aimed at bolstering domestic solidarity and intimidating the enemy.  Not all British weapons employed against Napoleon were
         fashioned from metal and loaded with gunpowder, however.  A broad variety of anti-French rhetoric was launched from many sites"
         (103).2."By 1804 the brief peace of Amiens had fallen apart, the cross-channel travel by nostalgic ex-Radicals like Wordsworth
         that it engendered had ceased, and it had become unfashionable to praise the French Revolution, which seemed only to have
         created a monster, Napoleon Bonaparte.  As the year opened, England anxiously awaited the expected invasion, Napoleon's forces
         having been gathering at Calais for months.  Every shot heard along the Channel stirred fears that the invasion had begun"
         (105).3."For months, the newspapers' invasion coverage would vacillate between such swaggering and outright alarmism, but
         either way, the invasion scare would figure continually in readers' consciousness.  The prospect of an avenging 'Boney' was
         even used to frighten children into good behavior.  The rising sense of alarm also seemed to increase the acerbity of attacks
         on Napoleon in the works of caricaturists like Gillray, Rowlandson, and Cruikshank, whose anti-Gallicism peaked in the years
         1803-1805.  At the same time, the British press pummeled what was left of revolutionary sympathies among its readers.  Representations
         of the French in the British papers, like representations of the invasion threat, were of one stripe in early 1804.  In its
         efforts to galvanize British spirit, the press portrayed France as deprived of its civil freedoms under the iron hand of its
         dictator.  Britain, in contrast, was represented as a land of liberty, with a pedigree of successful and bloodless 'revolutions'"
         (107).4."The British considered France's current belligerence the natural result of its Radical experiments in governmental
         reform.  As Conor Cruise O'Brien has written [in "The Decline and Fall of the French Revolution"]:
         	Far from spreading liberty in the world, the French Revolutionary expansion strengthened reaction by ensuring that resistance
         to the French Revolution would be associated with nationalism in other countries, which were challenged by the violent strain
         of French nationalism in other countries, which were challenged by the violent strain of French nationalism released by the
         French Revolution.  This was the response in England, Russia, Spain, as well as in the countries of early occupation.  Thus
         French Revolutionary expansion, far from disseminating the ideas of the Enlightenment, actually hindered the progress of those
         ideas, by causing them to be associated with the belligerent chauvinism of one particular nation, calling itself la Grande
         Nation.
         This development signaled not only the Revolution's failure, but the counter-revolution's success.  The struggle between revolutionary
         and counterrevolutionary ideologies further polarized British classes, encouraged nationalistic sentiment, increased the suffering
         of the poor, and restrained the enlightenment ideal of humanitarianism among the upper classes.  This hardening of both the
         English class structure and the political power structure under Pitt's administration had curtailed dialogue over the nature
         of the ideal political state:  the administration now spoke a largely unified discourse of power that could not easily be
         contradicted" (109-10).5."In 'Lines on the Expected Invasion 1803,' Wordsworth echoes the press's call for a unified front
         against the enemy:Come ye—whate'er your creed—O waken all,Whate'er your temper, at your Country's call;Resolving (this a free-born
         Nation can)To have one Soul, and perish to a man,Or save this honoured Land from every LordBut British reason and the British
         sword.Such ideological solidarity, Wordsworth asserts, is necessary while Britain is jeopardized:  but he represents a comparable
         ideological unity in Napoleon's France as a lamentable phenomenon.  In 'October 1803' ('these times'), he writes,How piteous
         then that there should be such dearthOf knowledge; that whole myriads should uniteTo work against themselves such fell despite:Should
         come in phrensy and in drunken mirth,Impatient to put out the only lightOf Liberty that yet remains on earth!Wordsworth's
         distinction is that this unity, in contrast to Britain's, emerges not from rational resolution, but from irrational 'phrensy,'
         thus apparently echoing the charge that the French are irrational.6."....Wordsworth refers to Napoleon only once in the Prelude,
         and even then implicitly, but what he says reveals a great deal about where the evolution of his political sympathies stood
         in 1804.  In Book Ten, Wordsworth openly deplores Napoleon's December coronation:...finally to closeAnd rivet up the gains
         of France, a PopeIs summoned in to crown an Emperor—This last opprobrium, when we see the dogReturning to his vomit, when
         the sunThat rose in splendour, was alive, and movedIn exultation among living clouds,Hath put his function and his glory off,And,
         turned into a gewgaw, a machine,Sets like an opera phantom.To some extent, Wordsworth echoes the press's counterrevolutionary
         discourse here representing the coronation as unnatural—leaving France to set like a 'gewgaw, a machine.'  But he also claims
         that Napoleon has negated the 'gains' of France, that he has killed a natural process, a 'sun / that rose in splendour.' 
         The politically incorrect implication is that the Revolution had followed a natural, 'living' process now subverted by an
         unnatural empire.Let us delve more deeply into the implications of this passage.  It has been noted that it characterizes
         France's embrace of Napoleon by echoing Corinthians 2:22, where Paul warns about the perniciousness of 'false prophets':
         	For when they speak great swelling words of vanity, they allure throught the lusts of the flesh, through much wantonness,
         those that were clean escaped from them who live in error....For it had been better for them not to have known the way of
         righteousness, than, after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them.  But it is happened
         unto them according to the true proverb, the dog is turned to his own vomit again; and, the sow that was washed to her wallowing
         in the mire. (2:18, 21-22)
         By alluding to this biblical passage in his description of Napoleon's coronation, Wordsworth suggests that the dog—France—has
         relinquished its quest for liberty and regressed to the despotic rule of a single, powerful man, a form of rule that the revolutionaries
         had endeavored to abolish.  Rather than contrast Napoleon unfavorably to the French kings he supplanted, as the press had
         done, Wordsworth stresses the similarities between kings and emperors.  Much like the monarch Wordsworth had described in
         the 'Letter to the Bishop of Llandaff,' Napoleon has attained an 'unnatural situation' of power and is consequently removed
         from sympathy with his subjects.Wordsworth's subtle biblical reference equates revolutionary ideals with knowledge of God
         and with righteous living, a daring connection to draw in 1804.  It is daring as well to imply that Napoleaon represents a
         return to a despotic past.  Seen in this light, Wordsworth's appropriation of Paul's warning against false promises of liberty
         reveals not an anti-revolutionary, but rather an anti-empire, subtext.  Wordsworth judges Napoleon's power unnautral not because
         he is 'that base-born upstart, the Corsican Usurper,' as the Anti-Jacobin Review styled him.  It is rather his ideological
         descent from the unnaturally powerful Bourbon kings overthrown by the revolutionaries to which Wordsworth objects" (115-16). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>