<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00046</field>
      <field name="title">"Love and Liberty"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="text">The moonlight-winds played through the leafy trees,Making sweet music o'er the sleeping flowers;The old stars told the hour,And,
         like the swell of mournful symphonies,The ocean surges, wafted by the breeze,Echoed among the bowers.I caught the solemn music—bent
         the knee,Joining the glorious hymn of Love and Liberty.Across far blue Morgen-land, the stormHung the dark mantle, and the
         gathering cloudsCame down like sable shroudsOver my own loved mountains, heavy, warm,With a sepulchral weight, the dead air
         hung,As waiting to be stirred.  The lightening flashedRapid and far—rains dashedIn torrents down the mountain.  Each a tongueProclaimed
         in loudest accents, "We are free!"In thrilling concert sung,The same all-glorious song of Love and Liberty.The wild night-winds
         howled down the mountain passes,The crescent moon steered like a fairy bark,'Mid reefs of vapor dark,And silvered with her
         beams the waving grasses,Or lighted up the pine-wood's sombre massesOn the far hillby.  The sea-bird caught the gleamOn her
         white wing.—The beamRevealed the mountain torrent's dashing sprayIts fountain free!Field, river, ocean, tree,Joined the all-glorious
         lay—Chanted the same glad hymn of Love and LibertyThe warm sun climbed the zenith, shining downInto the bosom of the fragrant
         rose.A deep and still reposeHung over the thick wood, and not a frownDarkened the placid Lake.  The river playedWith the bright
         yellow lotus flowers, and madeA thousand rainbows, as its waters roseIn created foam.  Each beautiful and free,In noonday
         jubilee,Chanted the joyous hymn of Love and Liberty.The hurricane with fierce and rapid motionCrossed the blue deeps from
         which the planets gleamedAurora's splendors streamed,With roseate hues down on the floating oceanOf rain and storm-cloud,
         that in wild commotionRolled on from pole to pole.  The stormy NorthIts golden bands sent forth—Flickering athwart the zenith
         with a lightSo spirtually bright,Making the vault of NightOne gorgeous mantle clasped and gemmed with gold.And, ever as of
         old,When sang the morning stars, they whispered me,"Joyous we are, and free—Still chanting that old song of Love and Liberty!" 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>