<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00012</field>
      <field name="title">The Battle of Bunker Hill, or, The Temple of Liberty</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">americanrevolution</field>
      <field name="text">THE BATTLE OF BUNKER HILL,or THE TEMPLE OF LIBERTY;an HISTORIC POEM IN FOUR CANTOS.The veteran could no more—grief choked
         his tongue,While cramping agony his bosom wrung.He motions backward with his sword. The signThe patriots comprehend,—to yield
         the line,And farther combat merciful decline.With funeral step relucant they recede,While their rent heart-strings drops of
         anguish bleedAt times a tear falls scalding down their cheek,But none the utterance of a word can speak.Cold beads of sweat
         upon the brow congeal,Which show what inward struggling they conceal.Putnam yet lingering on the rear the last,Back on the
         foe a stern defiance cast.His countenance appear'd like Jupiter's, when heSummon'd the gods to reverence his decree.The hero
         leads th' immortals o'er the plain,At whom the vessels pour'd their wrath in vain.The Eagle, though retreating, waves her
         plumesIn radiant light and victory assumes.Soon on a neighboring steep the flag is seen,Touch'd with a ray of setting sun
         serene.While round the glorious Height a rainbow curl'dIts chosen colors beautiful unfurl'd—A sign—that Liberty would bless
         the world.The gazing multitudes on bended knee,With upraised hands adore the Deity.Pure from the altar of the heart is givenAn
         incense that conveys the soul to heaven.From every hill instinct with life is sentGratitude—a mental sacrament,That from their
         neck they loosen'd felt the yoke—That the first link in slavery's chain was broke—That the Supreme for them his arm made bare,And
         placed the token of remembrance there—That when the hills of other lands should fail,This chosen Height in memory would prevail;And
         when no more shall other days be told—Their deeds with all their circumstance grown old,This day would live in capitals of
         gold;That Warren's name a talisman would be,For nations stooping on a bended knee,To rend their chains—to rise—to strike—be
         FREE!ODE TO INDEPENDENCE.LET deafening cannon peal to heaven—Their kindled thunders jar the earth—Lo, this the day to glory
         given—The day that hail'd a Nation's birth!Let the full soul from south to north,Join to proclaim the wondrous day—Let shouting
         millions on the Fourth,Shrill to the heavens the news convey!The theme demands creation's tongueTo bear its swelling chorus
         high—To anthem first Columbia sung,Amd shall be heard till Time shall die!As blackening whirlwinds edged with fire,Strike
         terror to the guilty name;So tyrants one by one expire,Consumed by Freedom's hallow'd flame!France in her giant strength sprang
         forthArm'd with a spear and truth's bright shield;And, while she sang her glorious birth,Waved the tri-banner o'er the field!Beneath
         its folds exalted stood,On honor's loftiest parapet,He, who the gazing world adored—Our great, our good, our own FAYETTE!A
         captive long in durance bound,England majestic feels her might;Her chains fall sunder'd to the ground—Indignant, she demands
         her right!Hail! Albion! hail! the charm is broke,That long hath chill'd thy heart with fear;Loosed be thy neck from oppression's
         yoke—Poised in thy hand is Freedom's spear!Th' impatient goblets charge with wine—Let every eye invoke the sphere;Kneel—pledge
         the sages—names divine!And hail them with enraptured tear!We this proud day to them decree,And swear with an uplifted hand,That
         we'll maintain their legacy,Or sprinkle with our blood the land!WASHINGTON CITY, July 4th, 1839. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>