<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00037</field>
      <field name="title">Lincoln: Seen and Heard</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">commentary</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">lincoln</field>
      <field name="topic">radicalism</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="topic">civilwar</field>
      <field name="text">The Poetry and Prose of the Emancipation Proclamation"The Scene was wild and grand," Frederick Douglass remembered of the
         day when the words of the final Emancipation Proclamation first came over the telegraph wires on January 1, 1863. "Joy and
         gladness exhausted all forms of expression, from shouts of praise to joys and tears." Yet eighty-five years later, looking
         back at those same words, Richard Hofstadter declared that they boasted "all the moral grandeur of a bill of lading" — a cargo
         receipt.  Mark E. Neely Jr. echoed that view in 1993: he condemned the text of the Emancipation Proclamation as "leaden legalese."
         And those modern assessments were not unlike the view that had been advanced a century earlier by an ardent Lincoln admirer
         named Karl Marx, who complained that the style of the proclamation called to mind the "mean pettifogging conditions which
         one lawyer puts to his opposing lawyer." Even Frederick Douglass conceded at the time, "It was not a proclamation of 'liberty
         throughout the land, unto all the inhabitants thereof,' such as we had hoped it would be, but was one marked by discriminations
         and reservations."Such comments, from the recent and distant past alike, have understandably served to nourish a growing sense
         among modern Americans that Abraham Lincoln was at best a reluctant and uninspiring Emancipator—and, as others have added,
         a superfluous one as well, it is difficult to deny that the reputation of the Emancipation Proclamation has fallen into historical
         decline. Unenlightened on issues of race, the fashionable arguments go, Lincoln used emancipation as a desperate weapon of
         war only when it became clear that the Union could not be preserved without depriving the South of the "slave power" and without
         arming blacks in the North to put down the rebellion. Furthermore, critics suggest, Lincoln's document really had little effect:
         it freed slaves only where Lincoln had no power to free them and left them enslaved where he exercised the authority to break
         their chains. And finally, detractors assert, so many slaves were in the process of liberating themselves by the time it was
         written, fleeing into Union lines throughout the South, that even if Lincoln had not proclaimed it, black freedom was inevitable
         anyway. As Barbara Fields has argued, "No human being alive could have held back the tide that swept toward freedom."But is
         it fair to imply that Lincoln simply did not hold the tide of freedom? Exactly how and why has the Emancipation Proclamation
         faded from its original reputation as a revolutionary act? And, most important, does it deserve revisionist dismissal or renewed
         appreciation? As to why the proclamation has declined in prestige, five likely reasons may help explain the downward spiral.
         The first has to be the shocking absence of scholarship on the subject. Great acts call for great books, yet the Emancipation
         Proclamation has inspired a total of one: John Hope Franklin's slim, 130-page volume, issued for the centennial of the proclamation
         in 1963 and now more than thirty-five years old. Meanwhile, some 10,000 books on Lincoln have been published since emancipation
         took effect. As readers become more and more familiar with every other detail of Lincoln's personal and political lif