<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00065</field>
      <field name="title">from "The Emancipation Proclamation"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">lincoln</field>
      <field name="topic">civilwar</field>
      <field name="text">In so many arid forms which States incrust themselves with, once in a century, if so often, a poetic act and record occur.
         These are the jets of thought into affairs, when, roused by danger or inspired by genius, the political leaders of the day
         break the else insurmountable routine of class and local legislation, and take a step forward in the direction of catholic
         and universal interests.  Every step in the history of political liberty is a sally of the human mind into the untried Future,
         and has the interest of genius, and is fruitful in heroic anecdotes.  Liberty is a slow fruit.  It comes, like religion, for
         short periods, and in rare conditions, as if awaiting a culture of the race which shall make it organic and permanent.  Such
         moments of expansion in modern history were the Confession of Augsburg, the plantation of America, the English Commonwealth
         of 1648, the Declaration of American Independence in 1776, the British emancipation of slaves in the West Indies, the passage
         of the Reform Bill, the repeal of the Corn-Laws, the Magnetic Ocean-Telegraph, though yet imperfect, the passage of the Homestead
         Bill in the last Congress, and now, eminently, President Lincoln's Proclamation on the twenty-second of September.  These
         are acts of great scope, working on a long future and on permanent interests, and honoring alike those who initiate and those
         who receive them.  These measures provoke no noisy joy, but are received into a sympathy so deep as to apprise us that mankind
         are greater and better than we know.  At such times it appears as if a new public were created to greet the new event.  It
         is as when an orator, having ended the compliments and pleasantries with which he conciliated attention, and having run over
         the superficial fitness and commodities of the measure he urges, suddenly, lending himself to some happy inspiration, announces
         with vibrating voice the grand human principles involved;—the bravos and wits who greeted him loudly thus far are surprised
         and overawed; a new audience is found in the heart of the assembly,—an audience hitherto passive and unconcerned, now at last
         so searched and kindled that they come forward, every one a representative of mankind, standing for all nationalities. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>