<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00036</field>
      <field name="title">"A Chinese View of the Statue of Liberty"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">statueofliberty</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="text">"And this statue of Liberty is a gift to a people from another people who do not love or value liberty for the Chinese."SIR:
         A paper was presented to me yesterday for inspection, and I found it to be specially drawn up for subscription among my countrymen
         toward the Pedestal Fund of the Bartholdi Statue of Liberty.  Seeing that the heading is an appeal to American citizens, to
         their love of country and liberty, I feel that my countrymen and myself are honored in being thus appealed to as citizens
         in the cause of liberty.  But the word liberty makes me think of the fact that this country is the land of liberty for men
         of all nations except the Chinese.  I consider it an insult to us Chinese to call on us to contribute toward building in this
         land a pedestal for a statue of Liberty.  That statue represents Liberty holding a torch which lights the passage to those
         of all nations who come into this country.  But are the Chinese allowed to come?  As for the Chinese who are here, are they
         allowed to enjoy liberty as men of all other nationalities enjoy it?  Are they allowed to go about everywhere free from the
         insults, abuse, assaults, wrongs and injuries from which men of other nationalities are free?If there be a Chinaman who came
         to this country when a lad, who has passed through an American institution of learning of the highest grade, who has so fallen
         in love with American manners and ideas that he desires to make his home in this land, and who, seeing that his countrymen
         demand one of their own number to be their legal adviser, representative, advocate and protector, desires to study law, can
         he be a lawyer?  By the law of this nation, he, being a Chinaman, cannot become a citizen, and consequently cannot be a lawyer.And
         this statue of Liberty is a gift to a people from another people who do not love or value liberty for the Chinese.  Are not
         the Annamese and Tonquinese Chinese, to whom liberty is dear as to the French?  What right have the French to deprive them
         of their liberty?Whether this statue against the Chinese or the statue of Liberty will be the more lasting monument to tell
         future ages of the liberty and greatness of this country, will be known only to future generations.Liberty, we Chinese do
         love and adore thee; but let not those who deny thee to us, make of thee a graven image and invite us to bow down to it.Saum
         Song BoNew York Sun 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>