<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00008</field>
      <field name="title">Les Miserables</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">fiction</field>
      <field name="place">french</field>
      <field name="topic">frenchrevolution</field>
      <field name="topic">rev1848</field>
      <field name="text">CHAPTER III.SLANG THAT CRIES AND SLANG THAT LAUGHS.The French Revolution, which was nothing but the ideal armed with a sword,
         rose, and by the same sudden movement closed the door of evil and opened the door of good. It disengaged the question, promulgated
         the truth, expelled the miasma, ventilated the age, and crowned the people. We may say that it created man a second time by
         giving him a second soul,—justice. The nineteenth century inherits and profits by its work, and at the present day the social
         catastrophe which we just now indicated is simply impossible. Blind is he who denounces it, a fool who fears it, for the Revolution
         is the vaccine of insurrection. Thanks to the Revolution, the social conditions are altered, and the feudal and monarchical
         diseases are no longer in our blood. There is no middle age left in our constitution, and we are no longer at the time when
         formidable internal commotions broke out; when the obscure course of a dull sound could be heard beneath the feet; when the
         earth thrown out from the mole-holes appeared on the surface of civilization; when the soil cracked; when the roof of caverns
         opened, and monstrous heads suddenly emerged from the ground. The revolutionary sense is a moral sense, and the feeling of
         right being developed, develops the feeling of duty. The law of all is liberty, which ends where the liberty of another begins,
         according to Robespierre's admirable definition. Since 1789 the whole people has been dilated in the sublimated individual.
         There is no poor man who, having his right, has not his radius; the man, dying of hunger, feels within himself the honesty
         of France. The dignity of the citizen is an internal armor; the man who is free is scrupulous, and the voter reigns. Hence
         comes incorruptibility; hence comes the abortiveness of unhealthy covetousness, and hence eyes heroically lowered before temptation.
         The revolutionary healthiness is so great, that on a day of deliverance, a 14th of July, or a 10th of August, there is no
         populance, and the first cry of the enlightened and progressing crowds is, "Death to the robbers!" Progress is an honest man,
         and the ideal and the absolute do not steal pocket-handkercheifs. By whom were the carriages containing wealth of the Tuileries
         escorted in 1848? By the rag-pickers of the Faubourg St. Antoine. The rag mounted guard over the treasure. Virtue rendered
         these ragged creatures resplendent. In these carts, in barely closed chests,—some, indeed, still opened,—there was, amid a
         hundred dazzling cases, that old crown of France, all made of diamonds, surmounted by the royal carbuncle and the Regent diamonds,
         worth thirty millions of francs; barefooted they guarded this crown. Hence Jacquerie is no longer possible, and I feel sorry
         for the clever men; it is an old fear which has made its last effort, and could no longer be employed in politics. The great
         spring of the red spectre is now broken. Everybody understands this now. The scarecrow no longer horrifies. The birds treat
         the manikin familiarly, and deposit their guano upon it, and the bourgeois laugh at it. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>