<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00006</field>
      <field name="title">Les Miserables</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">fiction</field>
      <field name="place">french</field>
      <field name="topic">frenchrevolution</field>
      <field name="topic">rev1830</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="topic">individual</field>
      <field name="text">CHAPTER IX.NEW WRONGSWHEN the hour for quitting the bagne arrived, when Jean Valjean heard in his ear the unfamiliar words
         "You are free," the moment seemed improbable and extraordinary, and a ray of bright light, of the light of the living, penetrated
         to him; but it soon grew pale. Jean Valjean had been dazzled by the idea of liberty, and had believed in a new life, but he
         soon saw that it is a liberty to which a yellow passport is granted. And around this there was much bitterness; he had calculated
         that his earnings, during his stay at the bagne, should have amounted to 171 francs. We are bound to add that he had omitted
         to take into his calculations the forced rest of Sundays and holidays, which, during nineteen years, entailed a diminution
         of about 24 francs. However this might be, the sum was reduced, through various local stoppages, to 109 francs, 15 sous, which
         were paid to him when he left the bagne. He did not understand it all, and fancied that he had been robbed.on the day after
         his liberation, he saw at Grasse men in front of a distillery of orange-flower water,—men unloading bales; he offered his
         services, and as the work was of a pressing nature, they were accepted. He set to work; he was intelligent, powerful, and
         skilful, and his master appeared satisfied. While he was at work a gendarme passed, noticed him, asked for his paper, and
         he was compelled to show his yellow pass. This done, Jean Valjean resumed his toil. A little while previously he had asked
         one of the workmen  what he earned for his day's work, and the answer was 30 sous. At night, as he was compelled to start
         again the next morning, he went to the master of the distillery and asked for payment; the master did not say a word, but
         gave him 15 sous, and when he protested, the answer was, "That is enough for you." He became pressing, the master looked him
         in the face and said, "Mind you don't get into prison."Here again he regarded himself as robbed; society, the state, by diminishing
         his earnings, had robbed him wholesale; now it was the turn of individual to commit retail robbery. Liberation is not deliverance;
         a man may leave the bagne, but not condemnation. we have seen what happened to him at Grasse, and we know how he was treated
         at D— 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>