<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00043</field>
      <field name="title">"The Liberty Bell"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">libertybell</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="topic">washington</field>
      <field name="text">The bell! the bell! the glorious bellWhose merry chimes delight the ear!An ever cheering tale they tell,That all true men
         exult to hear.The glorious bell of Liberty!Another peal comes booming o'erThe wide Atlantic, charged with gleeAnd tidings
         glad, to each heart's core.The soul-awakening sounds of old!They rouse up all life's hopes anew:I know them well;—I heard
         them tolled,In lands where Freedom's friends are few.I gave that bell a pull of yore,And though forsooth a feeble one,And
         I may never ring it more,My fingers stir as if each toneTo instant action called again,In Freedom's cause—and thoughts ariseOf
         noble deeds, and dauntless men,That swell the heart and fill the eyes.The peal of THIRTY-FOUR! the pealThat made the tropics
         dance for joy!Again I seem to hear and feel,Bliss without bounds, without alloy.The tocsin now that roused the landOf Tell,
         in every fibre thrills,And bravery seems of heart and handAn instinct there that Freedom wills.The tyrant's knell, in every
         climeWhere bondage lays its curse on earth,The bell of death—is tolled, for crime.Against the land that gave him birth.Oh
         for a glorious peal at lastOf the true bell of Liberty!To rend the air, and strike aghastThe moster might of Slavery.Oh! for
         a swing of that great tongue,To shake the proud oppressor's throne,Where'er it's set: with one ding-dongTo bring the potent
         despot down.Oh! for a burst of that deep bellOf Mafra's tower, to fright awayThe people's foes, and ring the knellOf giant
         Mammon's godless sway:To smile with fear the fiends who tradeIn human flesh and blood,—the knavesWho give the gold to make
         the raid,And rail at those who vend the slaves;To save the land that holds the gravesOf Franklin, Washington, and Penn,From
         laws that make her millions slaves,—And, worse than brutes, of Christian men. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>