<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00053</field>
      <field name="title">Toward a New Society: American Thought and Culture, 1800-1830</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">commentary</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">liberalism</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="topic">washington</field>
      <field name="text">1."'The history of our country is the history of liberty,' declared the poet Joel Barlow in 1807.  Yet, he added ominously,
         'In my opinion, the loss of liberty in this country is not an impossible event.'  Barlow spoke for many of his contemporaries
         in believing that the unique American experiment in republican government was fragile and might at any time be subverted.
         The first fifteen years of the nineteenth century were haunted by a nagging anxiety that the republic that had emerged from
         the struggles and sacrifices of the Revolution might not survive the unforseen social and economic changes that revolution
         had unleashed" (3).2."There has been a lively debate among historians about the extent to which liberalism displaced republicanism
         as the dominant American ideology by the early nineteenth century.  Some historians see the Jeffersonian Republicans as they
         saw themselves:  as bearers of republican values into the new century.  Others have maintained that with the creation of the
         Constitution or at least by the 1790s, the dominant patterns of American thinking were closer to the liberalism of Adam Smith
         than to traditional republicanism.  The historians' debate reflects the ideological confusion of the early republic itself
         in which individuals and groups moved in and out of different philosophical and explanatory modes as they adjusted to the
         dizzying speed of social change" (5).3."The striking change in dress in the early nineteenth century is symbolic of the way
         in which formal distinctions between gentry and others were being minimized.  The powdered wig of the upper classes had practically
         disappeared by 1800, and the long hair tied in a queue that replaced it was virtually gone by 1820.  By the beginning of the
         century knee breeches and silk stockings of the gentry were being replaced by the French revolutionary style of pantaloons,
         which increasingly became the style for men of all classes.  Men's clothes were started on their career of progressive simplification
         and sobriety, which lasted to the 1960s.  Women's dress followed a different pattern.  After a marked turn toward a simplicity,
         indeed a skimpiness, which many moralists found sexually provocative, by the 1820s women's dress was swinging back toward
         an ever increasing elaboration and amplitude.  While millions of Americans continued to wear homespun, the increasing availability
         of factory-made cloth helped to blur the distinction in the towns at least, between the clothing of the gentry and other people"
         (8).4."Although American leaders never mobilized the arts in support of the republic to the same extent as the revolutionary
         government of France, they were certainly aware of the importance of iconography.  In a rare act of artistic patronage, Congress
         commissioned John Trumbull to decorate the rotunda of the Capitol with paintings.  The choice of subject was a delicate business
         for a building that had symbolic as well as practical significance.  Trumbull decided on actual historical rather than allegorical
         subjects: the signing of the Declaration of Independence, the British surrenders at Yorktown and at Saratoga, and the resignation
         of George Washington.  The paintings were not Trumbull's best work; in addition, there were difficulties in finding a suitable
         style for public art that had to bear the weight of both the historically specific and the universal.  John Randolph complained
         of the Declaration of Independence, with its life-sized, accurate portraits of forty or so eighteenth-century gentlemen in
         knee breeches, that he had never seen a painting with so many legs.  But if documentary realism produced problems, so in fact
         did classical symbolism.When Jefferson recommended the famous Italian sculptor, Canova, to make a statue of Washington for
         the state capitol at Raleigh, North Carolina, he suggested that the costume be Roman, since 'our boots and regimentals would
         have a very puny effect.'  However, when the statue was installed in 1821 it was much criticized:  Americans might like to
         praise Washington's Roman virtue, but they wanted his statues to look American.  Davy Crockett liked the realistic Washington
         statue in Richmond, 'where they have him in the old blue and buff.  He belonged to his country—heart, soul and body, and I
         don't want any other country to have any part of him—not even his clothes.'  The American Horatio Greenough's 1833 statue
         of Washington in a toga provoked embarrassed ridicule, an indication of the limits of classicism as a reference system in
         a Christian and increasingly democratic country" (20). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>