<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00001</field>
      <field name="title">Rachel Ray</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">fiction</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">radicalism</field>
      <field name="topic">rev1848</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="text">CHAPTER XI.Cornbury Grange.But Rowan was a man more thoughtful than Cornbury, and was specially thoughtful as to
         his own position. He was a radical at heart if ever there was a radical. But in saying
         this I must beg my reader to understand that a radical is not necessarily a
         revolutionist or even a republican. He does not, by reason of his social or political
         radicalism, desire the ruin of thrones, the degradation of nobles, the spoliation of the
         rich, or even the downfall of the bench of bishops. Many a young man is frightened away
         from the just conclusions of his mind and the strong convictions of his heart by dread
         of being classed with those who are jealous of the favoured ones of fortune. A radical
         may be as ready as any aristocrat to support the crown with his blood, and the church
         with his faith. It is in this that he is a radical; that he desires, expects, works for,
         and believes in, the gradual progress of the people. No doctrine of equality is his.
         Liberty he must have, and such position, high or low, for himself and others, as each
         man's individual merits will achieve for him. The doctrine of outward equality he
         eschews as a barrier to all ambition, and to all improvement. The idea is as mean as the
         thing is impracticable. But within,—is it in his soul or in his
         heart?—within his breast there is a manhood that will own no inferiority to
         the manhood of another. He retires to a corner that an earl with his suite may pass
         proudly through the doorway, and he grudges the earl nothing of his pride. It is the
         earl's right. But he also has his right; and neither queen, nor earl, nor people shall
         invade it. That is the creed of a radical. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>