<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00058</field>
      <field name="title">Letter to Edward Coles</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">americanrevolution</field>
      <field name="topic">jefferson</field>
      <field name="text">To Edward ColesMonticello, August 25, '14Dear Sir,Your favour of July 31, was duly received, and was read with peculiar pleasure.
         The sentiments breathed through the whole do honor to both the head and heart of the writer.  Mine on the subject of slavery
         of negroes have long since been in possession of the public, and time has only served to give them stronger root.  The love
         of justice and love of country plead equally the cause of these people, and it is a moral reproach to us that they should
         have pleaded it so long in vain, and should have produced not a single effort, nay I fear not much serious willingness to
         relieve them &amp; ourselves from our present condition of moral &amp; political reprobation.  From those of the former generation
         who were in the fulness of age when I came into public life, which was while our controversy with England was on paper only,
         I soon saw that nothing was to be hoped.  Nursed and educated in the daily habit of seeing the degraded condition, both bodily
         and mental, of those unfortunate beings, not reflecting that that degradation was very much the work of themselves &amp; their
         fathers, few minds have yet doubted but that they were as legitimate subjects of property as their horses and cattle.  The
         quiet and monotonous course of colonial life has been distributed by no alarm, and little reflection on the value of liberty.
         And when alarm was taken at an enterprize on their own, it was not easy to carry them to the whole length of the principles
         which they invoked for themselves.  In the first or second session of the Legislature after I became a member, I drew to this
         subject the attention of Col. Bland, one of the oldest, ablest, &amp; most respected members, and he undertook to move for certain
         moderate extensions of the protection of the laws to these people.  I seconded his motion, and, as a younger member, was more
         spared in the debate; but he was denounced as an enemy of his country, &amp; was treated with the grossest indecorum.  From an
         early stage of our revolution other &amp; more distant duties were assigned to me, so that from that time till my return from
         Europe in 1789, and I may say till I returned to reside at home in 1809, I had little opportunity of knowing the progress
         of public sentiment here on this subject.  I had always hoped that the younger generation receiving their early impressions
         after the flame of liberty had been kindled in every breast, &amp; had become as it were the vital spirit of every American, that
         the generous temperment of youth, analogous to the motion of their blood, and above the suggestions of avarice, would have
         sympathized with oppression whereever found, and proved their love of liberty beyond their own share of it.  But my intercourse
         with them, since my return has not been sufficient to ascertain that they had made towards this point the progress I had hoped.
         Your solitary but welcome voice is the first which has brought this sound to my ear; and I have considered the general silence
         which prevails on this subject as indicating an apathy unfavorable to every hope.  Yet the hour of emancipation is advancing,
         in the march of time.... 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>