<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00062</field>
      <field name="title">Selections from The Complete Poetical Works of William Wordsworth</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">british</field>
      <field name="topic">napoleon</field>
      <field name="topic">switzerland</field>
      <field name="text">Calais, August, 1802.Is it a Reed that's shaken by the wind,Or what is it that ye go forth to see?Lords, Lawyers, Statesmen,
         Squires of low degree,Men known, and men unknown, Sick, Lame, and Blind,Post forward all, like Creatures of one kind,With
         first-fruit offerings crowd to bend the kneeIn France, before the new-born Majesty.'T is ever thus.  Ye men of prostrate mind!A
         seemly reverence may be paid to power;But that's a loyal virtue never sownIn haste, nor springing with a transient shower:When
         truth, when sense, when liberty were flown,What hardship had it been to wait an hour?Shame on you, feeble Heads, to slavery
         prone!Thought of a Briton on the Subjugation of SwitzerlandTwo Voices are there; one is of the Sea,One of the Mountains; each
         a mighty Voice:In both from age to age Thou didst rejoice,They were thy chosen Music, Liberty!There came a Tyrant, and with
         holy gleeThou fought'st against Him; but has vainly strivenThou from thy Alpine holds at length art driven,Where not a torrent
         murmurs heard by thee.Of one deep bliss thine ear hath been bereft:Then cleave, O cleave to that which still is left;For,
         high-souled Maid, what sorrow would it beThat mountain Floods should thunder as before,And Ocean bellow from his rocky shore,And
         neither awful Voice be heard by thee!It is not to be though of that the FloodOf British freedom, which to the open SeaOf the
         world's praise from dark antiquityHath flowed, "with pomp of waters unwithstood,"Roused though it be full often to a moodWhich
         spurns the check of salutary bands,That this most famous Stream in Bogs and SandsShould perish; and to evil and to goodBe
         lost for ever.  In our Halls is hungArmoury of the invincible Knights of old:We must be free or die, who speak the tongueThat
         Shakespeare spake; the faith and morals holdWhich Milton held.—In every thing we are sprungOf Earth's first blood, have titles
         manifold.October, 1803.One might believe that natural miseriesHad blasted France and made of it a landUnfit for men; and that
         in one great BandHer sons were bursting forth to dwell at ease.But 't is a chosen soil, where sun and breezeShed gentle favors;
         rural works are there;And ordinary business without care!Spot rich in all things that can soothe and please!How piteous then
         that there should be such dearthOf knowledge; that whole myriads should uniteTo work against themselves such fell despite:Should
         come in phrensy and in drunken mirth,Impatient to put out the only lightOf Liberty that yet remains on Earth!Advance—come
         forth from thy Tyrolean ground,Dear Liberty! stern Nymph of soul untamed,Sweet Nymph, O rightly of the mountains named!Through
         the long chain of Alps from mound to moundAnd o'er the eternal snows, like Echo, bound,—Like Echo, when the Hunter-train at
         dawnHave roused her from her sleep: and forest-lawn,Cliffs, woods, and caves, her viewless steps resoundAnd babble of her
         pastime!—On, dread Power!With such invisible motion speed thy flight,Through hanging clouds, from craggy height to height,Through
         the green vales and through the Herdsman's bower,That all the Alps may gladden in thy might,Here, there, and in all places
         at one hour.The Oak of Guernica—1810.The ancient oak of Guernica, says Laborde in his account of Biscay, is a most venerable
         natural monument.  Ferdinand and Isabella, in the year 1476, after hearing mass in the Church of Santa Maria de la Antigua,
         repaired to this tree, under which they swore to the Biscayans to maintain their fueros (privileges.)  What other interest
         belongs to it in the minds of this People will appear from the following.Oak of Guernica!  Tree of holier powerThan that which
         in Dodona hid enshrine(So faith too fondly deemed) a voice divine,Heard from the depths of its aërial bower,How canst thou
         flourish at this blighting hour?What hope, what joy can sunshine bring to thee,Or the soft breezes from the Atlantic sea,The
         dews of morn, or April's tender shower?Stroke merciful and welcome would that beWhich should extend thy branches on the ground,If
         never more within their shady roundThose lofty-minded Lawgivers shall meet,Peasant and Lord, in their appointed seat,Guardians
         of Biscay's ancient Liberty.—1811.Here pause: the poet claims at least this praise,That virtuous Liberty hath been the scopeOf
         his pure song, which did not shrink from hopeIn the worst moment of these evil days;From hope, the paramount duty that Heaven
         lays,For its own honour, on man's suffering heart.Never may from our souls one truth depart,That an accursed thing it is to
         gazeOn prosperous Tyrants with a dazzled eye;Nor, touched with due abhorrence of their guiltFor whose dire ends tears flow,
         and blood is spilt,And justice labours in extremity,Forget thy weakness, upon which is built,O wretched Man, the Throne of
         Tyranny!"To Thee—To Thee—; from "ODE: The Morning of the Day Appointed for a General Thanksgiving, January 18, 1816."On this
         appointed day shall thanks ascend,That Thou hast brought our warfare to an end,And that we need no second victory!Ha! what
         a ghastly sight for man to see!And to the heavenly saints in peace who dwell,For a brief moment, terrible;But, to thy sovereign
         penetration, fair,Before whom all things are, that were,All judgments that have been, or e'er shall be;Links in the chain
         of thy tranquillity!Along the bosom of this favoured Nation,Breathe Thou, this day, a vital undulation!Let all who do this
         land inheritBe conscious of Thy moving spirit!Oh, 't is a goodly Ordinance,—the sight,Though sprung from bleeding war, is
         one of pure delight;Bless Thou the hour, or ere the hour arrive,When a whole people shall kneel down in prayer,And, at one
         moment, in one rapture, striveWith lip and heart to tell their gratitudeFor Thy protecting care,Their solemn joy—praising
         the Eternal LordFor tyranny subdued,And for the sway of equity renewed,For liberty confirmed, and peace restored! 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>