<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00033</field>
      <field name="title">from "John James Barralet and the Apotheosis of George Washington"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">commentary</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">americanrevolution</field>
      <field name="topic">washington</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="text">1."In January 1802 John James Barralet (ca. 1747-1815) honored the late George Washington in a commemorative engraving.  Barralet's
         engraving shows the president, dressed in grave clothes, being raised from his tomb by Immortality and the winged Father Time
         who will assist him in his ascent.  Faith, Hope, and Charity are clustered together at the far left.  Liberty, her cap atop
         a pole, and an American Indian share the lower register with two rattlesnakes and an eagle.  In the nineteenth century this
         engraving was popular enough to go through four printings, yet to most modern viewers this image is what hieroglyphics were
         to Europeans before the discovery of the Rosetta Stone:  intriuging to contemplate but indecipherable.A nineteenth century
         American populace educated in the traditions of European humanism knew how to interpret allegorical imagery.  Symbolic figures
         with references to classical antiquity or the Christian past were common.  They adorned political engravings, honorary medals,
         coins, official seals, and even the corners of maps.  Learned men expected sophisticated visual references.  The artists,
         schooled in the conventions of European humanism, acted as intermediaries to the less well educated public.  When asked to
         stage parades and festivals celebrating events of historic significance in the new republic, they often used allegorical figures
         and decorated triumphal arches with classical images" (115).2."In the last part of his career Barralet often turned to Washington
         as a subject.  It was then a common practice for engravers to copy portraits of prominent men done by other artists, and Barralet
         was no exception.  But he embellished the Washington portraits with decorations drawn from the vocabulary of forms he had
         learned in Europe.  In one Washington portrait based on miniature by Walter Robertson, Barralet's decorations consisted of
         standard classical devices like a laurel wreath, an eagle, a liberty cap balanced on the point of a sword, flags, and palm
         branches.  Another Washington engraving after a painting by Gilbert Stuart was decorated with a knight's helmet, sword, and
         baton.  To an engraving after a miniature by John Ramage he added Liberty.  She sits between an eagle and a cornucopia and
         holds her cap aloft upon the tip of her sword" (118).3."For the many allegorical devices Barralet undoubtedly referred to
         that most widely circulated of all handbooks of iconographical imagery, Cesare Ripa's Iconologia.  The Iconologia was first
         published at the end of the sixteenth century when it was widely believed that painting, like poetry, should convey complicated
         meanings.  Drawing upon sources as diverse as ancient sculpture and medals, the writings of ancient Greek and Roman authors,
         church fathers, and contemporary scholars who were attempting to decode hieroglyphics, Ripa systematized for generations of
         artists the way in which an image could represent an idea.After the publication of the Iconologia artists who chose to use
         allegorical figures had a common source.  Most artists, including Barralet, modified the source but not so much that the figures
         could not be traced back to their common ancestor.  Ripa had explained that Peace should be shown burning weapons because
         that is how she appeared on Roman coins during the Pax Romana.  In the Iconologia Peace puts her torch to the weapons and
         garb of war.  The cornucopia in her left arm speaks for the advantages of peace.  Barralet rearranged these devices.  The
         cornucopia is placed at the bottom of the steps and is protected by the eagle; the fire is confined to a brazier.  In Barralet's
         composition Washington himself is allegorized.  Washington, a personification of Love of Country, is placed in proximity to
         the weapons and a burning brazier as Ripa had suggested" (119-120).4."After the middle of the eighteenth century, however,
         some Europeans had begun questioning the validity of conveying complex meanings by the use of Ripa's allegorical garnish.
         No less preeminent a figure than the critic Johann Winckelmann signaled his exasperation:  'I am sure that if he [Ripa] had
         thought of the Italian adage pisciare nel vaglio to mean waste of time and labor, he would have expressed even this pretty
         thought through figures.'  James Barry, a history painter who, like Barralet, left Ireland to follow his profession, had a
         more emphatic way of expressing the matter:  'from the jargon of far-fetched and over refined allegory what must be said then
         of Ripa and others who have been at the pains of raking together all this offal of the imagination.'But in America artists
         faced the very immediate problem of devising a rhetorical language through imagery to proclaim the new heroes of the Revolution.
         When allegory could suggest, by effecting a thoroughgoing transformation, that antique precedent and contemporary incident
         were as one, then it was welcomed by artists.  In his generation Barralet was unusual for the number of allegorical compositions
         he designed, but he was not the only artist to design them.The climate in America could hardly have been more propitious for
         commemorating Washington's death in antique guise using allegorical figures.  When Barralet designed his engraving, he chose
         the form of the apotheosis in which a great man ascends Mount Olympus to join the pantheon of Greek gods and heroes.  To complete
         his composition, Barralet selected allegorical figures with established iconographical pedigrees:  Liberty, Father Time, Immortality,
         Faith, Hope, Charity, and the American Indian.Liberty and Father Time had roots deep in European culture.  Liberty had been
         used on the coins and medals of the Roman Empire.  Ripa, ever ready with advice for the artists of his time, had suggested
         that Liberty hold a broken yoke and be accompanied by a cat.  A cat, he pointed out, was appropriate because no other animal
         loved freedom so much.  Most artists, however, ignored Ripa; Barralet was no exception.  Barralet's Liberty merely has the
         rudis and pileus, the rod of touch and cap of announcement connected with ancient forms of freeing a slave.  Twenty years
         earlier Augustin Dupré had depicted Liberty similarly on his greatly admired Libertas Americana medal" (123).5. "The publication
         of Barralet's engraving was timed to coincide with Washington's birthday.  February 22 already had become the high water mark
         in the flow of American sentiment for Washington.  Barralet calculated accordingly:  'APOTHEOSIS OF WASHINGTON finished for
         delivery....The subscribers are respectfully informed that the proof prints will be delivered at S. Chaudron's, No. 12, South
         Third Street.  Feb. 5, dlm.'  The advertisement, which ran from Monday, February 3, through Saturday, March 6, 1802, also
         provided a description of the engraving:  'The subject—Gen. Washington raised from the Tomb, by the Poetical and Historical
         Genius, assisted by Imoortality—at his feet America weeping over his Armour, on the opposite side an Indian crouched in surly
         sorrow, in the third ground the Mental Virtues, Faith Hope and Charity.'  In this advertisement certain figures have been
         reinterpreted, probably to make them more suitable compnaions to America's prime Revolutionary hero.  The 'Poetical and Historical
         Genius' is in fact Father Time, but the former title makes him a particularly appropriate companion for Washington.  'America
         weeping' is the figure with the attributes of Liberty and probably represents both America and Liberty, as is the case in
         other contemporary engravings" (133-34). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>