<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00038</field>
      <field name="title">"The Liberty Bell"</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">poetry</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">libertybell</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">icon</field>
      <field name="text">The Liberty Bell—The Liberty Bell,The tocsin of Freedom and Slavery's knellThat a whole long year has idle hung,Again is waggin
         its clamorous tongue!As it merrily swings,Its notes it flingsOn the dreamy ear of the planters and kings,And it gives them
         a token,Of manacles broken;—And all that the prophets of Freedom have spoken.With tongues of flame,(Like those which cameOn
         the men who first spoke the Saviour's name,)Comes over their soulAs death-bells knowl,Or the wheels of coming thunder roll!Our
         Liberty Bell—They know it well,The tocsin of Freedom and Slavery's knell!Our Liberty Bell! let its startling toneAbroad o'er
         a slavish land be thrown!Nay, on the wings of the North-East wind,Let it reach the isles of the Western Ind—Those isles of
         the sunWhere the work is doneThat, here at the North, is but just begun.Let the Bell be swung,Till old and young,That dwell
         New England's hills among,Shall wake at the peal,And, with holy zeal,Beside their mountain altars kneel,And pray that the
         yokeFrom the necks may be brokeOf the millions who feel the "continual stroke"Of the despot's rod;And that Earth's green sodNo
         more by the foot of a slave may be trod.Let the Liberty Bell ring out—ring out!And let freedom reply with a thundering shout,That
         the gory scourges and clanking chains,That blast the beauty of Southern plains,Shall be stamped in the dust;—And that thrice-gorged
         Lust,That gloats on his helpless bond-slave's bust,Ere long shall seeThat slave set free,And joining in Liberty's Jubilee.That
         Jubilee song!"O Lord, how long"Must the world yet wait for that Jubilee song?Yet, come it must;Jehovah is just,And his Truth
         and his Spirit we cheerfully trust.That truth to tellComes the Liberty Bell,And that spirit shall make it strike Slavery's
         knell.Our Liberty Bell! let its solemn chimeFall on the ear of hoary Time,As onward—onward to its goalHe sees the chariot
         of Liberty roll;While, with shout and song,The swelling throngOf the friends of the bondman urge it along.Let the same chime
         fallOn the ears of all,Who tread on the neck of the negro thrall,Till they start from the ground,As they will at the soundWhen
         the trumpets of angels are pealing around.And the murdered slaveComes forth from his grave,And smiles at the flash of th'Avenger's
         glaive,And the world shall accordIn the righteous awardTo both tyrant and slave, in that day of the Lord. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>