<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">lby.00055</field>
      <field name="title">Twenty-Two Years a Slave and Forty Years a Freeman</field>
      <field name="project">liberty</field>
      <field name="genre">history</field>
      <field name="place">american</field>
      <field name="topic">emancipation</field>
      <field name="topic">dissenting</field>
      <field name="text">Just before the time appointed for me to meet Mr. Moore, a slave girl named Milly, came secretly to Bath.  She had been one
         of Capt. Helm's slaves, and he had a while before sold her to a man who lived some distance west of the village.  Milly had
         now taken the matter into her own hands.  She had left her master to take care of himself, and was in short, "running away,"
         determined as myself, that she would be a slave no longer; resolved on death, or freedom from the power of the slaveholder.The
         time I had set for my departure was so near at hand, that I concluded to accompany her in her flight.  When the dark night
         came on, we started together, and traveled all night, and just as the day dawned we arrived at Manchester, where we stopped
         a short time with one Thomas Watkins.But I was not to be let go so easily.  I had been missed at Capt. Helm's, and several
         men started immediate pursuit.  I was weary, and so intent on getting a little rest that I did not see my pursuers until they
         had well nigh reached the house where I was; but I did see them in time to spring from the house with the agility of a deer,
         and to run for the woods as for life. And indeed, I so considered it.  I was unarmed to be sure, and not prepared to defend
         myself against two or three men, armed to the teeth; but it would have gone hard with me before I surrendered myself to them,
         after having dreamed as I had, and anticipated the blessings of a free man.  I escaped them, thank God, and reached the woods,
         where I concealed myself for some time, and where I had ample opportunity to reflect on the injustice and cruelty of my oppressors,
         and to ask myself why it was that I was obliged to fly from my home.  Why was I there panting and weary, hungry and destitute—skulking
         in the woods like a thief, and concealing myself like a murderer?  What had I done?  For what fault, or for what crime was
         I pursued by armed men, and hunted like a beast of prey?  God only knows how these inquiries harrowed up my very soul, and
         made me well nigh doubt the justice and mercy of the Almighty, until I remembered my narrow escape, when my doubts dissolved
         in grateful tears.But why, oh why, had I been forced to flee thus from my fellow men?  I was guilty of no crime; I had committed
         no violence; I had broken no law of the land; I was not charged even with a fault, except of the love of liberty and a desire
         to be free!  I had claimed the right to possess my own person, and remove it from oppression.  Oh my God, thought I, can the
         American People, who at this very hour are pouring out their blood in defence of their country's liberty; offering up as a
         sacrifice on the battle field their promising young men, to preserve their land and hearthstones from English oppression;
         can they, will they, continue to hunt the poor African slave from their soil because he desires that same liberty, so dear
         to the heart of every American citizen?  Will they not blot out from their fair escutcheon the foul stain which Slavery has
         cast upon it?  Will they not remember the Southern bondman, in whom the love of freedom is as inherent as in themselves, and
         will they not, when contending for equal rights, use their mighty forces "to break every yoke, and let the oppressed go free?"
         God grant that it may be so! 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>