<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00066">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"The Woman in Black"</title>
		<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00066</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 12 of the May 11, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
               <title level="a">The Woman in Black</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
May 11, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="beechertilton">Beecher-Tilton</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>


         <head>The Woman in Black</head>
		
<head>A Mysterious Female who Wanted to Argue a Point with Beecher</head>


         <p>A matronly woman about thirty-five
years old, with glossy curls falling over her shoulder, wrapped a light mantle
about her in the Plymouth lecture room a few nights since and took a seat in
the front row, right under Henry Ward Beecher's shadow. She was neatly dressed
in black alpaca, with lace ruffles at her throat and at her wrists, and her
hands were clothed with a fresh pair of black kids. She was a stranger, and her
bold advance into a section of the room reserved by custom for those who bask
in Mr. Beecher's radiance attracted attention. Mr. Beecher strode leisurely in
as though feeling a touch of spring fever, looked nervously at a quadrilateral
made of gas pipes, erected for private exhibition, and turned for comfort to the basket of flowers that a lady had sent for his table. When
Dr. Edward Beecher prayed he referred to the fact that the church was
surrounded by malign enemies and yet had as companions a legion of angels of
light. The woman in black arose, tiptoed so close to him that her drapery
almost brushed him, and passed down the aisle to the rear door. When Mr.
Beecher began to talk, she tiptoed her way back, took her seat leisurely, folded
her arms, and fixed her black eyes intently on Mr. Beecher.</p>

         <p>The talk was about the requisites of a Christian life, his
argument being that it was only necessary to dedicate oneself to Christ as Master.
He said: "Will you make your whole life amenable to the commands of Christ? That
is the simple question."</p>


         <p>The woman in black leaned forward,
her black eyes glistening with excitement, and said in a shrill voice, "Will
you let a woman answer it?"</p>


         <p>"When I get through, if it is
proper, you may," said Mr. Beecher.</p>


         <p>"Oh, excuse me. I thought you would
hear me now," continued the woman.</p>


         <p>Mr. Beecher was embarrassed, but he
did not lose possession of his idea for a minute, and rattled on, amplifying
the argument and picturing it with a quaint illustration. The woman in black
eyed him, with a derisive smile on her face, and she seemed to be intently
anxious to get an opportunity to give her views. Mr. Beecher said that a man
became a Christian as soon as he accepted the Master hand of the Lord Jesus
Christ, and promised that he would hereafter conform his life to Christ's life
and his spirit to Christ's spirit. The woman in black laughed, showing her
pearly teeth, and turned for sympathy to her neighbors, but they stared at her in surprise.</p>

         <p>As soon as Mr. Beecher ceased to
talk, the lady threw her mantle back, and prepared to respond to Mr. Beecher's
expected invitation to speak. The invitation didn't come. Mr. Beecher gave out
"Nearer my God to thee," and the black-robed woman waved her head, keeping time
with the pianist's prelude, but kept her eyes riveted on Mr. Beecher, whose gaze
was lost in the Plymouth collection. The sardonic smile on the face of the
woman in black suddenly changed to an angry pout as the benediction was
pronounced. She didn't bow her bead as Mr. Beecher implored "Grace, mercy, and
peace," and glared at him defiantly. As he closed she pounced over to the
reporters and said excitedly: "I will answer him yet. He has his platform; I
will have mine. He refused to hear me tonight, but he must hear me some time.
He has crucified me here."</p>


         <p>She sat down with as much energy as
she had got up, pulled on her over-shoes, and hastened out, muttering angrily
all the way.</p>


         <p>The Examining Committee remained to
receive applications for membership in Plymouth Church. Mr. S. V. White said
that the committee had not yet received any charges against Mrs. Tilton, and he
did not know that any were to be prefereed. Three persons out of every four believed
that Mrs. Tilton was crazy, and it was a forgone conclusion that she must leave
the church. Some way would be adopted to get her out of the church with as
little excitement as possible, but it was undisputed that she must go.</p>

         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00003" type="same subject"/></item>
               	<item><xptr n="ls.00014" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00021" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
	
			<item><xptr n="ls.00040" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00046" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>