<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00022">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"Dayton's Devilment"
</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00022</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 3 of the April 27, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Dayton's Devilment</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
April 27, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="boudoir" type="setting">boudoir</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>DAYTON'S DEVILMENT</head>

	<head>The Striking Escapade of a Family Physician who had Seduced the Wife of a Prominent Citizen</head>
	<head>A STRANGE INFATUATION</head>

            
         <p>Dayton, O., April 13 &#8212; Social circles here &#8212;indeed, I may say the entire community &#8212; are just now agog over the most
sensational bit of scandal with which Dayton has been visited for years.
Indeed, I hesitate to name it "scandal," for to the average newspaper reader
the word conveys an idea associated with the every-day-occurring cases of <hi rend="italic">crim.
con., </hi>of double guilt and blame, and of equal shame and perfidy, bad enough
in themselves, but frequently with an equally-divided burden of guilt. These,
indeed, are sufficiently painful, and worthy of all execrations heaped upon
them all in hideous fiendishness, in studied treachery, in long and carefully
laid plans for the overthrow of trusting virtue, and the destruction of a happy
home, into which the temper has been admitted in the most sacred relations
which our social system recognizes, is this one.</p>

         <p>A happy home; a beautiful, affectionate, honored
wife; a trusting adoring husband; a family physician at once as devoid of
principle and as full of cunning as the serpent, a course of treatment for
years with this seeming end in view, a fall beyond comprehension to the fallen
one, yet a fall which shattered at once the sacred altars of the most sacred
home, and shakes to the foundation those of many others of our beautiful city,
carrying surprise and pain and grief and agony to scores of homes and to hundreds
of hearts among the relatives and friends and intimate associates in the best
walks of life. Of the characters in this eventful drama the chief are Dr.
Joseph E. Lowes, a prominent physician to the best families here, and a
well-known local politician in the Republican ranks, and Mrs. Wm. Hoglen, the
beautiful and till now universally respected wife of a worthy and honored
citizen. Both parties have until now stood well in the community, both were
looked upon as people of education and refinement, and both were recognized as
belonging to the wealthier class, not the wealthiest, but counting their
possessions well up in the thousands, and able to surround themselves with all
the comforts and luxuries which make life pleasant, and betokened a career of
honor and usefulness in society.</p>

         <p>Dr. Lowes, the betrayer, the outrager, for I can
scarcely honor him with the name of seducer &#8212; has been resident of this city
for some ten years, and by a practice of his profession, coupled with an almost
penurious frugality, has accumulated probably $25,000. He is a tall,
finely-built man of thirty-five, with black, glossy, curling hair, a full black
beard, a commanding presence and a nature magnetic to a degree which makes him
at once dangerous and all powerful.  He came here, a single man, from Canada, married a
respectable widow of this place, and, in turn, a few years later became a
widower. He is of the Homeopathic school, so popular here, a member of the
Montgomery County Homeopathic Medical Society, an active member in the School
Board, and surgeon, with rank of major, in the Fourth Regiment Ohio National
Guards.</p>

         <p>Mrs. Hoglen, the victim, is the wife of William
Hoglen, of a well-known firm of this place, with her husband a native of this
city, and of its most respected families. She is a daughter of Mr. Richard
Chambers, a retired contractor, well known and universally respected. She is
described as a beautiful blonde, of twenty-six, with luxuriant golden hair,
large, dreamy blue eyes, a petite and perfect figure, faultless in face and in
manner, and of the most modest and at once lovable and loving disposition.
Naturally retiring, and yet with all those womanly graces which words cannot
describe, she was honored, respected and admired of all, blushing like a school-girl
when spoken to, and yet firm and noble in her womanhood and in Christian
graces.</p>

         <p>She was an honored member of the Methodist church, of which
her husband was a pillar, and until within the past few months, the period
covered by her shame, a constant attendant upon its services. She was the
mother of three beautiful children, and up to the present time had been
regarded as the most affectionate and dutiful of wives and loving mother. Some
years since she was troubled with an affection peculiar to her sex, and, after
employing various physicians to no purpose, Dr. Lowes was called in and, giving
some assurances of successful treatment, was continued. His visits and
attentions continued during three years, the husband paying him large sums of
money for his alleged services, but the wife continuing an invalid. About a
year ago the brothers of the husband became convinced that the Doctor's
intentions were not of a proper nature, and not only discharged him from
service in their families, but endeavored to bring, by indirect means, the
husband to see the true tendency of his influence. With an unbounded
confidence and earnest love for his beautiful wife, however, he continued
without the slightest suspicion of the facts, even up to last Tuesday evening,
when the cloud, which had been gathering for an entire year, burst in untold
violence upon his devoted head. More recently, however, the true state of
affairs became so plainly visible that the brothers determined that they must
be brought to the knowledge of the husband. Meanwhile one of them had visited
the Doctor and ordered him to discontinue his visits, which he promised to do
unless called on professionally. A few days ago, however, the intimacy
continuing, the brothers, three of them, aided by the servant girl employed in
the house and that of one of the brothers, devised a plan to bring the facts to
the knowledge of the trusting but now cruelly wronged husband.  He was requested by them to go to a certain point, a day's
travel from Dayton, on business, and after remaining there one day to
accomplish the business, he would be able to return. He therefore informed his
wife that he would be absent three days, and left on Monday morning. They
then, by means not necessary to detail, caused information to reach the Doctor
that the husband would be absent until Wednesday.</p>

         <p>The game worked well and by Monday night they
were sure that the Doctor would pay his visit on Tuesday night. They then
brought the husband back to Dayton by telegraph order, he arriving here on the
six o'clock train. By various pretexts he was detained at the office until the
pear was ripe. The servant girl had been instructed to lock all the doors to
prevent the game from escaping and take the keys away with her. Mrs. Hoglen, however,
insisted upon one key being left with her, and so there remained one way of
egress. By 10 o'clock the game was safely in cover, and the signal was given
to the brothers that everything was ready. Here they dropped their business
conversation with the unsuspecting William, telling him he had better go home
to his family, and bidding him good night sent him homeward, themselves
following unobserved to see the denouement. Meanwhile the servants, who, to
their credit be it said acted their parts heroically, had slipped into the
house, and listening in the hall overheard indistinctly a conversation between
the Doctor and his victim in her bedroom in the second story. When, however,
the husband came, suspecting nothing, he opened and shut the gate with some
little noise, the tell-tale sounds giving warning to the guilty couple
overhead, the servants heard a shuffling sound, which told them that the Doctor
was getting himself out of the way into another room. By the time the husband
entered, however, this was accomplished, and when he entered his wife's room he
found everything in apparent order, and his pretty little wife waiting to
receive him. Only one thing did he notice, and that was a sumptuous lunch,
with wines and other delicacies, set upon a sideboard at hand. To his question
of this, however, his wife replied that she had had it there for herself in the
afternoon, and not yet had it removed. Thus satisfied, and thoroughly tired
out with his two days' travel, he retired soon after. During the interval the
servant had slipped out and acquainted the brothers, who were waiting, with the
condition of the affairs, and told them that she was sure the Doctor was
secreted in a room adjoining that occupied by the unsuspecting Hoglen and his
faithless wife. Then it was decided &#8212; for it was determined by the brothers
that William should have proof for himself and make his own discoveries &#8212; that
the girl should go to the room and after discovering the Doctor, scream for
help, thus bringing the husband before he could escape.</p>

         <p>This plan was faithfully carried out. Taking a lamp in her
hand, as if about to retire, she walked boldly up-stairs straight to the
suspected room, and threw open the door.</p>

         <p>At first she saw nothing, and for the moment was
led to believe that the bird had flown. A littler closer examination, however,
convinced her that she was right, for lying on the floor near some clothing
hung against the wall lay his boots. Looking still further she saw the
Doctor's feet and the bottom of his pants showing below the skirts of a dress
hung against the wall. He had slipped into the dress, or behind it, in his
efforts to get out of sight, and there stood trembling yet hoping that he would
not be discovered. With a presence of mind worthy the sterner sex she
retreated to the door, and giving a piercing scream, called to Mr. Hoglen to
come quick &#8212; that there was a man in the house. Hoglen, who is a
broad-shouldered, muscular fellow, jumped from his bed, and with no weapon but
his arms and the scant apparel of the night, rushed into the hall.</p>

         <p> At this the doctor sprang from under the dress and flew
toward the door, boots in hand. He was caught by the plucky servant girl, but,
breaking away from her, ran, or almost flew, down-stairs, with Hoglen, who yet
supposed the "man" was simply a burglar. As the Doctor reached the foot of the
stairs the second servant was waiting, and, with wipe-spread arms, attempted to
check him, but he valiantly, seeing the situation, struck him a heavy blow on
the head with his boots, which he still held in his hand, and passed on, with
Hoglen in pursuit, but a few steps behind. As Hoglen passed the girl she said
to him: "It's Dr. Lowes."</p>

         <p>These words were like magic to him, and changed
him in a twinkling from a thief-catcher into an enraged husband in pursuit of
the villain who had robbed him of the most sacred thing on earth, the love and
honor of his wife. "In an instant," he says, "I understood all. The mysteries
of the past year not understood, but unsuspected in this light, became clear to
me."</p>

         <p>Meanwhile, the Doctor found himself locked in,
and was vainly rushing from one door to another to get out. The plucky servant
girl, after receiving the blow, had retreated into the single room from which
there was a means of exit, and, locking the hall door behind her, cut off that
last hope. All this took but an instant, and before Lowes had tried the third
door the wronged husband was upon him. The struggle was short, sharp and
decisive. Lowes, though a large man, was unable to cope with the strong arms
of the maddened husband, and a moment later Hoglen had him by the throat and
was slowly choking the life out of his miserable carcass. His black,
glistening, snaky eyes started from their sockets, his tongue protruded, his face
became discolored, and he sunk to the floor almost insensible, when the wife
rushed in between them and saved the husband from murder and the seducer from the fate he so richly deserved.</p>

                  <p>By this time the brothers had entered, when she attacked
them, fiercely charging them with having set the job up to catch her. The
husband, too requested them to withdraw, stating that he was able to settle
with Dr. Lowes, and started up stairs, evidently to obtain his revolver, to
make short work of the affair, but on returning he found that he had escaped
through a rear window, which had been unhappily left unguarded. The escape and
location were alike fortunate for the Doctor, but unfortunate for the
community, for had he not been killed by the outraged husband, he would I am
told, have surely been so attended by the brothers, that he would have been
forevermore harmless in families of even the most easy virtue. The brothers
were determined and desparate, and it is only through the lucky chance that
they had forgotten the back window that this admirable "family physician" now
retains his evidences of manhood.</p>

         <p>The wife was at first defiant, and seemed, as
she had appeared for months past, laboring under some strange influence, as if
the victim of some baneful drug. Finally, however, she broke down and
confessed all.</p>

         <p>She stated that this unholy intimacy had been
going on for months; she knew not how long. She said that some time last fall
she felt that she was completely in his power, and struggle against it as she would
she could not avoid his influence. The medicine which he gave her, her friends
say, served to act upon her as strange and terrible drugs affect the person;
she was wretched without them, and more strange and unaccountable in her
actions when she had them. The opinion is freely expressed by Mr. Hoglen's
brothers that she was drugged, both to produce this effect and to continue the
alleged "disease" for which he was treating her. As if to add the last strokes
to the wrongs and to further his hellish designs, it is stated that the Doctor
had positively forbidden the husband to have intercourse with her, stating that
her health would not admit of it, and had by other means striven to alienate
the affections of each from the other.</p>

         <p>This, it is stated, is by no means the first of
this admirable family physician's liasons.  It is stated by a prominent and reliable young man in a
position to know that crimes of this nature have been frequently committed by
the Doctor in his office with both married and unmarried females, and that but
for his interference it would have occurred oftener. The wife has been sent
home to her father's house by the husband, and is still there with her
children. She is in an agony of repentance and grief indescribable. The husband
has sold his entire business interest and other property here and is preparing
to leave, to go he knows not where. He is broken down by his sorrow.</p>

         <p>It is rumored that there are prospects of legal
proceedings, and, if the theories advanced by the family can be sustained,
there seems reason to believe that a term in the Ohio penitentiary awaits the
Doctor. It is said that he now makes no defense, scarcely denying the
accusation.</p>

         <p>Public opinion is almost entirely against him,
and it is stated that he will be asked to resign his position as School Trustee
and as officer of the Fourth Regiment.</p>

         <p>The Doctor, it is stated by Mr. Hoglen's family,
has already so far confessed his crime as to send a mutual acquaintance with an
offer to compromise by a payment of money, but this offer of course, was
rejected. The affair has created a profound sensation, such as Dayton has not experienced for many years.</p>

         <p>It is said that Dr. Lowes is offering his
property for sale, and is preparing to leave town, on account of the developments
of the last few days.</p>

         <p>The name of the two girls who so heroically
aided in arranging and carrying out the plan, by which the master was brought
to light, are Katie Brunkmeyer and Katie Schrillhamer. They should have a
monument.</p>

         <p>Should the intention of the relatives be carried
out, and Lowes be prosecuted and sent to the penitentiary, I can almost wish
that Deputy Dean were again there to try his hand upon this individual for a
few consecutive months. </p>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>