<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00049">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"Plump, Pretty and Pious"

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00049</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 3 of the May 11, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Plump, Pretty and Pious</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
May 11, 1878   

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>AND ANOTHER</head>


	<head>Which is From the Very Quiet and Moral Little Town of Oxford, Ohio, and of Course she is</head>

	<head>PLUMP, PRETTY AND PIOUS</head>

	<head>He Doesn't Pan Out Much on the First, But Then he is Awfully Pious and so Respectable</head>

	<head>BUT&#8212;THEY ALL DO IT</head>

            
         <p>Oxford, O., May 1&#8212;Some months ago it was
rumored that a well-known young unmarried lady of this place, whose family
connections were of a high social standing, was <hi rend="italic">enceinte.</hi> This was only
known to a few, and by them kept from becoming general. In fact, when the
truth became known last Friday week that she had given birth to a fine,
bouncing girl baby weighing twelve pounds, it fell like a thunderbolt upon the
masses of the good villagers. The young lady upon whom this misfortune fell is
one Mary E. Morris, a lady of twenty five years of age, and the daughter of the
late Mr. Morris, who died some five years ago, leaving a wife and six children,
all of whom are living. No sooner had the fact become known that Miss Mary had
given birth to an illegitimate child than people began to make inquiry as to
who the father was. In this promiscuous casting about for the male parent a
rumor was set afloat that Dr. Hill, a man of high respectability, of good
report, a member and an officer in the Presbyterian Church, married, with a
grown family, was the responsible party and the father of the child. No sooner
had it reached his ears than he pronounced it a base falsehood, and, calling a
meeting of the Session of the Church, demanded a full and public
investigation. The Session was called, and he, being stated clerk of the same
refused to act as such, when another member was elected to fill his place. A
committee was then appointed, consisting of Rev. Dr. Robert D. Morris, an uncle
of the unfortunate girl, and Rev. F.M. Wood, pastor of the Presbyterian Church,
to visit the lady and ascertain who was the father of the child, Miss Mary
Morris is also a member of the Presbyterian Church, but not what they call an
active member&#8212;taking no part in the Sunday school work and but rarely
attending church. The above committee, on Friday, April 17th,
waited upon Miss Morris, and took with them Professor R.H. Bishop, a Notary
Public, at which time she made the following affidavit, which exonerates Dr.
Hill and charges the parentage of the child upon one R.A. Morten, a young man of twenty:</p>

	<text type="correspondence">
		<body>
		<opener>"State of Ohio, County of Butler, ss.:</opener>

         <p>"Before me, R.H. Bishop, a Notary Public in and
for said county, personally came Mary E. Morris, of the village of Oxford, in
said county and state, who, being by me duly sworn, deposes and says that she
is now pregnant, and that she became so in or about the third week in July
last; that the father of the unborn child is R.A. Morten jun., of said village
of Oxford, and that neither previous to nor since the time mentioned above has
she had sexual intercourse with any man, except the said R.A. Morten jun., and
further this deponent saith not.</p>

         <closer>"Mary E. Morris"</closer>

         <closer>"Witness: F.M. Woodward and R.D. Morris."</closer>

         <closer>"Sworn to and subscribed before me this 17th
day of April, A.D. 1878.         R.H. Bishop."</closer>

         <closer>"[seal] Notary Public for Butler County Ohio."</closer>

		</body>
		</text>

         <p>This affidavit was presented to a meeting of the
Session as exonerating Dr. Hill from the charges and rumors connecting his name
with being the father of the child.</p>

         <p>Morten jun., the young man whom the parentage of
the child has been sworn by Miss Morris, is the son of R.A. Morten, a farmer
living just on the outskirts of the village and is only twenty years of age.
He is emphatic in his denial of being its father. He says he has often called
upon Miss Mary's sister, but not upon her. That some two weeks before the
birth of the child a friend came to him and told him of the condition of Miss
Mary, and as he had been calling at the house, there were rumors afloat that he
was the father. He says that on the same day he called at her house, when she
met him at the door; that they went into the house where he told her what had
been said, and wanted to know if it was true she was reporting him to be the
father; that she said, "No, your name will be the last mentioned in this
affair." He said that he then went away, thinking it was all right. As soon
as the affidavit was made laying the charge to him, Revs. Morris and Wood called
upon R.A. Morten, sen., and informed him of the fact. Mr. Morten went out to
where his son was working and told him of the affidavit, when the son assured
him he was not guilty, and Morten, sen., returned and informed the gentlemen
that he believed his son innocent, and would fight it out to the bitter end.  The son then went before a Notary Public, and made the
following counter affidavit, which, together with a statement from his father
will be laid before the meeting of the session tomorrow.</p>

	<text type="correspondence">
		<body>
		
         <opener>"State of Ohio, Butler county, ss:</opener>

         <p>"Before me, R.H. Bishop, a Notary Public in and
for said county and state, personally came R.A. Morten, jun., aged twenty
years, who made the solemn oath that he had been credibly informed that one
Mary Morris had made affidavit charging him, the said R.A. Morten, jun., with
being the father of her unborn child; and this affiant further testifies that
he is not the father of said Mary Morris' unborn child nor any other child,
born or unborn; and, further, that he never at any time or place had sexual
intercourse with the said Mary Morris.</p>
<closer>R.A. Morten, Jun.</closer>

         <closer>"Sworn to and subscribed before me this 19th day
of April, A.D. 1878.    R.H. Bishop</closer>

         <closer>"Notary Public Butler county."</closer>
		</body>
		</text>

         <p>The father of young Morten is deeply impressed
with the truth of his son's assertion of his innocence, and proposes to see him
through, as he calls it. He is a well-preserved man of seventy-eight years of
age, and is highly respected by all who know him. He was formerly resident of Carthage, of which village he was at one time mayor. The following is his statement
submitted in writing to the session.  </p>

         <p>"I knew nothing about the Dr. Hill slander until
I was visited by Rev. Dr. Robert Morris and Rev. Mr. Wood, Wednesday afternoon,
April 17, 1878, who gave me the astounding information that Miss Morris had
made solemn oath in which she charges my son, R.A. Morten, jun., with being the
father of her unborn child, and that she further states under oath that said
unborn child was begotten at the house of Mrs. Ray in July last, while Mrs. Ray
was at Connersville. The said Mary Morris was keeping house and taking care of
her (Mrs. Ray's) children during her absence. And Mr. Wood further stated that
Dr. Hill was charged with it, and that he (Dr. Hill) would not go himself, but
got Mr. Furgerson, Miss Morris' grandfather, to get her affidavit to clear him of this charge.  Miss Ray says that she was not away from home in July, but
in September she went to Connersville, Ind., to a county fair at said place.</p>

         <p>Mr. Morten, sen., says that, if necessary, the
above statement can be proven by members of their own church.</p>

         <p>A call was made upon a near relative of the
unfortunate lady, who was loath to talk about the matter. He said the young
lady's mother was suffering most keenly from her daughter's disgrace, and that
he was afraid her health and mind were affected beyond recovery; that they were
in needy circumstances, and that since the death of her husband he had been
supporting them; that whoever the guilty party was he should have manliness
enough about him to come forward and offer them some assistance in this great
trial. To the question as to whether any lawsuits would grow out of the
affair, he said no, he thought there would not, as he should oppose anything of
the kind. The affair is the topic of conversation in the village, and, of
course, both sides have ardent friends and defenders, and a few there are who
deeply sympathize with the unfortunate girl, while all do so for the stricken
mother of the erring woman, whose downfall may bring her mother to an early
death. There are all kinds of stories afloat of how certain parties had been
followed after night and seen entering the lady's house, and that said parties
were married men, etc., but how much truth there may be in them one cannot
tell. It is expected the church investigation, if not a sham, gotten up to
whitewash some one, will prove or disprove the many and damaging stories
connecting a certain party's name with the scandal.</p>

         <p>In conversation with Miss Morris' relative, a
gentleman, he said that young Morten visited Miss Mary about two weeks before
her confinement and told her that he would not desert her but see her safely
through her trouble, and told her she should not want for anything. </p>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>