<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00079">
   <teiHeader>


<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Sex Scandal: The Private Parts of Victorian Fiction</hi>
</title>
		<title level="c" type="chapter">Chapter 1, "Sex, Scandal, and the Novel"</title>
		<date type="original" value="1996">1996</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author name="Cohen">William A. Cohen
</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00079</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 2-3, 6-7, 16-19 of <hi rend="italic">Sex Scandal: The Private Parts of Victorian Fiction</hi>.  Published by Duke University Press, 1996.
. -->

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>



<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter 1, "Sex, Scandal, and the Novel"</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Sex Scandal: The Private Parts of Victorian Fiction</hi>
</title>
               <author>William A. Cohen</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Duke University Press

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Durham and London

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1996

</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
0822319563

</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
<term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
<term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
<term id="courtship" type="theme">courtship</term>
<term id="fictioninpress">fiction in press</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-08-18">18 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>



<change>
            <date value="2005-03-022">22 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>preliminary coding and edit</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
<div>
                     <head>1. </head><p>
"Sexual unspeakability does not function simply as
a collection of prohibitions in Victorian writers. Rather, it affords them
abundant opportunities to develop elaborate discourse&#8212;richly ambiguous,
subtly coded, prolix and polyvalent&#8212;that we now recognize and designate by
the very term <hi rend="italic">literary. </hi>Like other restrictions upon expression, the
conventions of sexual unspeakability serve writers as a productive constraint,
contributing to a certain historical formation of the literary. Literature in
turn supplies a culturally privileged repository for the production, and
recognition, of sexuality as unspeakable" (3).</p></div>
<div>
        
            <head>2. </head><p>
"In the Victorian period, scandals of all sorts
proliferated in the popular press. In part as a result of the repeal of the
stamp tax in 1855 and the paper duty in 1860, the number of newspapers in Great Britain multiplied, and they became cheaper, more widely available, and more national
in scope. This burgeoning medium generated stories for popular consumption on
a scale that had not been possible before, and the character of both newspapers
and news itself changed significantly. The papers' greater availability,
coupled with increasing literacy, made scandals publicly accessible in new
ways" (6).</p></div>

      <div>
            <head>3. </head><p>
"I suggest that scandal assumes its modern form
only once several conditions are met: that news media are national and
accessible; that they distance the subjects of their stories from their
audience enough to effect a divide between the exposed private life and the anonymous
public reading about it; and that the audience itself is conceived in terms
sufficiently capacious to encompass a wide range of class, gender, and
geographical positions" (6-7).</p></div>
<div>
        
            <head>4. </head><p>
"While it ought to be obvious, it has not been
remarked that scandal, often sex scandal, structures the usual plot of the
realist novel in the Victorian period. The typical story of the Victorian
novel involves the loss and eventual recovery of a fortune, benefactor, parent,
child, sibling, or spouse. The course of recovery necessitates disclosure of a
secret, which has been hidden because it is in some way immoral or illegal;
most often, it involves adultery or illegitimacy. The plot of the novel
unfolds by threatening and finally effecting the exposure of this secret to the
community, and once this revelation has occurred, the goods (property, family)
are redistributed, now more justly, among those who survive. The novelistic
plot, distilled in this way, is analogous to the form of the scandal" (16-17).</p></div>
<div>
         
            <head>5. </head><p>
"The connections between novels and newspaper
scandal stories are not only structural, though; they arise from the deeply
intertwined histories of the two forms, as the work of recent literary critics
has made clear. Scandal and the novel derive, according to these accounts,
from a common ancestor, and the history of the novel has involved a series of
efforts actively to dissociate itself from the taint of scandal" (18).</p></div>
<div>
         
            <head>6. </head><p>
"The scandal plot is so persistent, I suggest,
because it provides a way of working out the novel's own double duty: the duty
of telling stories composed centrally of incidents from private life and,
simultaneously, of using these stories to teach widely applicable public
lessons. Scandal motivates a type of moral pedagogy in the novel, generating
exemplary narratives that both school readers in acceptable behavior and enable
them to experience vicariously the violation of norms. Novels toe the orthodox
line in castigating sexual transgression by the same means that they occasion
its pleasurable consumption. Through the critique of scandal's procedures in
which they frequently engage, moreover, literary works provide readers the
thrill of following scandal while exempting them from the discomfort of being
scandalized" (19).</p></div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
