<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00025">
   <teiHeader>

<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">Henry Shaw: His Life and Legacies</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Faherty">William Barnaby Faherty
</author>
<date type="original" value="1987">1987</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00025</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 97-108 of William Barnaby Faherty's<hi rend="italic">Henry Shaw: His Life and Legacies</hi>, University of Missouri Press, 1987.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter 12, "Female Friends and Would-Be Wife"</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Henry Shaw: His Life and Legacies</hi></title>
               <author>William Barnaby Faherty</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
University of Missouri Press

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Columbia
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1987

</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
0-8262-0644-1
</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
               <term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
			<term id="premaritalsex" type="theme">premarital sex</term>
			<term id="prostitution" type="theme">prostitution</term>
			<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
			<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-09">09 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Second Round Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-03-07">07 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>
         
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

  <head>Female Friends and Would-Be Wife</head>
         <p>To
understand the breach of promise suit filed in the St. Louis Court of Common
Pleas against Henry Shaw as he was preparing to open his garden, a look at his
social attitudes and interests is imperative. In his sketch of Shaw's life,
Thomas Dimmock attributed to historian Frederick L. Billon, a friend of Henry,
the remark that Shaw "seemed to avoid making acquaintances among the
girls. . . . He intended marrying some English girl."' Nowhere in his
extant writings, however, did Shaw give such an indication. He never discussed
his cousin Henry Hoole's suggestions that he marry "Cousin Mary," and
he ignored his sister Sarah's recommendation of several lovely Guernsey girls.</p>

         <p>On
one occasion, as already stated, Caroline suggested that she, Sarah, and Henry
would probably remain "spinsters." And Shaw doubted that his cousin
Francis Hoole's impending marriage with Alathea Tattershal would bring him any
great happiness. Shaw's remark seemed to transcend Francis's choice of marriage
partner and to take a derogatory view of married life in general. While Henry
traveled through Europe, on the other hand, he received letters from Demosthenes
("Demo") Simos that spoke of young ladies they had met; and Shaw's
cousin Henry Hoole joked about the Missourian's amorous adventures on the
Continent. Shaw himself' wrote in his journal of the many young ladies he saw
on his travels and spoke most warmly of a lovely Caroline he met on his first
visit to Vienna.</p>

         <p>Among his miscellaneous letters, Shaw kept several from
friendly French girls, such as Aim&#233;e Dupont, to whom he sent gifts after his
return to St. Louis and some from a St. Louis woman by the name of Honorine
Douard, written in 1849. The latter explained in one of her letters that she
wrote in English because others were present in the room. French was presumably
her native language. She misspelled several words and seemed at times ill at
ease with English. She called herself "your little Honorine" and
suggested that their relationship was close. She apologized for the deception
in not telling him that she was married. "If you wish to aid me, as you
promised, [you] will enclose the rest of the money you promised me. . . . My
husband is in a situation that he can give me no money now. "
A short time later, signing herself Honorine Beranger, presumably her
married name, she thanked him for the money and for his wishes for her
happiness. "My dear friend," she went on, "you say you will see
me at Mrs. Harmony's, but if possible I would prefer that you will see me
tomorrow at my sister's at two o'clock."  </p>

         <p>
These female relationships were temporary and more or less
private. A later one gained national notoriety for
Shaw. As Shaw walked in his garden one morning, he saw a young woman whom he
later described to a friend as "not only a pretty woman but a fascinating
one." After he got acquainted, she came regularly to the garden.
When she did not come, she would send him a note (none of which he kept). In early
February 1856 this young woman, whose name was Effie Carstang borrowed $100
from Shaw to be returned on demand. Slightly over a year later, she borrowed
another $100. In August 1857, Effie rented from Shaw for one dollar a month a
rosewood piano made in Baltimore.  She agreed to send it back on recall. Shaw
later took the piano back, but that was not the last word on the musical
instrument from Miss Carstang.</p>

         
<p>On 19 July 1858, Effie Carstang sued Henry Shaw in
the St. Louis Court of Common Pleas for breach of promise of marriage. She alleged
that a friendship had grown between them and that in November 1856 she had
promised to marry him and Shaw in turn had promised to marry her. She remained
willing to marry the defendant. In the original claim, she asked damages to the
amount of $20,000 but then scratched over that figure and wrote $100,000 in the
line above with the approval of the court. 
</p>

         <p>
In a response three months later, Henry Shaw denied that
on any day in November 1856 or on any other day before or since had he ever
promised to marry Miss Carstang or asked her to marry him. He denied that she
had sustained any damages of any amount whatsoever. Shaw, in fact, had a
counterclaim. He held two promissory notes&#8212;one of 28 February 1856 and one of 19 May 1857. In each instance Effie had borrowed $100
from him and agreed to pay on demand. Shaw insisted she had not paid.
Strangely, Henry never alluded to the rental of the rosewood piano, even though
Effie and her sister both mentioned the "gift" of a piano that Shaw
took back sometime later.
</p>

         <p>The <hi rend="italic">
Missouri
Democrat 
</hi>described Effie as a young woman of about thirty, tall and
graceful, with dark hair, brilliant eyes, blonde complexion, and "a mouth
expressive of great firmness and decision of character." The same edition
described Henry Shaw as "about sixty years of age, with hair somewhat
grey, rather sharp features, but with an expression of countenance anything but
disagreeable. He was a man of great wealth, and his Tower Grove home was one of
the finest residences in the neighborhood of St. Louis." The article
concluded, "Mr. Shaw is one of our oldest citizens and during a long
residence here he has sustained a character hitherto unimpeachable."</p>

         <p>Years
later, <hi rend="italic">
Reedy's Mirror, 
</hi>the one St. Louis-based
periodical to win a reputation beyond the borders of the United States for pungent literary criticism and the discovery of new authors, described Henry and
Effie in an unexcelled way:

         <q rend="block">Henry
Shaw was a hardware man ... a nailing good one. By close application to
business, attention to judiciously advertising his wares, an incessant working
of the scissors in clipping coupons, he amassed a competency which later he
invested in St. Louis dirt. Then his eye, 'in a fine frenzy rolling,' turned from
the dreary monotony of spikes and mauls to the heavenly ecstasy of flowers ...
and engaged in what Bacon declared the most pleasing occupation of
man-gardening.... an Englishman, stolid, dogmatic, lettered - a man of strong
conviction, few intimate friendships but genial with those who succeeded in
getting into his charmed circle.... Somewhere and under some strange
concatenation of circumstances, Henry Shaw met Effie Carstang. Tall and willowy
was Effie. Her entire get-up, her <hi rend="italic">tout
ensemble</hi>, . . . was gorgeous.
She possessed a pair of orbs that made diamonds look like cobblestones, cheeks
that caused roses to look up ... a form that set artists to climbing poles, a
voice that threw musicians into conniptions, lips&#8212;now by the beard of the
Prophet&#8212;she had lips.</q></p>

         <p>    Such
were the principals in a stirring court drama. Lawyers for the plaintiff were
Maj. Uriel L. Wright, state legislator and spellbinding criminal lawyer, and L.
M. Shreve. Judge Edward Bates, John R. Shepley, and Judge James R. Lackland
defended Shaw. While the other four were well known locally, Bates, nephew of
an early Missouri gover-nor and a national figure, had represented Missouri in
the U.S. Congress, served in the state senate, and, after declining a position
in the administration of President Millard Fillmore, became judge of the St.
Louis Land Court. He had presided at the Whig National Convention m Baltimore in 1856; as one of the Republican candidates in 1860, he would amass almost half
as many votes as Abraham Lincoln on the first ballot at the convention in Chicago. The following year Lincoln would name him attorney general of the United States.</p>

         <p>On
the opening day of the trial, Friday, 27 May 1859, before Judge Sam
Reber, the sister of Miss Carstang, Mrs. Marie Seaman, testified in Effie's
behalf. She spoke of Shaw's visits and gifts, including the piano and books on
botany, and the interpretation she and her sister placed on these favors. On
Saturday, 28 May, the second day, the courtroom was crowded during the long
testimony, most of it evidence for the plaintiff. The counsel for the defense
extensively cross-examined Mrs. Seaman.</p>

         <p>The
  <hi rend="italic">Missouri
Republican 
</hi>generally gave much less
attention to the trial than the <hi rend="italic">
Democrat 
</hi>did,
but on 30 May the <hi rend="italic">
Republican 
</hi>quoted at length the long
speech of Shaw's attorney Shepley. Surprisingly, Shepley admitted the costly
gifts that his client had given Effie: valuable jewelry as a token of his
affection and the best fruits of his garden in Tower Grove. On Wednesday a man
by the name of Canese from Charleston, South Carolina, testified that Effie had
resided at an establishment frequented by "dashing fellows." But
Effie's counsel brought contrary evidence. Especially strong was that of judge
Alexander Hamilton, who said that the sisters were good tenants and prompt in
paying rent. From his business associations with them, he knew nothing
disagreeable about them. Everything, in fact, indicated the contrary. Another
witness, John Brady, also praised Miss Carstang.</p>

         <p>On
Thursday, 2 June, the sixth day of the case, the huge crowd again assembled.
The judge instructed the jury that it was not necessary to have clear evidence
of mutual consent of the respective parties; the jurors could infer a promise
of marriage from the circumstances of the relationship; no mutual expressions
of intention were needed, nor was any third-party witness. The judge also
directed them to make any monetary decision not simply on financial values, but
to consider any psychological or other difficulties the young woman had
endured.</p>

         <p>After
the judge had instructed the jury, Major Wright introduced testimony for the
plaintiff from a man in South Carolina to counter the remarks of Mr. Canese of
the day before. This gentleman testified that Effie's character was not
tarnished as alleged. Major Wright proposed to introduce a further witness, but
Bates and Shepley objected that no new witnesses should be introduced. The
judge sustained the objection.</p>

         <p>At
some time during the trial a letter became public that Effie had allegedly sent
to Henry. (Three weeks after the trial, William McHenry, commercial editor of
the <hi rend="italic">Missouri
Republican, 
</hi>stated that during the
trial, a counsel for Miss Carstang had pointed to such a letter, wanting the
jury to read it, but the court had excluded it.) In this letter
Effie stated that Shaw had visited her in her home. He had sent her flowers,
fruit, and other presents and seemed to desire that their relationship should
be made public. He sent a piano as a gift. She claimed he named a marriage time
and then postponed it because of arrangements at the Garden. Then he took the
piano back to his own house under the plea of a party to be held there. Finally
he ceased to visit her. Presuming he might be sick, she called on him at his
house, only to have him insult her with an indecent proposition. Effie
concluded her letter, "Had you called me as a gentleman and offered a
reasonable excuse or simply asked me to release you from this engagement and
assigned a reason, I trust I should have had too much pride not
to have complied at once. But your desertion, as it is, deserves whatever punishment
the opinion of a just public may visit upon its author."</p>

         <p>On
the seventh day of the trial, Friday, 3 June, the crowd was larger than ever.
Judge Bates "bombarded his hearers," to use the <hi rend="italic">Missouri
Democrat's

</hi>words, from 10:15 to 12:15.
Following this, Major Wright summarized the case in a speech that lasted
two and three-quarters hours. The <hi rend="italic">
Democrat 
</hi>described
it as the most eloquent speech ever made by the distinguished advocate. The crowded
courtroom burst continuously into noisy applause. Judge Reber admonished the
spectators for this excessive demonstration and ordered the sheriff to arrest
disturbers; only then did they grow quiet.</p>

         <p>At
four o'clock the jury gave its unanimous verdict&#8212;for Effie Carstang. The
crowd vented its full joy in the rotunda.  The <hi rend="italic">MissouriDemocrat</hi> believed that the decision was a popular one. The Missouri 
<hi rend="italic">
Republican 
</hi>
had little comment on the day of the verdict, but early the next year was
to speak favorably of the decision and of the plaintiff. Judge Sam Reber
awarded Effie damages of 
$100,000.
</p>

         <p>In his diary for
4 June, a day later, Attorney Bates wrote, "This atrocious verdict has
excited, as it ought, the indignant denunciation of the public. We have moved
for a new trial. . . . Jurors were so stupid or wicked, or both."   The
evidence, Bates felt, all pointed to a verdict for the defendant. "Yet we
were all astonished that a verdict was rendered, after but a few minutes
deliberation, for the plaintiff, with an assessment of damages of
$100,000." Bates presumed that judge Reber would want to cleanse his
record of so vile a blot upon the administration of justice. "The
abominable verdict shocked the moral sense of the community and made most men
fear for the safety of property and character."</p>

         <p>Perhaps
Bates judged the situation properly, perhaps not. To the wealthy people it was
a bad verdict; to the average poor person of the city, and of course there were
many more of them, the verdict seemed a good one, at least if one may judge
from the words of the <hi rend="italic">MissouriDemocrat</hi>. On the same day that Bates
wrote those words in his diary, Shepley joined him in asking for a new trial,
citing many reasons. They claimed that the verdict was against the law,
evidence, truth, and decency. They claimed, on the one hand, that the
instructions of the court were not followed; and on the other, that the court
admitted improper testimony and excluded proper testimony. They alleged that
the jurors were prejudiced against the defendant and reached their decision by
bargain and compromise, not by judgment. The Records of the Court of Common
Pleas asserted:

         <q rend="block">The
plaintiff in the progress of the trial was guilty of a gross&#8212;impropriety and contempt of court in causing to be published in a newspaper, a
letter purporting to be from the plaintiff to the defendant, which had been
offered in evidence by the <hi rend="italic">
plaintiff 
</hi>and
ruled out by the court; and the publication of which was well calculated if not
designed to bring bias and mislead the jury. The amount of the damages assessed
by the jury is excessive&#8212;unjustly and preposterously large&#8212;unsupported by
testimony and, of itself, proof of prejudice, passion and misconduct on the
part of the jurors.</q></p>

         <p>On
8 June, Moritz Stienbach, one of the jurors, stated that he did not understand
English well, did not believe the verdict righteous, did not understand
American practice, and thought he had to go along with the majority. Six days
later another original juror, G. W. Chadwick, countered by notifying Wright
that Shepley had clearly questioned Stienbach as to his understanding and
command of English and was satisfied. And, Chadwick continued, when the jury
had retired to the jury room, "All agreed at once to a verdict&#8212;except Mr.
Stienbach, and he did not object because of any proofs in the case," but
because a German newspaper the day before had questioned Effie's conduct in Charleston. After explanation, Stienbach agreed that he was for a verdict of $100,000.
Chadwick notarized the letter the same day and submitted it to the attorneys,
but the plea for a new trial prevailed.</p>

         <p>As
soon as the court agreed to a retrial, the attorneys for the beleaguered
bachelor set to work. On 6 June, two days after Shaw's lawyers had submitted
their appeal, a certain A. H. Smith of Sing Sing, New York, offered to bring
proof of Effie's bad character. Fourteen days later he wrote that his wife knew
of the sour reputation of both Effie and her sister, Marie Seaman, and offered
names of parties for evidence. Many other letters came in June or July of that
year that dealt in a negative way with the character, background, or
antecedents of Effie Carstang. A New Yorker by the name of J. Nichols stated
that some time before her father's death Effie had sued a certain Young Brown
for breach of promise. Another resident of New York, Peter Heiler, wrote that
Effie had brought suit against an otherwise unidentified Captain Williams.
Three letters came from Brooklyn: John Samow claimed that he had facts to set
aside the first judgment; John Holdreth accused Effie of improper conduct in
church &#8212; she had smiled during the sermon (horror of horrors!); and Thomas J.
Berry, a Brooklyn sailmaker, listed five men who "spoke lightly" of
Effie. An attorney in Cincinnati, R. D. Henry, also claimed that he had facts
to set aside the first judgment.</p>

         <p>The
magnitude of the initial verdict made the case a national concern. The <hi rend="italic">
New
York Illustrated News 
</hi>called it "the largest sum ever
awarded in this country in such an action." When the appeal came to court
in March 1860, <hi rend="italic">
Harper's Weekly 
</hi>reminded its readers that
this was the great breach of promise case of the previous year that gave a
verdict of $100,000 damages for the plaintiff. The article added a few personal
items about Effie and Shaw. She was attractive; her father, a widower,
Methodist, and businessman, had died ten years before. Effie had met Shaw in
1856, and the alleged promise of marriage had come in November of the following
year. Henry Shaw had lived in St. Louis forty-one years; he was a merchant with
great wealth, was of medium height, had a hardy complexion with blue eyes, and
possessed a great suavity of manners; in fact, he was one of the politest men
in St. Louis. His wealth was estimated at between one-and-a-half and two
million dollars. He had turned a barren prairie into an Eden.</p>

         <p>Marie
Seaman testified again that Shaw had begun to visit her sister, who lived with
her, two or three times a week in 1856. He gave her jewelry, a piano, gloves,
fruit, flowers, and other gifts. Generally he brought a gift at each visit. He
brought books about botany, since he wanted Effie to know botany before they
married. Shaw told Marie that he intended to marry Effie, and she began to
prepare for the wedding in 1857. When she and Effie visited Shaw, she never saw
any white person at his residence. Cross-examination avoided Mrs. Seaman's
allegations and concentrated on her divorce to cast suspicion on her
personally. </p>

         <p>At
least three different men, Joseph Havener, Moses Abbott, and Thomas Yostic,
said that John Carter, one of the jurors, had publicly stated in their presence
that Effie was not a decent woman and that Shaw was unjustly condemned in the
first trial. Carter denied having made such a statement.</p>

         <p>As counsel for
the defendant, Shepley summarized his position in this way: Effie sought Shaw's
acquaintance for the purpose of entrapping him. Hence most of the twenty days
of the trial consisted of depositions and testimony from men who claimed that
Effie had engaged in prostitution in Brooklyn, Cincinnati, and Charleston. Most of them said that they had <hi rend="italic">
heard 
</hi>she
was "a wanton woman." At least one of the men, Steven Birch, was so
confused under cross-examination that he testified that Effie was both a good
and a bad woman at the same time. The most damaging statement against Effie's
character came from James I. Cochran of Cincinnati on the eighteenth day.
Cochran had bad things to say about Effie; personally, he had kissed her, but
would not admit to having had intercourse with her.</p>

         <p>Effie
Carstang's counsel had been allowed to take a deposition from John Forbush, a
crippled man in Cincinnati who knew Cochran. Forbush stated that Cochran was a
perennial liar and known to be such. As to the allegation that Effie was a
woman of easy virtue, he had never heard anyone make such a statement. He
stated under questioning, "Neither Miss Carstang nor anyone else offered
to pay me anything for testifying in this case."</p>

         <p>Judge
Reber excluded testimony that called into question the veracity of several
witnesses for Shaw, and he did not allow the letter from Effie to Shaw to be
used. The <hi rend="italic">
Missouri Democrat 
</hi>felt that the letter's
publication in the <hi rend="italic">
Republican 
</hi>had really formed the basis
for successful application for a new trial.</p>

         <p>The
verdict against Effie came on Saturday, 31 March 1860, the twentieth day of the
trial. The <hi rend="italic">
Missouri Democrat 
</hi>stated flatly that the
decision "on the whole surprised the community . . . . Even people in Cincinnati thought she would win and people questioned the impartiality of the jury as others
did in earlier decisions. For instance, allegedly the foreman of the jury was
seen going to Shaw's house before the verdict. The majority of people seemed to
think that Effie should have gotten something, at least court costs." The  <hi rend="italic">Missouri
Republican 
</hi>gave less space to the verdict in the case than to judge
Bates's candidacy for the presidency. It did comment on the throng in the
courtroom, and it praised Major Wright for his summary as a "burst of
oratory sparkling in wit and humor and sharp edged sarcasms . . . [and]
historical allusions."</p>

         <p>Effie
submitted her request for a new trial on 2 June 1860,
basing her petition on the fact that several jurors were prejudiced, among them
John Carter and Charles Schuler, who allegedly stated that he had made 
up his mind and would not change his view no matter
what Major Wright or anyone else said.
</p>

         <p>While
the feature writer for the <hi rend="italic">
New York Illustrated News 
</hi>expected
a new trial, he took an ambivalent view on the one just completed. He thought
the whole Union should show its appreciation to the jury for its common sense
"in the face of lovely women ... immense legal talent, every possible
technicality . . . [and] every known precedent, unlike most juries in his
neighborhood that have hitherto been notorious for their liberal donations to
female plaintiffs of other people's money. " In the
same issue, ten pages later, the writer spoke of Shaw's "scandalous means
of defense. He ransacked the country to destroy forever the character of a more
youthful, humble and poor antagonist." But the writer agreed that Shaw
had no alternative under the initial verdict. Shaw was "prompted by a hope
of neutralizing the strong feeling the people of St. Louis seemed to entertain
toward the plaintiff " The writer saw no real disgrace in proposing
marriage and then backing off. He felt that "Shaw was smarting under the
heavy verdict in the first trial."
</p>

         <p>The
<hi rend="italic">
St. Louis Times 
</hi>expressed joy that the case
was over and noted the general regret that the plaintiff did not get something.
It saw Shaw in a "most unenviable position" and concluded that both
lost. Effie appeared as "an <hi rend="italic">
intriguante 
</hi>and
adventurer of the most dangerous type" and Shaw "as a libertine of
seventy [sic]." The incidents revealed "more meanness than passion."</p>

         <p>Shaw's
counselor, Edward Bates, had left a vehement denunciation of the first verdict
in his diary. That journal&#8212;at least in the printed edition - did not even
mention the second trial. On the day of the verdict, in fact, Bates wrote
highly critical analyses of President James Buchanan's forays into the field of
lawmaking.</p>

         <p>Judge
Bates, who in reality did little at either hearing, received $250 in fees for
each of the two trials; Shepley's fees for both suits amounted to $1,425.
Disbursement by Judge J. R. Lackland reached $2,079 for travel and expenditures
in rounding up testimony. Shaw's entire expenditure on the case totaled
$15,358.81 at first counting.</p>

         <p>The
difference between the fees of Shepley and Bates and the disbursements of
Lackland on the one hand and the total expenses on the other leave unaccounted
about $10,000. Why this strange discrepancy?  <hi rend="italic">
Reedy's Mirror, 
</hi>many
years later, said it went to Charles E Cady. The article stated:

         <q rend="block">. . . Charlie Cady . . . one of the legal staff . . .
packed his grip and made a bee-line for the city down on the Atlantic seaboard.
Better than his education as a lawyer was his experience as a
"rounder" on such a mission. He turned Charleston upside down, in and
out, secured enough depositions to load a freight car, and sufficient testimony
of a damaging character to blacken and blast and smash and utterly annihilate
the reputation of all the saints in the calendar. Then he returned to St.
Louis, walked into court with a countenance as innocent of guile as a babe's,
and began to open up and read document after document of such salaciousness of,
and concerning the said Effie Carstang, she and her heirs and assigns forever,
as to cause bald heads of that day and generation to clutch at their whiskers,
to marvel that doings of the kind described could be carried on in a free and
enlightened republic. Effie Carstang didn't get her hands on a cent on account
of her suit against Shaw, but Charlie Cady did. He pocketed Ten Thousand in
very cool, exceeding cool cash.</q>
</p>

         <p>Cady
did not get the full $10,000, though. He accounted for almost half that much
money: $2,526.37 in rounding up testimony, $1,525 in salary for his efforts.
The destination of the other six thousand remains one of the few unaccounted
outlays in Shaw's account book.</p>

         <p>This
proved the most sensational, but not the last court case involving Henry Shaw.
His business papers show 122 court cases, usually involving minor questions of
property. They would begin in 1870 and reach a high of fifteen in 1880, with
the second highest number, eight, in 1888, the last full year of Shaw's life.</p>

         <p>Effie
Carstang and her sister Marie Seaman presumably moved away from St. Louis shortly after the trial. During several previous years the <hi rend="italic">
St.
Louis Directory 
</hi>had listed Mrs. M. Seaman as residing at 123 N. 5th St. Effie resided with her sister in property rented from judge Alexander
Hamilton. After the trial the name of Mrs. M. Seaman no longer appeared in the <hi rend="italic">
St. Louis Directory. 
</hi>
         </p>

         <p>Though
he never married, Shaw did have a true and lasting love, according to the
testimony of a man who held the post of head gardener for the last twenty years
of Shaw's life. In an interview years later, the gardener told a woman reporter
for the <hi rend="italic">
Republic, 
</hi>"She was an American
girl and neither he nor she ever married." One day when they were past
seventy, she called on Shaw, and the gardener saw them walking arm in arm
through the Garden in the moonlight. The gardener thought they would at last
marry. When asked why they had never done so, he responded,
"That I know, but I shall never tell you or anyone." The gardener, no
doubt, kept his word.
</p>
<div1 type="file references">
            <list>


			
              	<item><xptr n="ls.00142" type="image on history"/></item>



	</list>
         </div1>
</body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>