<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00065">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"The Wetton Scandal"</title>
		<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
		<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00065</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 2 of the April 27, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         


</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">The Wetton Scandal</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
April 27, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="carriage" type="setting">carriage</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>


         <head>
The Wetton Scandal</head>

	<head>The Hero of the Mobile Sensation Arrested for Bigamy</head>




         <p>The Indianapolis, Ind., <hi rend="italic">News </hi>relates
the following later developments in the Wetton scandal sensation of Mobile, Ala., an account of the first exposure of which appeared with illustrations in the <hi rend="italic">Gazette
</hi>some weeks since.</p>


         <p>Last night C. Albert Wetton, ex-auditor of one
of the Mobile railroads, was arrested in this city by Chief of Police Travis
and Captain Forbes on a warrant based on a grand jury indictment against the
gentleman for bigamy. Wetton and his wife lived happily together for several
years in Mobile, and as he was in receipt of a salary of 5,000 they were
enabled to maintain a fine establishment. About a year ago he formed the
acquaintance of Mrs. Mary Jane Hartpence, the wife of an Indianapolis printer
by the name of Walter Hartpence. Last fall he obtained a Utah divorce from his
wife without notifying her of the fact, and after having, as he supposed,
legally ridden himself of her, persuaded her to take a trip to California. He parted with her at St. Louis on Friday, November 16, 1877, leaving her to
make the journey alone, and started back in the general direction of Mobile. By some means the suspicions of the wife became aroused and instead of going on to the Golden State she returned to the South after a delay of a day or two. On leaving his wife Wetton came to this city and late Saturday night routed up County Clerk Brown from whom he obtained a marriage license, Receiver Hunt, of
the Grand Hotel, making the necessary affidavits. Mary Hartpence had been
granted a decree of divorce during the previous September by Judge Julian, and
both supposing that every legal bar to their union had been removed, were
married on the afternoon of Sunday, November 18, in the parlors of the Second
Presbyterian Church, Rev. W. A. Bartlett officiating. The singularly married
couple went South, and it so chanced that they encountered wife No. 1 in a
sleeping car. A scene followed which was graphically illustrated in the <hi rend="italic">Police
Gazette </hi>shortly after. Wetton lost his situation by reason of the scandal
growing out of this episode, and removed to Ohio with wife No. 2.</p>


         <p>At the last term of the grand jury in this city
a bill for bigamy was returned against Wetton, and several days ago his true
wife came here with the expressed purpose of prosecuting her unfaithful
husband. She decoyed him to this city by giving him to understand that she
wanted to arrange with him for the procurement of a legitimate divorce. He fell
into the trap readily, arriving from Cincinnati last evening. He had been
expected on the noon train but missed connections. The outraged wife was very
anxious to have him arrested, but once in the hands of the police she appeared
very solicitous to get him out of trouble.</p>


         <p>This morning Wetton was visited by his wife, who
is now only too willing to compromise provided her husband will give up the
"other woman," get employment and take her back to his arms again. The case
has gone beyond her control. Wetton's bail was fixed at $1,000, which he has
been unable to furnish. The prisoner is a man about thirty-five years of age,
of very prepossessing appearance and fine address. He is much torn up over his
arrest. </p>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>