<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00096">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Natural History of Courtship</hi></title>
		<title level="c" type="chapter">"Concerning Coquettes"</title>
		<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">Punch</hi></title>
		<date type="original" value="1842">1842</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author name="Wills">W.H. Wills
</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00096</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 125-126 of the original 1842 publication of <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Concerning Coquettes</title>
               <title level="m">The Natural History of Courtship</title>
               <author>anonymous</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Punch

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
London

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1842

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="carriage" type="setting">carriage</term>
               <term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
			<term id="dance" type="setting">dance</term>
			<term id="courtship" type="theme">courtship</term>
			<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
			<term id="arrangedmarriage" type="theme">arranged marriage</term>
			<term id="british" type="place">British</term>
<term id="fiction" type="media">fiction</term>

            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-23">23 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-25">25 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary encoding Edit</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
            <p>A coquette is a graduate in the science
of flirtation, who has taken every degree from her alma-mater &#8212; who is so good
a mistress of arts that she no longer needs a tutor, and is competent to manage
her own affairs without the aid of a chaperon. Being, according to Ben
D'Israeli, a "Psychological curiosity," she undergoes two changes before
arriving at maturity: &#8212; From the insect of the school-period she becomes the
chrysalis of the ball-room, whence she emerges from beneath the wing of her
chaperon to flutter forth the full-grown butterfly, or coquette.</p>

         <p>A finished coquette is pretty, intellectual, and
very fond of waltzing. She can, at a moment's notice, be intensely agreeable,
or quietly repellant; she can smile with one side of her face upon a new
conquest, and frown with the other upon his waning rival. She has a scale of
attractions by which she measures her deportment towards different
individuals. To a younger son, with small prospects, she is reserved and
formal; to a captain of infantry, polite; to a ditto in the Guards,
condescending. She is affable to the heir-presumptive of a rich title;
affectionate and confiding to the heir apparent; but to the title itself,
perfectly bewitching! She will walk a quadrille with a county member, but will
not, if possible, waltz with anything under a peer. She can be a <hi rend="italic">spirituelle
</hi>to a wit, grave to a parson, and poetical to a minor. She knows
instinctively the exact moment when to commence a flirtation; and &#8212; having no
passion, no feelings &#8212; can adroitly break off an ineligible one, even if the
wedding liveries have been ordered.</p>

         <p>To play off her arts with the proper degree of
confidence &#8212; of carelessness about the result &#8212; of that seeming indifference to
success which is the main element of success, the first duty of the coquette is
to provide herself with a stock-lover &#8212; one who is so devotedly hers, that
there is no fear of losing <hi rend="italic">him </hi>even if all else should fail. It was
not, therefore, till the Hounourable Mrs. Couple saw her <hi rend="italic">prot&#233;g&#233;e </hi>excellently
provided in this respect, in the person of Sir Charles Simper, that she
withdrew her valuable advice and services from Miss Rose Robinson. With the
pride of a professor, who sees his pupil rise to celebrity and honour in his
peculiar branch of learning, did the delighted chaperon point to her scholar as
a perfect coquette.</p>

         <p>"A large party of fashionables," observed the <hi rend="italic">Morning
Post </hi>of a recent date, "are assembled at the seat of the Lord Fallover, Fallover Park, Staffordshire. The young earl seems determined to emulate the hospitable
liberality of his ancestors, for the following long list of distinguished
fashionables are at present his guests." The names of Miss Robinson, Sir
Charles Simper, and P. Pleinpurse, Esq., concluded the catalogue.</p>

         <p>It was here that Rose evinced herself a perfect
mistress of her art. She had already nearly "entangled" one of the richest
commoners in England &#8212; a dandy and dilettante; but her success in that quarter
being doubtful, on account of the difficulty of managing a person so
inordinately vain as Mr. Pleinpurse, she, with a laudable ambition, now aspired
to her host. Lord Fallover was a fox-hunter and fancy farmer, who cursed the
opera, and comprehensively criticized the whole of the fine arts as a bord; and
her address, in sympathizing with the opposite tastes of these antipodes, won
the admiration of some of her fellow-guests, and the envy of others. She spent
her mornings in admiring Fallover's beagles, his patent ploughs, his enormous
turnips, his obese oxen. She learnt all the good points of a horse, and
praised his favourite hunters, as if she had graduated amongst "Scott's lot,"
and finished her training at Tattersall's. She took the box-seat beside him
when he drove his four-in-hand, and attended every "meet" in a red riding-habit.</p>

         <p>Thus, all the morning she was Fallover's Diana;
but in the evening she became Pleinpurse's Euterpe. Then it was she melted her
mellow tones into love songs, or raised her voice in the <hi rend="italic">very </hi>heroic
duetts of Donizetti. Then she was eloquent upon the <hi rend="italic">sotto voce </hi>of
Frezzolini, the <hi rend="italic">aplomb </hi>of Lablache, the <hi rend="italic">tremulando </hi>of Rubini. In
the evening there was nothing she adored so much as music; in the morning
brindle oxen were her passion; but just before dinner &#8212; when there was nobody
else to flirt with &#8212; it was the society of Sir Charles Simper which she
declared was so delightful.</p>

         <p>The party was rapidly breaking up &#8212; her mama was
on the eve of returning &#8212; yet the Earl had not proposed. One last chance was
given him; &#8212; he had bought a new horse, which was to be tried in the Tilbury,
and Miss Robinson obtained the other seat in a drive round the Park. Fallover
was by no means a loquacious man, and the lady made desperate efforts to draw
him out by her own remarks: &#8212; "What a beautiful country! &#8212; a paradise! Thrice
happy must be his lot to possess so charming an estate." And then, "A country
life &#8212; how perfect a millennium &#8212; how far more attractive than the dissipations
of London!" (a heart-breaking sigh accompanied the exclamation.) Lord
Fallover assented to all she said, and pulled up at an elegant farm-house.
With many apologies he borrowed a groom to drive her back to the Hall &#8212; "He had
business with his tenant, Mr. Aacres."</p>

         <p>Rose remembered that this identical tenant had a
lovely daughter and determined to dine in London that day. Pleinpurse had
offered her mama and her seats in his carriage &#8212; (the servants could go to town
in Simper's) &#8212; and on arriving at the Hall the offer was accepted.</p>

         <p>That journey did wonders with Pleipurse; and a
week after the affair was arranged, all but giving a handsome <hi rend="italic">congé</hi> to
Simper. Rose would not, however, do so till the settlements had been actually
signed; for no coquette is justified in turning off a lover till his chance is
hopeless. The Earl had married the farmer's daughter, to the utter disgust of
every chaperon and coquette of his acquaintance.</p>

         <p>Leaving Miss Robinson for the present, let us
remark, that whilst the accomplished coquette wins our astonishment by the
excess of her ingenuity, her perfect nerve on occasions of the most startling <hi rend="italic">embarras,
</hi>and her Protean changes of demeanour, &#8212; the clumsy <hi rend="italic">maladroit </hi>flirt,
who possesses all the desires without any of the arts of coquetry, excites that
which would come very near contempt, if so strong a word can be justly applied
to any of the "angels of life."</p>

         <p>Inferior kinds of coquettes are only to be met
with in inferior classes of society. They are known at a glance &#8212; they wear
very low dresses and large quantities of jewellery. They smell strongly of
Rowland's Kalydor, which is sometimes accompanied with a suspicion of pomatum.
They talk a vast deal, and frequently laugh in spite of their teeth. To their
admirers they are guilty of either of the most lavish fondness or the most
unpardonable rudeness. They make any engagement that is offered, and break it
without the smallest compunction. Flattery is their food, caprice their rule
of conduct. In a word, as the proficient coquette is the elegant,
beautifully-tinted butterfly, so the ill-bred flirt is the mere moth. The
former ends her existence as a chaperon &#8212; the latter as something worse; for
coquetry hovers so near the extremest edge of virtue's limits, that without the
vigilant exercise of the finest art, the boundary is sure to be over-stepped.</p>
	<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00055" type="same fiction"/></item>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00095" type="same fiction"/></item>

               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00143" type="image on fiction"/></item>
		<item><xptr n="ls.00144" type="image on fiction"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00145" type="image on fiction"/></item>
		<item><xptr n="ls.00146" type="image on fiction"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>