<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00021">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"A Cheeky Chicago-un"

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00021</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 6 of the May 21, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">A Cheeky Chicago-un</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
May 21, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="divorce" type="theme">divorce</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>A CHEEKY CHICAGO-UN</head>

	<head>Amours of a Festive Railroad Man of O'Learyville, who Established his Legitimate Home</head>
	<head>IN A QUIET LITTLE TOWN</head>

	<head>But who had his Harems all Along the Line; and now his Admiring Neighbors Promise him</head>
	<head>A TAR AND FEATHER ULSTER</head>

                     <p>Hinsdale, Ill., May 14.&#8212;A domestic cyclone, bearing on its
wave the secrets of a home and the shattered reputations of several frail but gushing
and voluptuous females, has struck this little town, situated on the line of
the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy railroad, and some eighteen miles west of
Chicago. Its twelve or fourteen hundred staid, steady and God-fearing citizens stand
bewildered at the lascivious doings of one of their number. The developments of
the present case bring to the surface the loyalty of and fidelity of a prudent
wife, and go to show the depths of suffering that sometimes lie hidden in the
breast of a good woman, to be brought forth from its hiding-place only at the
demand of public justice, and when it can no longer, be hidden from unsavory
whisperings and disgusting comments. The prominent figure in the present
scandal which has struck Hinsdale with the force of an earthquake is embodied
in Henry L. Estabrooks, traveling auditor of the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy railroad, with headquarters at Chicago. If the innumerable stories of this gentleman's
escapades be true, there can be little doubt that the mantle of the late Mr.Young,
with the proclivities of a Beecher ensconced in the folds of the garment, had
fallen upon him. During this festive gentleman's eight years' residence in Hinsdale it is claimed that he has persistently and brutally violated his marriages vows.</p>  

<p>He did not, however, confine his operations to the shady
suburb of Hinsdale, but covered a section of country bounded by the home
residence and Lake Michigan, with a large section of country in and around Chicago yet to be heard from. As is natural to suppose, many of the residents of Hinsdale
and those along the line of road leading to Chicago, strongly objected to this.
After mature consideration about a year ago on the part of several of the
citizens of the pleasant western suburb, it was deemed necessary, in the
interest of morality, to request the gentleman to pack his grip-sack and locate
in other fields. This conclusion was conveyed to the railroad man, but
trusting in the protection of law-abiding citizens, he declined with thanks.
The wife of the peculiarly constituted gentleman, an estimable lady, the mother
of two children, and who is respected and loved by the citizens for her many
excellent qualities, has recently separated from the husband, after many years
of harsh and brutal treatment, it is said.</p>

         <p>Her application for a divorce is
now in the hands of a well-known Chicago attorney, and will be vigorously
prosecuted. It is claimed by the abused wife that for years she has been unable
to retain a domestic in her employ, from the fact of the husband's propensity
to chloroform her (the wife), and then devote the hours of her unconsciousness
to the scullery maid. An instance of late date is related, where the wife
visited her mother, in Chicago, and during her absence placed the home in
charge of a domestic, engaged the day preceding her leaving. The wife, at the
solicitation of the husband, remained from her home several days, during which
time the girl says she was subjected to repeated attacks of an indecent
character from Estabrooks. It is related by the domestic that he proposed
marriage to her several times, but she declined to preside over his domestic
affairs, as well as others of a seductive nature.</p>

         <p>His importunities gained strength and frequency from her
every refusal. One night he was unusually demonstrative; he declared his
undying, fierce, consuming love for her in the strongest terms, and, when she
refused, he talked of shooting himself, and told her he could save his life and
hers only by consenting to smile across the tea-table. She consented, for she had
a fear of firearms, and the anticipations of the mangled corpse which should
contain his heart, sort of froze her with terror. The railroad man was so
jubilant over his success in this case that he couldn't or didn't avoid
speaking of it. After a time the fact came to the ears of the domestic that he
had spoken of his strong will, and how he had conquered her, and this so moved
her that she gave the railroad man "dead away" to his wife and every scullery maid
in Hinsdale. He tried, the girl states, to win her back, but she was
inflexible. Then, as the last method he could think of, he resorted to letter
writing, and succeeded in setting up a rather dramatic model for the literature
of lovers. In his epistles to the girl he asks forgiveness for all the trouble he
had caused her; assures her of forgiveness for all the trouble she has caused;
rehearses his agony, which is unbearable; tells her that he would be out of it
quick, only that he wanted to make his property over to parties who would protect
it from the claims of his wife. In one of these letters to the servant the
gentleman becomes tired of life, and proposes to blow out his brains, after which
he asks her to remain in the village that morning so as to get the news early.
He requests her to destroy his letters when he has passed away, and not forget
to visit his last resting-place, and concludes with the assurance that he is "hers while life lasts."</p>

         <p>This was about the form adopted by the diplomatic railroad
man in "working up the cases" of the several domestics who came into his
household, and they, without an exception, have invariably "given him away,"
not only to the abused and suffering wife, but have spread the fact among the
domestics of the suburb, and they in turn have given the facts, highly
embellished, no doubt, into higher circles, until the man has become loathed
and abhorred by the entire community.</p>

         <p>Sometime during the early part of
the present month Mrs. B. again visited her relations in Chicago. During her
absence the recently-employed domestic was, as she says, subjected to such
gross usage at the hands of Estabrooks that she was compelled to seek refuge in
an adjoining residence, where she remained until Mrs. E.'s return, when the
full facts were laid before her. The latest act of the man had become generally
well known throughout the town, and the matter of his compulsory leaving the neighborhood
or being subjected to an artistic coat of tar and feathers was freely
discussed. As before, law and order prevailed. The residents of the town,
without an exception, it is believed, have openly espoused the cause of the wronged
wife in her application for a separation, and express a determination to make
the gentleman "move out" at an early date.</p>

         <p>This cherub of a husband, it is
related by the unfortunate woman, has repeatedly beaten her, and once, while
pregnant, she was knocked down and kicked, until the neighbors came to her
assistance and ejected him from the house. A daughter, ten years of age, has
also been subjected to brutal punishment from the father. Estabrooks afterward
justified these acts of brutality by the statement that he was a martyr, to the
toothache. There are other acts charged against the husband and father equally
damaging. For instance, it is asserted by the wife, and substantiated by those
who had an opportunity of knowing the truthfulness of the assertion, that the
wife and children were frequently compelled to submit to indecent exposures.  In addition to all this it is given as a notorious fact that
the family of a harmless fellow placed in a subordinate position by Estabrooks,
in one of the offices of the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy railroad, has been
debauched by the patron. </p>

         <p>The family resided at Western
Springs for a couple of years, during which time the liaison between Estabrooks
and the wife was openly conducted, and to such an extent as to be freely
commented upon by the railroad employees and others who were daily observers of
the shameful conduct of both parties. The conduct of the wife became so glaring
that the husband finally applied for a divorce on the ground of the wife's
adultery with Estabrooks. The divorce was granted, and the ex-wife, It is
claimed, is now scratching a living on Wabash avenue, in the vicinity of Twelfth street.</p>

         <p>There is a scarlet woman, too, in
the case, and she comes in the form of a seductive grass-widow, the relic of an
ex-railroad official. She is a blonde, a pronounced one, and like Mr.
Sparkler's various flames, this particular blonde has "no bigged nonsense about
her."  When a wife comes in her path, and interferes with her prey, she strikes
from the shoulder. Mr. Estabrooks, it is stated, has long been an ardent
admirer of the voluptuous blonde, and has had her domiciled in his home at Hinsdale for several weeks in succession, against the repeated protests of his wife and
children. The grass-widow has been in daily attendance at the offices of the Chicago and Burlington road in this city, and is well-known to the officials. The wife
states that during a visit, in company with her little boy, to her husband's office
in Chicago, this woman was found comfortably quartered in his embrace.  The incident is related by Mrs. Estabrooks in this way: On
gaining the floor on which her husband's office was located, she stopped in the
hall to converse with a lady acquaintance, while the child entered the office
in search of his papa. The boy immediately returned with the request that his
"mamma come quick." Mama did "come quick," and stopped quicker. A scene followed&#8212;one
that developed from tragic prose to pallor and surprise with words of
recrimination and worse.</p>

         <p>"My husband, who is this?" gasped
the wife. It was plain to any employee and railroad official who in
immediately gathered in the vicinity of the auditor's department, who "this"
was for it wore a look caught from the inner walls of a house of ill-fame; it
had the stamp of the harlot upon it. When the clapper smote it brazen interior
it gave forth its harsh sound with a prostitute's word and accent. The recreant
lord clutched his desk and stood pale and angered for a few moments in the
presence of his wife and child and a score or so of the railroad employees.</p>

         <p>Other instances of like character
are quoted, and, the residents of Hinsdale are unanimous in the belief that a
great injury has been perpetrated upon an estimable wife and mother, who has
labored long to suppress the irregularities of an unworthy husband. </p>

         <p>And the end is not yet. Tar and
feathers are nightly expected. </p>

         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>
		<item><xptr n="ls.00014" type="same subject"/></item>

               	<item><xptr n="ls.00003" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00040" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00046" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00066" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>