<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00009">
         <teiHeader>
                  <fileDesc>
                           <titleStmt>
                                    <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">When Passion
                                                  Reigned: Sex and the Victorians</hi>
                                    </title>

                                    <title level="j" type="journal"/>
                                    <title level="c" type="chapter"/>
                                    <title level="m" type="monograph"/>
                                    <author name="Anderson">Patricia Anderson</author>
                                    <date type="original" value="1995">1995</date>

                                    <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

                                    <editor>Laura White</editor>
                                    <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
                                             <name>Michael Page</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
                                             <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
                                             <name>Susan Belasco</name>
                                             <name>Wendy Katz</name>
                                             <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
                                             <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
                                             <name>Harriet Turner</name>
                                             <name>Katherine Walter</name>
                                             <name>John Wunder</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                           </titleStmt>
                           <editionStmt>
                                    <edition>
                                             <date>2004</date>
                                    </edition>
                           </editionStmt>
                           <publicationStmt>
                                    <idno>ls.00009</idno>
                                    <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules
                                             for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
                                    <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
                                    <availability>
                                             <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln,
                                                  all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be
                                                  shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
                                                  of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or
                                                  republication on other terms, in any medium,
                                                  requires express written consent from the editors
                                                  and advance notification of the publisher, the
                                                  Center for Digital Research in the Humanities.
                                                  Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this
                                                  archive has been granted by the owners of the
                                                  originals for this publication only.</p>
                                    </availability>
                           </publicationStmt>
                           <notesStmt>
                                    <note type="project"> Transcribed from pages 71-92 of Patricia
                                             Anderson's <hi rend="italic">When Passion Reigned: Sex
                                                  and the Victorians</hi>. Published by Basic Books,
                                             1995. </note>
                           </notesStmt>
                           <sourceDesc>

                                    <bibl>
                                             <title level="a">The Making of Lovemaking</title>
                                             <title level="m">
                                                  <hi rend="italic">When Passion Reigned: Sex and
                                                  the Victorians</hi>
                                             </title>
                                             <author>Patricia Anderson</author>
                                             <imprint>
                                                  <publisher> Basic Books </publisher>
                                                  <pubPlace> New York </pubPlace>
                                             </imprint>
                                             <date> 1995 </date>
                                             <idno type="ISBN"> 0465089917 </idno>
                                    </bibl>
                           </sourceDesc>
                  </fileDesc>
                  <profileDesc>
                           <textClass>
                                    <keywords>
                                             <term id="british" type="place">British</term>
                                             <term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
                                             <term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
                                             <term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular
                                                  press</term>
                                    </keywords>
                           </textClass>
                  </profileDesc>
                  <revisionDesc>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Laura White</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>edit item</item>
                           </change>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Laura White</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>edit headers</item>
                           </change>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-04-13">13 April 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Michael Page</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
                           </change>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI
                                             files</item>
                           </change>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
                           </change>
                           <change>
                                    <date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
                                    <respStmt>
                                             <name>Zach Bajaber</name>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
                           </change>
                  </revisionDesc>
         </teiHeader>
         <text>
                  <body>

                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic"> The Making of Lovemaking </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>As they pursued the women of their choice, [Victorian men]
                                             individually reflected the romantic and sexual ideals
                                             of the day. If [they] were not generally poets, some at
                                             least dipped into the outpourings of others, as did
                                             many of the women they desired. Still more people
                                             nourished their romantic longings on best-selling
                                             fiction. Meanwhile, songs and other entertainments,
                                             greeting cards, love letters, courting customs, and
                                             marriage manuals also fostered the relationship of the
                                             sexes. Romantic sexual love was a constant, often
                                             public presence in Victorian life and popular
                                             consciousness. Inevitably this helped to shape people's
                                             expectations and behavior in their private
                                             relationships. The creation in this way of a widely
                                             influential romantic ideal was physical lovemaking's
                                             cultural foreplay&#8212;the making of
                                             lovemaking.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic">Thrilling Through Every Fiber </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>The men and women of romantic fiction set the pace. In the
                                             typical fashion of his kind, Captain Ainsley Falkland,
                                             hero of <hi rend="italic"> Taken by Storm</hi>, an 1885
                                             novel serialized in the London Journal, puts his strong
                                             arms around the heroine, Beryl, and prepares to "ravish
                                             a kiss from her palpitating lips." She in turn responds
                                             characteristically to his "sweet
                                             kisses"&#8212;quick to feel the thrill of physical
                                             arousal, the Victorian romantic heroine thrived on
                                             passion. "With love's joyous impulse," Beryl nestles
                                             her head rapturously on her lover's breast. "'My own
                                             Ainsley,' she murmurs, clinging to him in a perfect
                                             abandon of love's mystic emotions, that thrills through
                                             every fibre of her being."</p>

                                    <p>Other fictional couples were equally devoted and open in
                                             showing their feelings. In the early episodes of
                                             Charles Reade's <hi rend="italic">A Terrible Temptation
                                             </hi>, an 1871 <hi rend="italic">Cassell's
                                             Magzine</hi>serial, the two principal characters, Sir
                                             Charles Bassett and Miss Bella Bruce, are newly engaged
                                             and mutually smitten: <q rend="block">Every day he sat
                                                  for hours at the feet of Bella Bruce, admiring her
                                                  soft feminine ways and virgin modesty, even more
                                                  than her beauty. And her visible blush whenever he
                                                  appeared suddenly, and the soft commotion and
                                                  yielding in her lovely frame whenever he drew
                                                  near, betrayed his magnetic influence, and told
                                                  all but the blind she adored him.</q> But even
                                             from the blind Bella's passion was no secret. She would
                                             also "prattle her maiden love like some warbling
                                             fountain" or, seized by emotion, exclaim to Charles,
                                             "'I love, and honor, and worship, and adore you to
                                             distraction, my own&#8212;own&#8212;own!'"</p>

                                    <p>Bella and Charles, Beryl and Ainsley, and countless fictional
                                             couples like them helped to direct the course of
                                             real-life heterosexuality. Each of the stories in which
                                             such characters figured might have been enjoyed by a
                                             million or more readers. <hi rend="italic">A Terrible
                                                  Temptation </hi> and his other tales of love made
                                             Charles Reade at least as popular as Dickens. Whether
                                             concocted by Reade or more obscure writers, romance was
                                             rife in Victorian fiction. The reading public had only
                                             to open a cover and turn a page or two, and there would
                                             be the ideal of romantic love created and re-created in
                                             compelling plots and illustrations of perfect, happy
                                             couples.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>

                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic"> Romance All Around </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>In an age when print was the major source of mass
                                             entertainment, fiction played the single greatest role
                                             in the making of lovemaking. But other pastimes also
                                             made their collective contribution. Those with the
                                             leisure and means to attend art exhibitions might feast
                                             their eyes and feed their fantasies on paintings of
                                             attractive couples in settings of rustic beauty.
                                             Improving methods of reproduction made such images
                                             available to an ever-wider public. People passing to or
                                             from work might pause over portraits of lovers
                                             displayed in the windows of print shops, or stop at a
                                             newsagent's to browse through the array of illustrated
                                             magazines that regularly pictured romantic
                                             scenes&#8212;a picnic for two, an umbrella shared
                                             on a rainy day, or an intimate outing on a secluded
                                             river. The new art of photography also assisted the
                                             cause of love by capturing the memory of the warm sun
                                             and embraces that went with a day off from work, spent
                                             courting in a park or at the seaside.</p>

                                    <p>Photography offered yet another possibility for keeping
                                             romance on people's minds. One of its offshoots was
                                             among the most popular of entertainments in the
                                             middle-class home. This was the stereograph, which
                                             consisted of two identical photographic images paired
                                             together. Viewed through a stereoscope, the forerunner
                                             of the twentieth-century Viewmaster, the double image
                                             resolved into a single three-dimensional picture. The
                                             London Stereoscopic Company (motto: "A stereo-scope for
                                             every home") and other suppliers offered a wide variety
                                             of stereographic images for their customers'
                                             viewing&#8212;everything from the wonders of
                                             ancient Egypt to current events. One of the most
                                             popular subjects was the relationship of the sexes. The
                                             scenes were generally staged using actors or models
                                             posing in studio settings. The tone might be sad
                                             ("Broken Vows") or sentimental ("The First Love
                                             Letter") or humorous, as in the episode of the suitor
                                             who hides under his young lady's crinoline. Whether
                                             they inspired tears or titters, the three-dimensional,
                                             often color-tinted stereographs showing love between
                                             the sexes gave romance a tangible presence in many
                                             Victorian parlors.</p>

                                    <p>Romance also made itself felt through another parlor fixture,
                                             the piano. During the nineteenth century such
                                             instruments became ever cheaper to manufacture, so that
                                             by 1880 they were featured in virtually every
                                             middle-class household. They were also prestigious
                                             additions to the parlors of the most prosperous
                                             artisans and tradespeople. In middle-class families at
                                             least one female member normally knew how to
                                             play&#8212;such accomplishment was a common part of
                                             a girl's education. In an informal evening's
                                             entertainment involving the family or a few guests, one
                                             or more of the young ladies might play love songs while
                                             others present would listen, perhaps sing along, or
                                             quietly let their imaginations stray into pleasurable
                                             realms.</p>

                                    <p>The piano also provided an opportunity for young people to
                                             enact the rituals of courtship safely in public view,
                                             yet with a modicum of delicious privacy. While parents
                                             or chaperons occupied themselves with card games or
                                             conversation, a young woman and her suitor could enjoy
                                             the physical closeness that the piano encouraged. She
                                             played, he stood nearby, from time to time bending
                                             nearer still to turn a page and breathe in her perfume.
                                             New love could thus grow, nurtured by the parlor piano
                                             and its romantic strains.</p>

                                    <p>While the piano and stereograph were regular fixtures in the
                                             making of love-making, there were also special
                                             occasions, and on these the greeting card took over.
                                             Apart from seasonal motifs, Christmas and New Year's
                                             cards often introduced a note of romance. In one, a man
                                             takes a woman into his arms under the mistletoe, while
                                             a fragment of verse completes the action&#8212;"he
                                             pressed her, kiss'd her, caress'd her." Another card
                                             offered a lighter look at love. It shows a man and
                                             woman embracing on a city street; at the same time a
                                             servingwoman from an adjacent house empties a bucket
                                             whose contents&#8212;water, or worse,
                                             maybe&#8212;are about to hit the amorous pair. The
                                             card's message reads, "May there be no damper on your
                                             pleasure at this festive season."</p>

                                    <p>The high holiday for the exchange of romantic greeting cards
                                             was February 14. The popularity of the valentine grew
                                             rapidly in the Victorian period, and the mid-February
                                             flow of cards increasingly strained the capacity of the
                                             Post Office. In 1841 the English sent a total of
                                             400,000 valentines; by 1871 the figure had risen to one
                                             and a half million for London alone. Valentines ranged
                                             in quality and price. At sixpence, the most affordable
                                             had simple woodcut illustrations enhanced by a
                                             half-dozen or so basic colors. Expensive varieties
                                             costing several shillings were often exquisitely
                                             beautiful, rich in color and decoration&#8212;gold
                                             or silver leaf, ribbon, lace made of paper or fabric,
                                             tiny silk flowers with pearlized leaves, pieces of
                                             plush velvet, and pink and gold embossed cupids were
                                             among the embellishments used on these lavish tokens of
                                             love.</p>

                                    <p>Some valentines were whimsically romantic. Particularly
                                             popular in the 1860s and 1870s were facsimiles of Post
                                             Office telegrams. Bearing the legend "Love Office
                                             Telegraphs" and an insignia of two cupids, they were
                                             stamped with the post-mark "Loveland, Feb. 14." The
                                             engraved messages of more conventional valentines were
                                             often short and direct: "I love but thee." "Accept my
                                             heart." "Affection's token." "Adoration." A few struck
                                             a chord of sadness&#8212;"I hide my love while it
                                             consumes me" but most were optimistic: "Happv Love."
                                             "Ever True." "Yours unalterably." Still others,
                                             elaborated their sentiments in line, of romantic
                                             verse:</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">
                                             <l>How prized the coral and the shell, </l>
                                             <l>And beautiful the pearl,</l>
                                             <l>Who can the hidden treasure tell,</l>
                                             <l>O'er which the soft waves curl.</l>
                                             <l>Yet dearer still art thou to me, </l>
                                             <l>Than all in air, or earth, or sea.</l>
                                    </lg>

                                    <p> The common practice was to send valentines unsigned or with
                                             initials only. The Victorian sexual mystique demanded a
                                             little mystery, even if it was only symbolic, and the
                                             recipient knew full well who was the sender. Romantic
                                             though it was, this secretiveness is a bit unfortunate.
                                             It is now often impossible to determine even the sex of
                                             the sender, let alone his or her identity. Still, there
                                             are occasional revealing exceptions. Among those
                                             distinguishable by gender were three men who inscribed
                                             their own words of love among the embossed hearts and
                                             printed sentiments they sent to the women they loved.
                                             The ink of these handwritten feelings is now faint, but
                                             their sincerity still resonates clearly across the
                                             years. "Accept this token of constancy from your most
                                             devoted." "With best wishes and sweet kisses." And,
                                             simply, "My dear, from GC, 13/2/1856."</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>

                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic">Quivering Lips and Blooming
                                                  Blushes</hi>
                                    </head>


                                    <p>Important though they were to the Victorians, there was more
                                             to the making of lovemaking than the sentiments and
                                             trappings of romance. At the real heart of the matter
                                             was sex. In <hi rend="italic">A Terrible
                                                  Temptation,</hi> Bella on occasion punctuates her
                                             fervent declarations of love for Charles by "flinging
                                             herself passionately yet modestly on his shoulder." Her
                                             passionate modesty was not a contradiction in terms but
                                             one of the many demonstrations of the Victorian gift
                                             for the decorous cultivation of sexuality.</p>

                                    <p>Especially gifted in this way were the many writers of
                                             fiction who celebrated biology with propriety. Not
                                             uncommonly, but discreetly of course, they evoked the
                                             imagery of female sexual parts. In describing Bella's
                                             beauty, Charles Reade gave loving attention to her
                                             mouth. Searching his imagination, he saw "two full and
                                             rosy lips. They made a smallish mouth at rest, but
                                             parted ever so wide when they smiled, and ravished the
                                             beholder." In writing <hi rend="italic"> Taken by
                                                  Storm, </hi>the author gave his hero Ainsley a
                                             constant desire to "sip the nectar" from Beryl's
                                             "pretty" and "quivering" lips. Some readers would have
                                             taken such passages strictly at the face value they
                                             ostensibly presented. Others would have responded to
                                             the sexual connotations of ravishing or quivering lips,
                                             and let their mind's eye stray downward. "Ravish" and
                                             "quiver" both had suggestive meanings, while alluring
                                             facial lips were respectable symbols of a more
                                             fundamental erogenous zone.</p>

                                    <p>Indeed, the language of such symbolism compared closely to
                                             the more literal-minded descriptions in pornography.
                                             The difference was that pornographers gave short shrift
                                             to faces and devoted themselves directly to other "fair
                                             lips" and "pink slits," A reference or two to "dewy
                                             moisture" or "sucking the honey of love" completed the
                                             picture. True to type, the voyeuristic narrator of <hi
                                                  rend="italic"> The Disembodied Spirit </hi> was
                                             quick to fix his gaze in the direction of what lay
                                             between the "quivering thighs" of his current object of
                                             desire. Soon his "eyes dwelt on ... a pair of scarlet
                                             pouting lips, whilst the soft mound above thrilled as
                                             if longing for some unknown pleasure."</p>

                                    <p>Lacking the literalism of pornography and its relentless
                                             taste for the objectification of people, popular
                                             fiction exercised greater inventiveness in the
                                             treatment of sexual themes. It made much of blushing,
                                             for instance. Whenever in the presence of her
                                             fianc&#233;, Charles, Bella blushes visibly.
                                             Beryl's great love for Ainsley suffuses her complexion
                                             with "brilliancy." Similarly, "roseate hues," "vivid
                                             blushes," and "love's colors" constantly "steal" into
                                             the faces of most other romantic heroines in the throes
                                             of passion. It was no accident that feminine blushing
                                             was one of the preferred motifs of the Victorian
                                             romance. Second only, perhaps, to the palpitating
                                             bosom, it identified the true womanly woman.</p>

                                    <p>In 1900 Havelock Ellis's "scientific" analysis of the blush,
                                             part of <hi rend="italic"> Studies in the Psychology of
                                                  Sex,</hi> confirmed what had long been popular
                                             consensus on the subject. Blushing was first of all a
                                             sign of female modesty, a desirable trait in heroines
                                             and real-life women alike. It was also in itself
                                             appealing. In February 1858 the author of the advice
                                             column in <hi rend="italic"> Cassell's Magazine </hi>
                                             assured a concerned young woman that her blushes were a
                                             distinct romantic asset: "That face which has lost the
                                             power to blush, has also lost the power to
                                             charm&#8212;true men." </p>

                                    <p>Beyond adding to a woman's general attractiveness, the blush
                                             was also specifically sexual. Ellis and others before
                                             him argued that physiologically it was virtually the
                                             same as the "general rosiness" of the sexual flush and
                                             directly comparable to the "erection of sexual organs."
                                             It was thus a signal of arousal and, for the unmarried,
                                             an appropriate sex substitute. Small wonder that
                                             fiction made much of feminine blushes as beacons of
                                             arousal, they undoubtedly titillated readers and
                                             stimulated authors' sales.</p>

                                    <p>It almost goes without saying that heroes did not blush. In
                                             and out of fiction, real men controlled their
                                             sexuality, emotions, and bodily responses&#8212;or
                                             so they were supposed to do. At times this was
                                             difficult, even for heroes. Ainsley found Beryl
                                             "perfectly irresistible" and could not stop himself
                                             from "ravishing" her lips. Indeed, she was "possessed
                                             of such power over him" that he gave up a fortune to
                                             marry her, "his only earthly treasure." Charles was
                                             also overcome by his passion for Bella. On those
                                             occasions when she "flung herself passionately" upon
                                             him, he was weakened to the point of feeling "highly
                                             gelatinous" and bereft of "all power of resistance."
                                             His coloring, though, remained unchanged.</p>

                                    <p>But if even in the heat of passion men were constrained to
                                             suppress their own blushing, at least they were always
                                             at liberty to take a prurient manly interest in the
                                             blushes of women. This the poet Joseph Ashby-Sterry
                                             acknowledged, although with less than lyric greatness.
                                             In "A Breezy Ballad," part of his anthology for the
                                             boudoir, he is delighted with "Old March" wind who
                                             "romps with skirts and dresses," revealing "snowy
                                             frills" and provoking a "wealth of blooming blushes /
                                             Seen through tangled mass of hair!" Here were not only
                                             blushes, but suggestively tangled hair, ladies'
                                             unmentionables, and romping&#8212;a favorite
                                             activity of the sexual adventurer. The poet had in fact
                                             created an entire erotically charged scenario.</p>

                                    <p>Writers of romantic fiction could be just as thorough. Take
                                             the 1870 <hi rend="italic"> Bow Bells </hi>serial <hi
                                                  rend="italic"> Morton's Fate, </hi>a simmering mix
                                             of passion, murder, revenge, separation, and mistaken
                                             identity. Marion and Walter, her divorced husband and
                                             now her lover once more, are together in Paris and
                                             about to marry again. But Marion knows what Walter
                                             cannot&#8212;that their love is destined always to
                                             be thwarted in life. She determines to put an end to
                                             this dire fate by poisoning first him, then herself. As
                                             the story ends, they die in each other's arms,
                                             "passionately entwined as one."</p>

                                    <p>Their final, intense encounter on this earth is imbued with
                                             unspoken sexual appetite. After dining intimately in
                                             Marion's boudoir, they set to "dallying daintily" with
                                             "rich fruits" contained in silver baskets upheld by
                                             nude figurines, and spread sensuously over the table.
                                             She plays the guitar and sings "a tender love ditty."
                                             The accompanying illustration is also infused with the
                                             characters' sexual love. Physical union the dominant
                                             motif, the figures' eyes are locked; she leans back
                                             against his legs. His arm is thrust out, his hand
                                             stroking her hair. Apart from its possibly phallic
                                             connotation, Marion's guitar is the visual device
                                             joining their two bodies. In the making of Victorian
                                             lovemaking, passion was no abstraction. With or without
                                             actual intercourse, it was a bodily reality, integrally
                                             bound up with living&#8212;and, in Marion and
                                             Walter's case, with dying as well.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic"> Sex Symbols </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>Outside of the privacy of the bedroom, the passionate fever
                                             pitch that romantic fiction could reach was not
                                             regularly surpassed. But while Victorian sexuality was
                                             not always openly intense, it was still a constant if
                                             often coy presence in romantic life.</p>

                                    <p>February 14 provided a formal occasion for some tantalizing
                                             glimpses&#8212;eroticism was not far from the
                                             surface of the frills and sentiment of many valentines.
                                             In the verse about hidden treasure, "coral" had a
                                             possibly suggestive association with "coral lips," that
                                             much-loved image of both romantic and pornographic
                                             fiction. "Pearl," meanwhile, was a symbol of female
                                             sexuality and figured often in valentine poetry and
                                             ornament. Another popular motif was the glove, either
                                             in the form of a paper miniature pasted to the card or
                                             an entire valentine shaped like a glove. The motif
                                             signaled a man's serious romantic interest in the
                                             recipient, and often it was an unspoken
                                             proposal&#8212;"prelude to a Ring." Additionally,
                                             as casings into which bodily parts were inserted,
                                             gloves were inescapably colored with erotic overtones.
                                             Not surprisingly, they were among the most beloved
                                             objects of sexual fetishists.</p>

                                    <p>The air of fetishism also lingers about a tiny lady's lace
                                             nightcap, complete with real pink silk ribbons, mounted
                                             on the paper lace background of yet another valentine.
                                             The image was not a common one, but the
                                             message&#8212;"Good night dear"&#8212;captured
                                             a recurring theme. Valentine verses were frequently
                                             evocative of beds and going to bed. Female breasts were
                                             invariably the "pillows" where men longed to lay their
                                             heads, while their women lulled them into "balmy rest"
                                             and "soothing sleep." Weary from "playing the game" all
                                             day, the Victorian man apparently sometimes needed
                                             sleep more than sex. Also, perhaps, he occasionally
                                             confused being sexual with being mothered.</p>

                                    <p>Finding a mother substitute does not appear to have been
                                             foremost in the minds of the young men who gathered
                                             around that bare-legged center of courtship the parlor
                                             piano. Beyond its connection with innocent romance, it
                                             was where male sexuality sometimes aggressively
                                             asserted itself. The piano as a scene of seduction
                                             showed up in Victorian painting&#8212;most notably,
                                             William Holman Hunt's <hi rend="italic"> The Awakening
                                                  Conscience </hi>(1853)&#8212;and in popular
                                             magazine illustrations of the day. As an <hi
                                                  rend="italic"> instrument, </hi>the piano was also
                                             the object of ribald humor. In the comic song "Tuner's
                                             Oppor-tuner-ty," the piano tuner takes a more than
                                             professional interest in his client, Miss Crotchety
                                             Quaver, a young woman whose versatile "playing"
                                             requires regular tuning service:</p>
                                    <lg1 type="poem">
                                             <lg2 type="stanza">
                                                  <l>And to keep her piano in tune she would
                                                  have</l>

                                                  <l> A good tuner constantly there,</l>

                                                  <l>And he'd pull up the instrument three times a
                                                  week, </l>

                                                  <l>Just to keep it in proper repair.</l>
                                             </lg2>
                                             <lg2 type="stanza">
                                                  <l>
                                                  <hi rend="italic"> Chorus: </hi>
                                                  </l>
                                             </lg2>
                                             <lg2 type="stanza">
                                                  <l>And first he'd tune it gently, then he'd tune
                                                  it strong, </l>

                                                  <l>Then he'd touch a short note, then he'd run
                                                  along, </l>

                                                  <l>Then he'd go with vengeance, enough to break
                                                  the key, </l>

                                                  <l>At last he tun'd whene'er he got an
                                                  op-por-tu-ni-ty.</l>
                                             </lg2>
                                    </lg1>

                                    <p>Like many other comic songs, this one was sold as a song
                                             sheet and performed, with appropriate gestures no
                                             doubt, on the music hall stage. There the nudging,
                                             winking style of entertainment enjoyed considerable
                                             license. Clothed in humor, the making of lovemaking
                                             could "go all the way" in full view, with the general
                                             approval of a mass audience. Typically bawdy was an
                                             1890s song called "Starve Her, Joe." It begins with a
                                             married man, Joe, whose domestic tranquility is
                                             disrupted by the extended visit of his wife's mother.
                                             Driven to distraction, he contemplates starving the
                                             offending in-law to death. Quickly coming to his
                                             senses, he abandons this plan and instead seeks solace
                                             with Flo, an attractive lady barber with, as Joe puts
                                             it "such a goo-goo eye / I lay back my head and sigh."
                                             He then launches into a full-frontal chorus:</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">

                                             <l>Lather! lather! lather me, Flo!</l>

                                             <l>Your little brush, it tickles me so-o-o! </l>

                                             <l>But please don't hurt that pimple below </l>

                                             <l>When you start to lather me, Flo!</l>
                                    </lg>

                                    <p>As Joe and most of the audience well knew, "pimple" had two
                                             meanings&#8212;one of which was "a swelling."</p>

                                    <p>Although it did not necessarily go to the lubricious lengths
                                             of the music hall, sexual humor still found a place
                                             offstage. The repertoire of stereographic entertainment
                                             included a lot of light-hearted
                                             naughtiness&#8212;the suitor under the crinoline,
                                             the monk with his naked female "provisions," husbands
                                             dallying with pretty French maids, and so on.
                                             Valentines also had their moments of comic
                                             suggestiveness. In one vignette a hoydenish young woman
                                             (with an impressively large bottom) tries on a type of
                                             men's breeches known as peg-tops. The humor rested on
                                             the double meaning of "peg"&#8212;once clad in the
                                             trousers, the young woman is disappointed to find
                                             something missing. "Oh dear there's nothing in 'em,"
                                             she exclaims:</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">
                                             <l> Call these Peg topsthen I beg </l>

                                             <l>You'll tell me where to find the Peg.</l>
                                    </lg>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic"> Cleaving Together </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>While many Victorians were never averse to a little sexual
                                             humor, most did not allow themselves to be long
                                             diverted from sexuality's serious purpose&#8212;the
                                             procreative marriage. As biology proceeded along a
                                             decorous course toward matrimony, there were certain
                                             rituals and conventions to be observed. Women had their
                                             ways of signaling marriage-mindedness&#8212;eye
                                             contact, blushing, flirting&#8212;but men usually
                                             made the actual proposal. "Man proposes (or at least
                                             should do so) and woman disposes," was the wisdom of
                                             the day, and few would have thought to challenge it.
                                             The heroes of fiction and their counterparts in
                                             everyday life produced gold rings with a flourish, or
                                             fell to their knees in romantic entreaty, or otherwise
                                             declared their matrimonial intentions. "Name the day
                                             ... that makes thee mine" was the plea of many men who
                                             sent valentines, while the poet Ashby-Sterry ended his
                                             "Lover's Lullaby" on a similar note:</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">
                                             <l>Mirror your fate, then, in mine, love; </l>

                                             <l>Sorrow and sighing resign:</l>

                                             <l>Life is too short to repine, love, </l>

                                             <l>Link your fair future in mine!</l>
                                    </lg>

                                    <p>Although there were always exceptions and variations
                                             according to class, the general expectation was that
                                             the engagement was the time for a couple to enjoy
                                             increasing physical intimacy, but to stop short of
                                             premarital sexual intercourse. As the wedding date
                                             approached, those who adhered to this regime of going
                                             just so far, but not the whole distance, found their
                                             sexual tension growing and their restraint weakening.
                                             Men and women alike thus looked forward eagerly to the
                                             wedding night. Of course, anticipation did not mean
                                             that there were no prenuptial anxieties. For all her
                                             genuine passion, Charles Kingsley's bride-to-be Fanny
                                             confessed to a certain amount of fear mixed with her
                                             sexual yearning. Her groom meanwhile was wrestling with
                                             his own worry. "The blaze of your naked beauty," he
                                             confided anxiously, might dazzle him into
                                             impotence.</p>

                                    <p>As it turned out, all went well in the Kingsleys' conjugal
                                             bed. Sexual gratification was in fact what a majority
                                             of about-to-be-married Victorian couples optimistically
                                             looked forward to. Pictures and verses in wedding cards
                                             represented this hopeful longing and the imminent joys
                                             of consummation. A card from the 1880s depicts a bride
                                             and groom in their bedroom, alone at last, kissing
                                             tenderly. "What...oft they dreamt, and oft they longed
                                             for" was about to become, as the card's poet expressed
                                             it, "reality at last":</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">
                                             <l>And the veil, in sweet caresses, </l>

                                             <l>Yields to love's most ardent touch; </l>

                                             <l>Gently then they draw the curtain </l>

                                             <l>To hide love's secret with a blush.</l>
                                    </lg>

                                    <p>Even pornography, usually unsentimental, was apt to soften a
                                             little when it turned to the theme of newly wedded
                                             bliss. A turn-of-the-century pornographer's catalogue
                                             of "Photographic Novelties" unctuously advertised a
                                             series of images of "The First Wedding Night": "The
                                             preludes of love, the clever caresses, the endless
                                             ecstacies and then the carnal refinements, the search
                                             after the new, the unknown and lastly prostrated, the
                                             felicity of the total initiation."</p>

                                    <p>After the first joys of consummation had subsided, sex
                                             remained at the core of the healthy Victorian marriage.
                                             Not everyone experienced sensual fulfillment as intense
                                             as that of the Kingsleys&#8212;what made for a
                                             happy sexual relationship varied from couple to couple.
                                             Still, there were broad guidelines for establishing and
                                             maintaining appropriate and rewarding marital
                                             relations. Those who sought sexual knowledge or the
                                             improvement of their conjugal lives could always turn
                                             to one of the many manuals whose advice helped to shape
                                             marital lovemaking.</p>

                                    <p>Frequency of intercourse was a standard theme. The experts,
                                             mostly physicians and doctors of divinity, agreed that
                                             sexual moderation was the ideal and that excesses were
                                             to be avoided. This view arose not out of prudery but
                                             in part out of a belief in the necessity of spermatic
                                             economy&#8212;the end result of the overexpenditure
                                             of seed might be the moral, intellectual, and physical
                                             degeneration of the human race. Or so believed a number
                                             of commentators, among them Sylvanus Stall, who wrote
                                             several sex manuals published in Canada, England, and
                                             the United States. In <hi rend="italic"> What a Young
                                                  Husband Ought to Know</hi>(part of an 1897-1902
                                             series called Sex and Self), Stall, like other
                                             authorities, was concerned for the general health of
                                             couples. Too much sex, he cautioned, might be "most
                                             ruinous" to the health of the wife and lead to a host
                                             of fearful conditions in the husband: "backache,
                                             lassitude, giddiness, dimness of sight, noises in the
                                             ears, numbness of fingers and paralysis."</p>

                                    <p>But how much was too much? The experts were not entirely
                                             dogmatic and, to a point, allowed for individual
                                             preferences and circumstances. Most offered some
                                             general direction as well. A few recommended relations
                                             every twenty to thirty days. A greater number
                                             considered once a week to be sounder practice for
                                             maintaining a satisfactory bond of "mutual affection"
                                             between husband and wife. Pregnancy, however, changed
                                             matters. By and large, greater than usual moderation
                                             was the rule, although Stall advocated complete
                                             abstinence.</p>

                                    <p>It is impossible to know with any certainty the extent to
                                             which Victorian couples followed the experts' advice,
                                             and how often most actually made love&#8212;there
                                             were then no national polls or statistical averages. In
                                             1892 Dr. Clelia Mosher of Stanford University conducted
                                             a survey of about forty-five middle-class American
                                             women. Her sampling was too small to permit sweeping
                                             conclusions, but it is not unreasonable to take it as a
                                             general indicator of more widespread behavior among the
                                             prosperous middle classes. On average the women
                                             reported having sex once a week, while a few indulged
                                             more often. At the lower ends of the economic scale, it
                                             is probably likely that frequency declined. Exhausting
                                             labor, poverty, and lack of privacy were not conducive
                                             to sexual activity.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic">Sex and the Married Woman</hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>The writers of marriage manuals tended to overlook the
                                             existence of an impoverished working class. In the
                                             world of sex experts the ideal of the well-off
                                             middle-class family reigned supreme. From such a
                                             privileged vantage point, the feeding of extra mouths
                                             was not an overriding concern, and the ready consensus
                                             was that the primary purpose of sex was procreation.
                                             Sexual feeling, wrote Dr. Mary Wood-Allen in her 1899
                                             advice book <hi rend="italic"> What a Young Woman Ought
                                                  to Know, </hi>"is the indication of the possession
                                             of the most sacred powers, that of the perpetuation of
                                             life. Passion is the instinct for preservation of one's
                                             kind, the voice of the life principle, the sign of
                                             creative power."</p>

                                    <p>But the reproductive purpose of sex did not mean a negation
                                             of pleasure. Dr. Wood-Allen was quick to refer
                                             approvingly to "throbbing and pulsing in every fibre."
                                             In Stall's opinion, pleasure was one of the strongest
                                             arguments for moderation. Indulge "every slight
                                             inclination" and oversatiation would be the unhappy
                                             result, but exercise a degree of moderation and
                                             "realize the greatest pleasure and satisfaction." Dr.
                                             R. T. Trall, author of <hi rend="italic"> Sexual
                                                  Physiology,</hi>published in 1870, counseled
                                             people to set aside whole days for making love. Whether
                                             the object of such activity was a "love embrace merely"
                                             or a "generative act," he was convinced that it should
                                             be pleasurable to husband and wife alike. "Surely," he
                                             insisted, "if sexual intercourse is worth doing at all,
                                             it is worth doing well."</p>

                                    <p>It is one of those enduring myths about the Victorians that
                                             sexual pleasure was a disproportionately male
                                             enjoyment, and that women on the whole were
                                             indifferent. The misconception arose principally out of
                                             the work of the now notorious Dr. William Acton, an
                                             "expert" on the "evil habit" of masturbation and other
                                             sexual matters. In his 1857 treatise, <hi rend="italic"
                                                  > The Functions and Disorders of the Reproductive
                                                  Organs, </hi>he pronounced with chauvinist
                                             certainty that "the majority of women (happily for
                                             them) are not very much troubled with sexual feeling of
                                             any kind." Of course, he admitted with spurious
                                             fair-mindedness, there were exceptional women who
                                             experienced "sexual excitement." But this, he hastened
                                             to add, invariably progressed to "nymphomania, a form
                                             of insanity which those accustomed to visit lunatic
                                             asylums must be fully conversant with."</p>

                                    <p>Acton was read widely in his day, and his opinions were
                                             undoubtedly given some credence. For instance, they
                                             validated the asexuality that was simply some women's
                                             nature. Perhaps they also alleviated the guilt of those
                                             in whom ill health had diminished sexual interest. But
                                             many Victorian authorities on sexuality had grave
                                             doubts about Acton's views and even his competence.
                                             Others simply ignored him and propounded their own
                                             ideas. Stall for one considered that the "largest
                                             number" of women took at least moderate pleasure in the
                                             sex act. He also acknowledged another, smaller group
                                             "in whom sexuality presides as a ruling passion....
                                             Such women should never be married except to men of
                                             good health, strong physique, large powers of
                                             endurance, and with a pronounced sexual
                                             inclination."</p>

                                    <p>He also described a third group that on the surface appears
                                             to be indistinguishable from Acton's sexually
                                             anesthetic women. But a closer look shows that Stall
                                             did not regard some women's sexual coldness as either
                                             inevitable or healthy. It was a correctable condition
                                             whose causes were varied. Indigestible food, late
                                             hours, and general debility from too little fresh air
                                             and exercise all contributed to sexual malaise. So,
                                             too, did excessive novel-reading, tight lacing, and
                                             chronic constipation. He did not say so directly, but
                                             the implication is also there that some women might
                                             have overreacted to Acton and his misogynist kind and
                                             come to believe that frigidity was very nearly a
                                             virtue.</p>

                                    <p>Not least of all, Stall blamed ignorance. Of this both
                                             husband and wife might be guilty, but the greatest onus
                                             for knowledge and consideration he placed on the man.
                                             Ignorance could lead to clumsy and unintentionally
                                             brutal lovemaking on the husband's part&#8212;and
                                             on the wife's, permanent aversion. An informed and
                                             considerate approach, Stall maintained, would make all
                                             the difference between a "disgusted" bride and "a union
                                             of lifelong happiness." Quoting from Mrs. Eliza B.
                                             Duffey, a contemporary authority on "the relations of
                                             the sexes," he counseled new husbands to "practice in
                                             lawful wedlock the arts of the seducer rather than the
                                             violence of the man who commits rape, and you will find
                                             the reward of your patience very sweet and
                                             lasting."</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic"> Getting Satisfaction </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>No doubt many Victorian husbands never became as well versed
                                             as they ought to have been in the fine art of wife
                                             seduction. Even so, their wives were not necessarily
                                             sexually unsatisfied. Quite the opposite, often. In
                                             fiction just-married heroines typically took on "new
                                             beauty" or "the blossom of wifehood"&#8212;the
                                             signals of recently discovered physical satisfaction.
                                             In a more forthright vein, greater than a third of the
                                             women in Dr. Mosher's survey reported experiencing
                                             orgasm "always" or "usually"; another 40 percent said
                                             "sometimes" or "not always." Even among the remaining
                                             women&#8212;about a quarter of the whole
                                             group&#8212;there were some who at least
                                             occasionally felt arousal.</p>

                                    <p>Other middle-class American wives indicated general sexual
                                             contentment through their language and tone in letters
                                             to their husbands. One woman wrote playfully to her
                                             absent husband in the summer of 1873: "How are you this
                                             hot day? I am most roasted and my chemise sticks to me
                                             and the sweat runs down my legs.... don't you wish you
                                             could be around just now." Another wife's sexual
                                             longing was too great for teasing. "I like you to want
                                             me, dear," she wrote to her husband in 1883, "and if I
                                             were only with you, I would embrace more than the back
                                             of your neck, be sure."</p>

                                    <p>For all their expressiveness, these women, the many others
                                             like them, and the men with whom they exchanged loving
                                             letters all preserved a characteristically Victorian
                                             reticence when it came to what, precisely, gave them
                                             erotic pleasure. Even most marriage manuals were
                                             unforthcoming about the mechanics of lovemaking. Stall,
                                             among others, says nothing on the subject. Such
                                             discretion need not be narrowly interpreted as prudery,
                                             nor even as fastidiousness with regard to subject
                                             matter. Saying nothing about the technical particulars
                                             served the sexual mystique of the day. It left room for
                                             variation and experimentation, as long as no one
                                             violated the general rule of mutual pleasure.</p>

                                    <p>At least one expert, however, was more explicit&#8212;and
                                             dogmatic. This was a French medical man, Auguste Debay,
                                             the author of <hi rend="italic"> Hygiene et physiologie
                                                  du mariage, </hi>published in 1848 and reprinted
                                             throughout the century. Debay insisted that the only
                                             "natural" and "normal" way of making love was in the
                                             missionary position. His conviction arose from an
                                             assumption of general male superiority as much as it
                                             did from a notion of appropriate intercourse. In bed or
                                             elsewhere, men "naturally" belonged on top. Many of his
                                             contemporaries no doubt agreed and, coincidentally or
                                             not, enjoyed sex in the missionary position.
                                             Nevertheless, it is hard to imagine the populace of a
                                             country famed for its lovemaking unanimously and
                                             invariably obeying Debay's authoritarian stricture.</p>

                                    <p>And, looking across the Channel, it appears no less
                                             inconceivable that upon marriage, versatile English
                                             eroticism could universally subside into missionary
                                             monotony. Kingsley for one had a lively sexual
                                             imagination. How could he have been content with
                                             marital relations limited to the missionary
                                             position&#8212;even though he undoubtedly had a
                                             tendency to mix religion with sex. Take off your
                                             clothes and pray, he had once suggested to Fanny. "Then
                                             lie down, nestle to me, clasp your arms and every limb
                                             around me, and with me repeat the <hi rend="italic"> Te
                                                  Deum </hi>aloud." Eccentric Anglican clergyman
                                             though he might have been, Charles Kingsley was no
                                             puritan missionary.</p>

                                    <p>Whatever the ways in which individual couples chose to make
                                             love, the joys of marriage, including its physical
                                             side, were ideally supposed to last. In his manual for
                                             young husbands, Stall hinted at "the later years" of
                                             marriage, which could bring with them "the largest
                                             possible good and blessing." In 1901 he would follow up
                                             the hint with a further volume, <hi rend="italic">What
                                                  a Man of 45 Ought to Know.</hi> Romantic fiction
                                             offered a similarly optimistic view, and many of its
                                             couples continued to enjoy "perfect bliss" and
                                             "passionate devotion" long after marrying.</p>

                                    <p>In real life, frequency of intercourse perhaps declined over
                                             time&#8212;or so the Mosher survey suggests but in
                                             many marriages, romance and sexual pleasure endured
                                             throughout the years. Among the love letters preserved
                                             from Victorian America, a number attest to the
                                             longevity of marital passion. In 1856 Nathaniel
                                             Hawthorne, famed author of <hi rend="italic"> The
                                                  Scarlet Letter </hi>and other novels, expressed
                                             the fervid sentiments of many when he declared to his
                                             wife of fourteen years: <q rend="block">Oh, dearest,
                                                  dearest, interminably and infinitely
                                                  dearest&#8212;I don't know how to end that
                                                  ejaculation. The use of kisses and caresses is,
                                                  that they supersede language, and express what
                                                  there are no words for. I need them at this
                                                  moment&#8212;need to give them and to receive
                                                  them.</q></p>

                                    <p>Not unexpectedly, Hawthorne's enthusiasm was perhaps exceeded
                                             only by the erotic devotion of Kingsley. During a brief
                                             separation in the first year of his marriage, he
                                             tantalized his wife with the question, "Shall we the
                                             first night we meet reenact our marriage night?" "Oh!"
                                             he exclaimed, "to be once again with you&#8212;to
                                             lie once more naked in your arms." A half-dozen years
                                             later, in May 1850, separation still made him
                                             physically long for her. "These soft, hot damp days
                                             fill me with yearning love," he wrote. "Your image
                                             haunts me day and night as it did before we were
                                             married, and the thought of that delicious
                                             sanctuary"&#8212;but here the fantasy breaks off.
                                             No less passionate but more discreet than her husband,
                                             Fanny had carefully inked over his amorous
                                             revelation.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div>
                                    <head>
                                             <hi rend="italic">To the Bridal Altar Go </hi>
                                    </head>

                                    <p>While most Victorian husbands might not have been as
                                             articulate as Kingsley, there were many as
                                             passionate&#8212;and with wives as compatible as
                                             Fanny. As the nineteenth century progressed, more and
                                             more people strove toward this conjugal ideal. The
                                             number of marriages grew during the Victorian years, as
                                             the marital norm became increasingly central in the
                                             making of lovemaking. Common-law arrangements
                                             progressively decreased until they survived only among
                                             the poorest, who tended to keep quiet about their
                                             irregular circumstances. For those of means marriage
                                             had longer been the established norm, but it was more
                                             firmly entrenched than ever by the turn of the
                                             century.</p>

                                    <p>Some advertising did not fail to use the norm to its own
                                             advantage. An attractive pictorial advertisement for
                                             Pears' Soap featured the image of a young woman sitting
                                             in a field and plucking petals from a daisy.
                                             Superimposed were a few lines of appropriately
                                             "romantic" verse:</p>

                                    <lg type="poem">
                                             <l>A Maiden's Wishes </l>

                                             <l>&#8212;are but three.</l>

                                             <l>O'er all the world, whoe'er she be&#8212;</l>

                                             <l>To handsome grow,</l>

                                             <l>And have a beau,</l>

                                             <l>And to the bridal altar go&#8212;</l>

                                             <l>All these fruitions of her hope</l>

                                             <l>Come quickly if she'll</l>

                                             <l>USE PEARS' SOAP</l>

                                    </lg>

                                    <p>With or without the help of Pears' Soap, women not only
                                             increasingly got married but, as far as their families
                                             could afford, ever more favored elaborate and colorful
                                             weddings to mark the day. In the last two decades of
                                             the nineteenth century, bridesmaids wore colored gowns,
                                             instead of the traditional white. For brides, the
                                             shades of preference were cream or ivory, rather than
                                             stark white; other popular choices were by later
                                             standards startling&#8212;claret velvet,
                                             purplish-brown satin, gray corded silk. In contrast,
                                             the bridegroom and his attendants became less colorful.
                                             As the popular notion of masculinity grew more rigid,
                                             the male members of the wedding party gave up shades of
                                             blue, claret, and mulberry. By the 1890s the only
                                             acceptable color for a frock coat was black. </p>

                                    <p>Not everyone was happy with the ideal that middle-class
                                             weddings represented. Here and there the voices of
                                             dissent spoke out against the marital norm. A number of
                                             late-Victorian feminists were critical of marriage and
                                             its embedded premise that women were property. These
                                             and other women also wanted greater educational and
                                             political rights, as well as marital reform. In 1893
                                             still others&#8212;men as well as
                                             women&#8212;founded the Legitimation League to
                                             protest against conventional marriage, advocate free
                                             love, and demand legal rights for children born out of
                                             wed-lock. Meanwhile, the majority of men and women took
                                             little notice of these voices. As the century ended,
                                             they were absorbed in falling in love and planning
                                             romantic weddings.</p>

                                    <p>In yet another sphere, still far removed from most common
                                             experience, the sexologists were at work distinguishing
                                             and describing the "normal" and the "pathological,"
                                             turning sex into definitions of standard or deviant
                                             modes of behavior&#8212;talk, that is. Although
                                             their efforts escaped the attention of most people,
                                             there appeared a few signs in everyday life that sex
                                             was already less a total affair of the body than it had
                                             been not long before. By 1900 new, matter-of-fact
                                             fictional heroines tended not to blush, or at least not
                                             so readily as their predecessors. Suitors, accordingly,
                                             were not so apt to turn "gelatinous" in their presence.
                                             At the same time, the odd sex manual was inclined to
                                             equate sexual love with effective technique, rather
                                             than with individual passion and bodily response. </p>

                                    <p>But even as the nineteenth century gave way to the next, such
                                             signals were still sporadic and faint. The making of
                                             lovemaking retained most of its old devotion to
                                             passion. At once profoundly romantic and physical, the
                                             mystique of carefully nurtured eroticism had not yet
                                             dissolved into analytical talk. Throughout the
                                             Victorian age, for countless lovers, both courting and
                                             married, sex radiated much of the "sweetness and light"
                                             that the poet and moralist Matthew Arnold envisioned in
                                             a perfect world. Inevitably, though, in a less than
                                             perfect reality there were unlit places shadowy corners
                                             where most lovers, content in the felicity of the norm,
                                             never cared to venture. In such places passion's aspect
                                             darkened.</p>
                           </div>

                  </body>
         </text>
</TEI.2>
