<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00002">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">
               <hi rend="italic">Love in the Time of Victoria: Sexuality, Class and Gender in
                  Nineteenth Century London</hi>
            </title>

            <title level="j" type="journal"/>
            <title level="c" type="chapter"/>
            <title level="m" type="monograph"/>
            <author name="Barret-Decrocq">Fran&#231;oise Barret-Decrocq</author>
            <date type="original" value=""/>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00002</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century
               Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in
                  the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                  copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to
                  reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the
                  originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project"> Transcribed from the Verso Press edition of Fran&#231;oise
               Barret-Ducrocq's <hi rend="italic">Love in the Time of Victoria: Sexuality, Class and
                  Gender in Nineteenth-Century London</hi>, pages 97, 98, 100, 102-3, 105-6, 109,
               and 112. Translation by John Howe; originally published in 1991. </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


            <bibl>
               <title level="a">Love and Marriage</title>
               <title level="m">
                  <hi rend="italic">Love in the Time of Victoria: Sexuality, Class and Gender in
                     Nineteenth-Century London</hi>
               </title>
               <author>Fran&#231;oise Barret-Ducrocq</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher> Verso </publisher>
                  <pubPlace> London </pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date> 1991 </date>
               <idno type="ISBN"> 0860913252 </idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
               <term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
               <term id="premaritalsex" type="theme">premarital sex</term>
               <term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
               <term id="british" type="place">British</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-08-18">18 August 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-03-15">15 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

         <change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Zach Bajaber</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1.</head>
            <p>"Carnal relations between young people have always been tolerated by the working
               classes in Western Europe, on the express condition that they are followed soon
               afterwards by marriage" (97).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. </head>
            <p>"This freedom of behaviour, specific to the working classes, was determined by one
               element: the 'promise of marriage'. Only this promise, which in traditional practice
               bound the man by his word of honour, could authorize pre-marital sexual relations. It
               thus traced the real dividing line between permissible and delinquent conduct"
               (98).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. </head>
            <p>"The given word was still invested with such symbolic importance that it was enough
               merely to pronounce in private, orally or by letter, for our young women to regard it
               as a solemn oath. Of course we have no exact transcripts of these declarations, made
               at the moment of engagement or during the sexual act. But it seems reasonable to
               suppose that young women would have expected something formal, probably no more than
               'I promise to marry you'. Whatever the actual phrase, it appears to have retained its
               contractual significance even when uttered during the blaze of sexual passion, or not
               even pronounced until after the act" (100).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. </head>
            <p>"What was the setting for these sexual frolics?  For the most part, they seem to have
               occurred in everyday surroundings, in the workplace or at home. Romantic <hi
                  rend="italic">billets-doux</hi>, the exaltation of grand passion, are not much in
               evidence here. Quite often the act was performed in the workplace, in the lodger's
               room or in the home of the girl's parents. The house would perhaps have been empty,
               with some people on holiday or on a visit, others at work, the children asleep.
               People would make love in places where they spent a lot of time: domestics, for
               example, in the kitchen, others in their rooms. This was especially true where the
               couple both worked for the same employer or lived in the same lodgings: the normal
               setting was the girl's room, or the boy's room, or the kitchen; sometimes as
               'upstairs' room or the servants' hall" (102-3).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5. </head>
            <p>"Skilled workers, shop assistants, commercial travelers, policemen and other
               categories close to the petty bourgeoisie were the first to acquire a taste for
               Sunday outings in the country. Among domestics, sexual advances were more often
               inspired by the change of scene during their employers' holidays" (105).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>6. </head>
            <p>"The Hansom cab, that enclosed public place whose steady progress reminded the couple
               of their imminent separation, was the scene of many seductions:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">He took me home in a cab and effected his purpose of violence as we
                  were returning.</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">We occasionally walked out and in December he took me in a cab
                  where Crim. Con took place.</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">He seduced me in Aug 1866 in a cab we were going from Uxbridge to
                  Gerrards X...</hi>
            </p>

            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Father seduced me in a cab as we were out. C.C. was repeated in the
                  same manner and he also took me to a coffee house" </hi>(105-6).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>7. </head>
            <p>"A popular song composed and sung by the famous musical hall artiste Arthur Lloyd
               suggests that a girl could change her mind at any moment, and that the culprit would
               then be punished for his persistence:</p>

            <lg type="poem">
               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">I followed her home and to speak to her tried,</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">She said 'Why d'ye follow me?' and I replied,</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">'I love you dear girl and would make you my bride,'</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">You Know!...</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">Then she said, 'Well, I like you, but silence beware!</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">You know!</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">I've a very stern parent his bedroom's up there! You know!'</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">I struggled to kiss her, she gave a loud cry,</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">I heard a door open and ere I could fly,</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">A very hard fist struck me twice in the eye! You know!...</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">A policeman appeared and exclaimed 'What's all this?' You
                     know!</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">'Oh,' said I, 'a young girl I was trying to kiss!' You
                     know!</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">To the station he marched me at a very quick pace...</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">His Worship exclaimed, when the case he had tried,</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">'Forty shillings or one month' with horror I cried</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">'Forty shilling or one month, for what&#8212;' he
                     replied:</hi>
               </l>

               <l>
                  <hi rend="italic">'You know!' </hi>(109)</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>8. </head>
            <p>"One last hypothesis: the public admission of indecisiveness, of humming and hawing
               at the moment of the sexual act, may be the first sign of a new, more modest
               attitude, or perhaps susceptibility to guilt about pre-nuptial sex" (112).</p>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
