<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" []>

<TEI.2 id="ls.00078">
   <teiHeader>


<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Murder of Helen Jewett:  The Life and Death of a Prostitute in Nineteenth-Century New York</hi></title>
		<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapter 9, "Reading and Imagination," and Chapter 10, "Tracing Seduction"</title>
		<date type="original" value="1998">1998</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author name="Cohen">Patricia Cline Cohen
</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00078</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">Transcribed from pages 173-76, 184, and 200-01 of Patricia Cline Cohen's <hi rend="italic">The Murder of Helen Jewett:  The Life and Death of a Prostitute in Nineteenth-Century New York</hi>.  Published by Knopf, 1998.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter 9, "Reading and Imagination," and Chapter 10, "Tracing Seduction"</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Murder of Helen Jewett:  The Life and Death of a Prostitute in Nineteenth-Century New York</hi></title>
               <author>Patricia Cline Cohen</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Alfred A. Knopf

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1998

</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
0679412913

</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>


<keywords>
               <term id="boudoir" type="setting">boudoir</term>
               <term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>

<term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>

<term id="courtship" type="theme">courtship</term>

<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>

<term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>

<term id="premaritalsex" type="theme">premarital sex</term>

<term id="fictioninpress">fiction in press</term>

<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-08-18">18 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-21">21 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>preliminary coding and edit</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <div><head>1.</head><p>"Another form of reading available to Dorcas [Dorcas Doyen; later pseudonymously known as "Helen Jewett"] during her Augusta [Maine] years was the . . . <hi rend="italic">Maine Patriot and Gazette</hi>. . . . In its brief five-year publication run (1827 to 1831), it frequently carried amusing essays and small news items on love, courtship, marriage, and the relations between the sexes in general.
         </p>
<p>The very first issue of the <hi rend="italic">Patriot and Gazette</hi>, for example, carried an original article titled 'The Influence of Novels and Romances on the Morals.' . . .  The author argued that novels, and especially historical fictions, were eminently suitable reading because it was possible to learn 'profitable lessons' from characterizations of fictional people, both the good&#8212;like the chivalrous Richard I and the bad&#8212;for example, the 'licentious profligacy of Charles II.'  Novels 'vivify the imagination . . . they tend to raise the spirits' and present 'human nature in its liveliest colours,' all features to be admired.  Of course, some novels were admitted to be 'pernicious' in their effect&#8212;Fielding, Rochester, and Smollett were singled out as perhaps dangerous.  But Richardson, Socott, and Irving got the seal of approval as being both educational and simply good to read.  The use of the authors' last names alone shows that the Maine newspaper expected its Augusta readers to be familiar with the works in question, even as [it] acknowledged that controversy existed over the propriety of reading them.</p>
<p>Over the months, the weekly <hi rend="italic">Patriot</hi> embellished its columns with small articlees on personal advice for navigating the world of relationships between the sexes. . . . A November 1827 article on matrimony declared that the happiest marriages occurred when 'the contracting parties were of a condition nearly equal; so that when the first ardours of love are abated by time, neither can assume a superiority, or think it a condescention [sic] to have acceded to the nuptial alliance.'  The servant Dorcas would not have found this advice encouraging; a girl with designs on someone in her employer's class might have read it as a rebuke or a timely reminder to a young man in danger of taking such a girl too seriously. . . ." </p></div>
<div>
            
<head>2.</head><p>"The <hi rend="italic">Patriot'</hi>s youthful focus on courtship
and marriage articles could have helped a young girl from Maine backcountry
understand the mores and expectations for courting behavior among young men and
women of the Augusta elite. The <hi rend="italic">Patriot </hi>approved of women's
outrageously wide shoulders and blousy sleeves of fashionable dress; it took
its readers on a tour or 'Peep into the Seraglio,' the harem of sultans. The
paper made a bid for laughs with slightly suggestive stories, like one about a
misunderstanding between a Frenchman and an American girl over the phrase 'be
easy,' taken for 'baiser' (to kiss) by the man, or another titled 'Flirtation,'
with characters Edmund Weston and Helen Clapp. They even referred to a poem
about 'Black Sal, or Dusky Sally,' the alleged slave paramour of Thomas
Jefferson of forty years before&#8212;and this in a Democratic paper, the party
claiming to be heir to the party of Jefferson. The paper reflected a playful
1820s sensibility about courtship, friendship, and romance: suggestive but not
ribald, upholding good morals but without being prudish in the least.</p>

         <p>Even direct curiosity about sex
could be tastefully handled, the paper demonstrated. In August 1828 the <hi rend="italic">Patriot
</hi>advertised a traveling lecture show that would teach young Augustans the
fundamentals of sex and reproduction. Dr. Williams's 'anatomical preparations
in wax' of the human body could be seen at the Masonic Hall on Water Street
from eight in the morning until four in the afternoon&#8212;seen by men only, that
is. There was a Mrs. Williams too, and she presented the waxed figures to a
ladies-only audience, between four and seven in the evening. Admission for
this diverting and edifying entertainment was twenty-five cents" (172-76).</p>
</div>
<div>
                   <head>3.</head><p>"Newspaper of the 1820s and 1830s, including the <hi rend="italic">Patriot,
</hi>routinely covered one other form of news about sex: court cases over
breach of promise suits, culled from other newspapers in distant
jurisdictions. (Civil suits over seduction were much less common but no less
interesting to readers.) Such news items were usually just small snippets of a
story, a column inch or two, telling the two most essential points&#8212;how the
fellow deserted the girl and how much she recovered in the way of damages. For
example, in February 1829 the <hi rend="italic">Patriot </hi>ran an item from a Boston paper about a Wayne County, New York, girl, pregnant and jilted on her wedding
day. The jury awarded her $500, somewhat on the low side for successful
suits. From such stories, uncommonly enacted in the courts but widely
reprinted in the press, young men and women in the throes of courtship learned
about the substantial costs of transgressive behavior. Pregnant brides could
wind up deserted; grooms on the lam could be out anywhere from $500 to $1,500.</p>

         <p>In September 1828 the <hi rend="italic">Patriot </hi>carried
a small notice of a New York City civil action for breach of promise, involving
a clerk who courted his landlady's daughter for seven years and then suddenly
married another. The jury awarded the aggrieved girl $1,500. A much fuller
account of the same story appeared in the Hallowell paper, the <hi rend="italic">American
Advocate</hi> . . . . The <hi rend="italic">Advocate </hi>reported that the clerk was seventeen, the
girl fifteen, when the courtship began. Seven years later the clerk married
another, and his lawyer argued on his behalf that any man can be a victim of
the 'uncontrollable nature of true love'; when 'passion touches his breast...he
does not look into Blackstone.' The lawyer was William Price, one of Richard
Robinson's lawyers in 1836, when he would again defend a New York clerk charged
with an offense against a lover. In the 1828 trial, Price took the line that a
young man was entitled to marital passion and happiness, and that having
suddenly found it with a new woman, he was right to abandon the old love&#8212;in
fact, to marry the first girl knowing he did not love her would have been a
disservice to her. The lawyer for the young woman countered by saying that
Lawyer Price, a bachelor, had no understanding of marriage; when the defendant
put a ring on the plaintiff's finger and whispered in her ear (what, it
apparently mattered not), clearly a pledge of marriage had been made. He
appealed to the men of the jury, all married, to consider the obligations of
engagement; the plaintiff had even tended the defendant in illness, a gesture
of service presumably denoting an expected return. Thus a circumstantial
promise of marriage was confirmed, and the jury found for the young woman. How
the young clerk, now twenty-four, managed to come up with the enormous $1,500
fine is nowhere part of the record" (176-77).</p>
</div>
<div>
                     <head>4.</head><p>"Seduction suits were an old and, until the 1820s,
a largely underutilized feature of English common law. Under strict
application of the law, fathers, masters, or guardians of seduced women could
bring a tort action under trespass law to recover damages for loss of service.
The key idea was loss of service and attendant damage to a man's property in a
woman: a seduction allegedly undermined ability to perform duties to parent or
master. Pregnancy was not essential to the action, but it did increase both
the credibility of the plaintiff's case (in proving the sexual intercourse had
taken place) and the prospect of recovering demonstrable expenses and damages.
Under the traditional grounds for the suit, the complicity of the girl in the
intercourse was immaterial, oddly enough; this was a legal dispute between
men. If a father or master encouraged a romance, say, by permitting bundling
to occur&#8212;night courting in a bed alone&#8212;then it was difficult to persuade a
judge to award damages.</p>

         <p>Seduction suits surged in popularity in the
early nineteenth century. In the years between 1815 and 1830, courts
increasingly entertained cases of jilted brides and desolate or pregnant lovers
and began to award fairly hefty damages, typically from five hundred dollars to
two thousand dollars. Judges often remarked in their opinions that they were
departing from the old fictions of lost service and were really compensating
women and their families for loss of reputation, emotional damage, and lowered
marriage chances. Women were now construed to be the victims of seduction, not
complicit participants" (184).</p>
</div>
         <div>
            <head>5.</head><p>"Stories and novels featuring seduction plots
gained renewed popularity in the early nineteenth century, featuring women
victims who typically suffered from madness or death after lustful men ruined
them. In a case of life imitating art, seduction suits in court reinforced the
message; large sums of money measured a woman's ruination. Both law cases and
seduction fictions accorded an increased value to female virginity. Underlying
both was an assumption that women's sexual desires were not nearly as strong as
men's; a belief in women's general 'passionlessness' took hold. Seduction
happened because of male lust and female innocence; women's lower sexual energy
effectively diminished their responsibility for sex.</p>

         <p>The illogical part in this formulation was that
the presumed innocent victim, the passionless woman, bore the brunt of the
social punishment. But at the same time, it was an effective formulation: it
gave the party thought to be least likely to succumb to sexual temptation the
extra motivation to put the brakes on any illicit behavior. The outcome of
irreparable damage to a woman's reputation and prospects powerfully discouraged
her from agreeing to illicit sex" (200-01).</p></div>

         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
