<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00014">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"Badgered Beecher"
</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author>
</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00014</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 4 of the April 27, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Badgered Beecher</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
April 27, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="beechertilton">Beecher-Tilton</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

          <head>Badgered Beecher</head>
         
<head>Plymouth Church Experiences Another Throe
of the Great Moral Earthquake.</head>
         

            <head>MRS. TILTON TELLS AGAIN.</head>
         
<head>This Time she Swears it is so, for she Cannot Tell a Lie,
and she did it &#8212; with her Little Hatch-it.</head>
         
            <head>THE BIGGEST CACKLE ON RECORD.</head>
         
         <p>A quiet man of thirty-five, walked into the
newspaper offices of this city, on Monday afternoon, 15th inst.,
with a slip of paper in his hand, on which was printed the following:</p>

	<text type="correspondence">
		<body>
		<opener>
         <salute>"Mr. Ira B. Wheeler.</salute></opener>

         <p>"My Dear Sir: A few weeks since, after long
months of mental anguish, I told, as you know, a few friends, whom I had
bitterly deceived, that the charge brought by my husband of adultery between
myself and the Rev. Henry Ward Beecher was true, and that the lie I had lived
so well the last four years had become intolerable to me. That statement I now
solemnly reaffirm, and leave the truth with God, to whom also I commit myself,
my children and all who must suffer. I know full well the explanations that
will be sought by many for this acknowledgment &#8212; a desire to return to my
husband, insanity, malice, everything save the true and only one: my quickened
conscience and the sense of what is due to the cause of truth and justice.
During all the complications of these years you have been my confidential
friend, and therefore, I address this letter to you, authorizing and requesting
you to secure in publication.</p>

         <closer>"Elizabeth R. Tilton.</closer>

         <dateline>"Brooklyn, April 13, 1878."</dateline>
		</body>
		</text>

         <p>The bearer was Mr. Wheeler himself, and he
modestly said that he had been asked by Mrs. Tilton to give it to the
newspapers. He was closely quizzed and he said that he had been a friend and
adviser of Mrs. Tilton, having known her from childhood. He is a New York lawyer, and a resident of Elizabeth, N.J. Since her separation from Theodore he
has acted professionally as her counsel. Being asked about the confession, he
said that she freely made it, unbeknown either to her husband or to Mr.
Beecher. He believed it was a sincere one, and that it was made from no other
motive than the one given therein. Her conscience was troubling her, and it
was a matter between her and her God to confess her sin as publicly as she had denied it.</p>

         
         <p>Being asked whether she had made the same confession to him,
Mr. Wheeler answered that she had and to other persons also. Mr. Wheeler was
manifestly sincere in what he said, and he convinced all with whom he spoke
that the confession was genuine. The news fell like a thunderbolt on the Beecher party, although they one and all said they had been expecting it. Mr. S.V. White,
treasurer of Plymouth Church, said that he did not doubt Mrs. Tilton had
written it. The air had been full of it of late, and after it had become
certain that Tilton and wife were to come together again the Beecher party were
prepared for anything. The confession was doubtless the price of
reconciliation. He did not know who I.B. Wheeler was, but he did know that of
late threats to blackmail Mr. Beecher had been made. If money was not given
the persons said there would be further scandal developments. Much of the
newspaper talk on the subject of the reunion of the Tiltons was preparatory to
the confession. Thomas G. Shearman said that he knew of the confession coming,
and he believed it was genuine, but it was part and parcel of the bargain by
which Tilton and wife are to live together again.  He referred to the
affidavits made by Mrs. Tilton, in which she explicitly denied her guilt, and
said that her latest confession was inconsistent with them. Others of the Beecher flock went further. They said that the woman is insane; that she is a liar and
not to be believed. They reiterated that it is a blackmailing operation, and
said that no attention would be paid to it. Reminded that Mrs. Tilton is yet a
member of Plymouth Church in good and regular standing, they said that she
would have to be expelled for lying.</p>

         <p>As the evening progressed the excitement grew
very great on Brooklyn Heights. Troops of reporters hurried to Beecher's House.</p>

         <p>They were politely received. Mr. Beecher was not at home.
They were told he was off lecturing, but his family could not tell where, other
than it was somewhere up the line of the Erie railroad. Every member of the
family asked said that they did not know where he was. When asked whether it
was a practice for him to go off without saying where he was going, they
answered that it was not. This was the first time he had done such a thing.
Judge McCue, one of the justices of the Brooklyn city court, said: "Mrs.
Tilton made an affidavit before me in my private office, in which she called
Almighty God to witness her innocence, and then she assured me privately that
the charges against her were the result of one of the basest and most malicious
conspiracies ever known. She was emphatic in every denial. Well, those who
believe in Mr. Beecher's guilt will be more than ever convinced, and those who
believe in his innocence will adhere to their belief more zealously, and the
whole unsavory scandal will be poured out upon the community again."</p>

         <p>Mr. Augustus Storrs, one of the investigating
committee, said that he had not heard of a confession, although he had been
told than there might be one. "Mrs. Moore," he said, "is a familiar person to
the public. Her actions in that period when she went hither and thither
denouncing Mr. Beecher and telling of her daughter's sin proved to her friends
that she was out of her mind. Ex-Judge Nathan B. Morse, her husband, told me
that she was not only unpleasant to be with, but unsafe. Now it would be very
strange if Elizabeth Tilton hadn't something of her mother in her. I must say
that from all I have heard I think that Mrs. Tilton is crazy. Certainly the
spells which we have seen her in go to prove it. The confession may be
authentic, but who will believe it?  A lie thrice told will have no effect."</p>

         <p>The news spread with wonderful speed, and it
seemed to plunge the stately Columbia Heights into the same fever which raged
so long in the summer of 1874, when every day brought a new surprise. Those
who moved in the inner circle of Plymouth Church were prepared for the shock.
The indications of the coming storm had appeared in many places, and faint
intimations, albeit that they were speedily repressed cropped out in the
newspaper columns. Every time the story was told that all the plans for
putting the scandal to sleep were to be upset by Mrs. Tilton, an adroit answer
was ready to destroy its strength. The wily Mr. Shearman had the fact that
Mrs. Tilton was to turn on Mr. Beecher long before any one else, and he caused
the rumors of a confession to be printed and then denied them so as to lull
suspicion. All that could be done was done to avert the disaster of a
confession. The threat of war seems first to have come from Mrs. Morse, Mrs.
Tilton's mother. A gentleman possessed of all the facts said that early in the
winter Mrs. Morse had visited Mr. Beecher and told him that Elizabeth had to be
taken care of, and that if she was not liberally supported there would be
trouble. Mr. Beecher consulted with some of his friends, and they agreed that
it would not do for him to be known as the supporter of Mrs. Tilton after all
the scandal, and they advised him not to pay her any money. Mrs. Morse renewed
her demand, and, it is said, accompanied it with strong and abusive language,
and wrote several pointed notes to Mr. Beecher, but without any effect. Mrs.
Tilton was induced to start a school in Henry street under the promise of a
liberal support from the families of Plymouth Church.</p>

         <p>She found, however, that she was not only not to be
liberally supported, but that persons from whom she expected favor expressed
the opinion that after her course she was not a fit person to instruct
children. This stung her to desperation, and she threw up her school. She
complained of her harsh treatment by Mr. Beecher and his friends, and after, as
she said, they had used her for all their purposes, and she blamed herself for
deserting her husband, who had been magnanimous to forgive her sin and to
promise her protection. She wrote a letter to Mrs. Raymond, the wife of
Professor Rossiter W. Raymond, which the reporter's informant said had been
seen and read by several persons in Plymouth Church. He understood that she
had written a similar letter, saying that she was no longer going to live in a
lie, to Mrs. Anna Field, who accompanied her daily to the trial of the
Tilton-Beecher suit.</p>

         <p>Women from Plymouth Church made frequent visits
to her, and reported a growing change in her disposition toward Mr. Beecher.
To one she said: "What viciousness all this trouble has brought out, to be
sure; nearly every form of crime." A lady member of the Plymouth Church who has maintained friendly relations with Mrs. Tilton and her mother, Mrs. Morse,
called on Mrs. Tilton, being, as she says, unable to sleep until she knew the
truth or falsity of the alleged confession. Mrs. Tilton opened the door for
her. The hair above her forehead had blanched to whiteness and she seemed to
have grown ten years older with the last few weeks. The feelings of the visitor
were so intense that she walked directly past Mrs. Tilton into the parlor
without uttering a word. When Mrs. Tilton had entered the lady asked her,
while both were yet standing: "Libby, what is all this trouble about?"</p>

         <p>"There has been trouble enough, but what do you
mean?" was the reply.</p>

         <p>"Did you write the statement that purports to be
your confession of guilt, and that has been sent to the newspapers for
publication?"</p>

         <p>"I did," replied Mrs. Tilton, firmly. "And
every word of it is true."</p>

         <p>"How could you," continued the visitor, "sit for
all this time perjuring yourself every day?"</p>

         <p>"I don't know how I could do it," replied Mrs.
Tilton, "but I did."</p>

         <p>"Did your daughters know what you now say is the
truth before they went to Europe?"</p>

         <p>"Yes, they did."</p>

         <p>Mrs. Tilton was almost broken down. She
displayed wonderful courage in maintaining the rightfulness of her new attitude
toward Mr. Beecher, but she was in a state of great nervous excitement.</p>

         <p>"Has Mr. Tilton been supporting his children?"
asked the visitor of Mrs. Morse.</p>

         <p>"Sumptuously," replied the lady.</p>

         <p>"Has he seen Mrs. Tilton lately?"</p>

         <p>"He has had two interviews with her after his
last return from lecturing, but he is now lecturing again &#8212; thousands of miles
away."</p>

         <p>Mr. Beecher was out of the city to-night when
Mrs. Tilton's letter was made public, and his whereabouts was not known save to
a few friends. The <hi rend="italic">Tribune </hi>telegraphed him a copy of the letter at a
late hour, and received the following letter in reply:</p>

	<text type="correspondence">
		<body>
		<opener>

         <dateline>Waverly, N.Y., April 15, 1878.</dateline>

         <salute>"To the Editor of the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>:</salute></opener>

         <p>"I confront Mrs. Tilton's confession with an
explicit and absolute denial. The testimony to her own innocence and mine,
which for four years she had made to hundreds in private and public, before the
court, in writing and orally, I declare to be true. And the allegations now
made in contradiction of her uniform, solemn and unvarying statements hitherto
made, I utterly deny. I declare to be innocent of the great transgression."</p>
<closer>Henry Ward Beecher.</closer>
	</body>
	</text>

         <p>In conversation with a reporter in that town, he
made the following statement: "Mrs. Tilton was examined repeatedly by my
counsel, and plied with the most searching questions, and by her consistent and
explicit testimony satisfied them all of her innocence and won their esteem.
When the Council of 1876 was called, several interviews were arranged between
her and eminent gentlemen, both of the clergy and of the law. In every case
she satisfied them of her absolute innocence. Subsequently to that, at an
interview, arranged for the purposes of giving prominence to her declarations
and form to her testimony, which was taken down by a shorthand writer, and
which I believe to be still in existence although I have never seen it, she
elaborately and in detail reaffirmed her innocence and mine. These are the
most prominent instances of her uniform testimony. It should be borne in mind
that she first charged me with this offence to her husband. Upon my visiting
her she withdrew it in writing. She subsequently renewed the charge. She then
again and indignantly denied it, and left her husband's house, and for four
years has continued, in every conceivable form and under the most solemn
circumstances, to deny it, until now, when once again, for the third time, she
renews it. Against this long and tortuous career, I oppose my uniform and
unimpeachable truthfulness."</p>

         <p>A reporter, for the purpose of verifying the
confession, called at the house of Mrs. Tilton, in Brooklyn. Mrs. Tilton
herself answered the bell. She looked far better than in the past. There
seemed, however, to be a much greater proportion of gray in her naturally black
hair than there was two years ago. The reporter saw only a vague resemblance
of her old self as she looked early in the trial, but a closer likeness to her
as she appeared when, one morning toward the close of the suit, she arose and
waited the reply of the judge to her written appeal for permission to testify.</p>

         <p>It was, however, Mrs. Tilton, beyond question,
and she responded pleasantly when so addressed. The reporter had with him a
copy of the card furnished by Mrs. Wheeler. Showing it to her and asking
whether she had indeed written it and was desirous that it should be published,
Mrs. Tilton flushed violently and cast down her eyes. Then, after a moment,
she said, "The card was written by me."</p>

         <p>"And you authorized Mr. Wheeler to make it
public?"</p>

         <p>"Yes, sir," she said, and still with downcast
eyes; "did he leave it with you? It's all right, sir."</p>

         <p>Mr. Moulton was interviewed in Albany. He spoke
substantially as follows: "I was convinced the admission would be made, but I
was hardly prepared to expect it at this time. I know it from my knowledge of the woman.  Elizabeth Tilton was so upright, so sincere minded that it
was only a question of time when she should tell the truth. I remember that
Theodore Tilton once asked me, 'Frank, do you believe Elizabeth will ever tell
me before she dies?' and I answered him that she surely would. I think that
Mr. Tilton came to expect that it would occur some day. He always believed in
her abiding sense of truth and right. You may look through the record of the
trial and you will not find an instance of his speaking of her harshly or even
unkindly. He spoke of her as a white-souled woman. He always conceded that
she was dominated and overcome by Mr. Beecher's influence in the guise of
religion."</p>

         <p>At the residence of Mrs. Morse, the mother of
Mrs. Tilton, where the latter is living, no information could be obtained. The
door was soon opened a few inches, as far as a chain and bolt would permit.
One of Theodore Tilton's sons then asked the visitor's errand. Upon being
informed that he desired to see Mrs. Morse he demanded the inquirer's
business. When told that it was a reporter who desired to see her concerning
Mrs. Tilton's letter the lad promptly said, "Mrs. Morse has no information to
impart to the press." A sharp voice from the top of the stairs called out,
"Close the door," and the command was obeyed. </p>

         <p>"I don't know," said Colonel Beecher, "whether
my father expected anything of this sort or not. We never talked to him about
it, but I will say for my part that I am not surprised. I have known for the
last six weeks that Mr. Tilton has been visiting his wife, and I was prepared
for something of this sort. An hour since I was for the first time told of it
by a friend." He declined, however, to give the name of his informant, and
said most courteously, "You can well understand that as Mr. Beecher's son I do
not care to discuss the matter at all. I cannot say what the result will be or
what my father will do. He has born calumny for years. I am quite sure he can
stand this, but it is cruel, sir, wickedly cruel."</p>

         <p>Mr. Ira B. Wheeler, to whom Mrs. Tilton's
confession was addressed, stated that the letter was handed to him in New York by Mrs. Tilton herself. It was her own voluntary act, and was written from no
one's dictation. It was entirely written by her and without suggestions from
any one. She told Mr. Wheeler a few weeks ago that she had made a confession
to a few friends. In conclusion he said: "I believe her to be actuated only
by a desire to free her conscience from the load upon it. She wished to make
the truth known in the matter. You may assert positively that Mr. Tilton knows
nothing of the matter."</p>


         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00003" type="same subject"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00021" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00040" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00046" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00066" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>