<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00051">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">The Celebrated Trial, Madeline Pollard vs. Breckinridge, The Most Noted Breach of Promise Suit in the History of Court Records</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Anonymous">Anonymous</author>
<date type="original" value="1894">1894</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00051</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
 Transcribed from pages 72-85 of the original 1894 publication of <hi rend="italic">The Celebrated Trial: Madeline Pollard vs. Breckinridge</hi>, published by the American Printing and Binding Company.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
<bibl>
               <title level="a">Seventh Day of Trial</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Celebrated Trial: Madeline Pollard vs. Breckinridge</hi></title>
               <author></author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
American Printing and Binding Company
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
?
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1894
</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="american" type="place">American</term>
               <term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
			<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
			<term id="carriage" type="setting">carriage</term>
			<term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
			<term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-30">30 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>OPENING OF COURT.</head>

       
         <p>When the Court opened Mr. Butterworth handed Mr.
Carlisle a letter.  Mr. Carlisle and Judge Wilson looked at it curiously, and
it was passed to Miss Pollard, who glanced at it and passed it to Mrs. Ellis, her companion. Mr.
Butterworth held a type-written copy in his hand. Mr.
Carlisle seemed worried, and summoned one of his clerks, to whom he gave some
instructions. The clerk left the Court room very hastily.</p>

         <p>
Miss Pollard then took the stand, and Mrs. Ellis sat next
her, ready to lend aid if the strength of the witness failed. </p>

         <p>Mr. Carlisle's preliminary questions were about
Miss Pollard's parentage. Her father was a saddler; when he died 1886 all the
Odd Fellows and Masonic lodges in Kentucky sent delegates to Frankfort to attend the funeral. She told of spending some
time with her Pittsburg aunt after her father's death.</p>

         <p>In answer
to Mr. Carlisle, Miss Pollard said: "In the last days of August, in 1892,
Mr. Breckinridge met me at the Baltimore and Ohio Railway Station."
</p>

         <p>"How
did he greet you?"</p>

         <p>"He
drew me to him, kissed me, and put me in a carriage and we were driven into the
country."</p>

         <p>"What
did he say in the carriage?"</p>

         <p>"He
told me that he had something to tell me, and he said he was vain enough to
think I would be glad to hear it. He said that the children were all grown up
now, and that there was no reason why he should not marry; he asked me if I
would marry him, and I told him I would."</p>

         <p>"Where
were you stopping during this stay in Washington?"</p>

         <p>"At
25 Lafayette
  Square."</p>

         <p>"During
your few days' stay at this time, was the subject of marriage mentioned?"</p>

         <p>"Yes,
frequently."</p>

         <p>"Where
did you go from Washington?"</p>

             <p>"I
went to New York, where Mr. Breckinridge joined me. The subject of marriage was
mentioned during those few days." </p>

         <p>"Did
he say anything about when the marriage should take place?"</p>

         <p>"Yes, he said he had waited fourteen
months after the death of his first wife before taking a second wife, and he
thought a year would be sufficient to wait for our marriage."</p>

         <p>"Did
you agree with him?"</p>

         <p>"No,
I said that more consideration was due his children; that he should wait at
least two years."</p>

         <p>"Was
there anything said further?"</p>

         <p>"Yes;
I said that Mrs. Willard, who keeps a young ladies' school in Berlin, was going
back to Europe with her two daughters, and I thought if I went with them I
could take a course of study there while the engagement lasted. It
would only cost a thousand dollars a year, and it would be better that I should
go there."</p>

         <p>"Did
you receive any note from Mrs. Willard about the trip?"</p>

         <p>"Miss
Willard, who was stopping at Gray Gables, the summer home of President
Cleveland, at Buzzard's Bay, wrote me that 
she hoped I would go with
them."
</p>

         <p>This
note was produced and read by Mr. Carlisle.</p>

         <p>Miss
Pollard was also questioned concerning her residence at 25 Lafayette Square, where she said Mr. Breckinridge called on her
frequently, and said many times that a year after his wife's death was
sufficient to wait. "I saw him always once a day, sometimes twice a day, and during the evening," she said. </p>

         <p>Miss
Pollard said she had communicated the fact of her engagement to Mrs. Thomas,
who lived at 25 Lafayette Square, and also to Claude de la Roche Francis.  She
told of the
conversation with Colonel Breckinridge, which Mr. Francis said he overheard, in
which Colonel Breckinridge said he was sorry she had told Mr. Francis of their
engagement. Miss Pollard also told the story of her presentation to Mrs. Luke
Blackburn by Colonel Breckinridge as his future wife, and of his placing her in
Mrs. Blackburn's charge as "my future wife," as testified to by Mrs.
Blackburn a few days ago.
</p>

                 <p>Miss
Pollard went on to tell of the time when she and the defendant went again to
see Mrs. Blackburn, and Miss Pollard asked Colonel Breckinridge to tell Mrs.
Blackburn when he intended to marry her. "I knelt down beside his
chair," she said, "and asked him that, and Mrs. Blackburn, I think,
objected to this display of affection."
</p>

         <p>Miss Pollard was asked
concerning her visits to Dr. N. S. Lincoln and to Major Moore, the
superintendent of police, with Colonel Breckinridge, on which occasions, according to
the testimony of Dr. Lincoln and Major Moore, Colonel Breckinridge acknowledged
his engagement to her.
</p>

         <p>"In 1884," said Miss Pollard, "I
was summoned from school in Cincinnati to go to Frankfort, where my sister was
very ill.  Mr. Rodes put me on the car. A gentleman was in the car and coming
over to me he said: 'Your face is familiar; don't I know you?' I said:
'No, but I know who you are. You are
Colonel Breckinridge.' He sat down on the other side of the aisle and asked me
if he might come to see me. I said my aunt and my mother would be very glad to
see him at Frankfort. That was all that was said."</p>

         <p>Questions
by Mr. Carlisle brought out the history of Miss Pollard's engagement to James
C. Rodes. She had met him and he asked her to marry him. She said she did not
want to marry then; she wanted to get an education first. He said if she would
marry him he would pay for her education. Miss Pollard did not answer that she
would marry him, but "I told him that if he would pay for my education I
would either marry him or pay him back with interest.   He agreed,
and a paper containing the agreement was drawn up and signed in the presence of
my mother."</p>

         <p>Miss Pollard said she did not keep the letters
written her by Rodes; she always destroyed his letters.</p>

         <p>Colonel Breckinridge and Mr. Stoll exchanged
knowing smiles at this answer.</p>

                 <p>"In one of these letters Mr. Rodes said he could compel me
to marry him or pay him back. I could not pay him back, and I did not want to
marry him. I did not know a man, woman, or a child to whom I could turn for
advice until I thought &#8212; until I thought of &#8212; Mr. Breckinridge.   I wrote him
asking if Mr. Rodes could compel me to marry him. He answered that letter in person,
coming to see me at Wesleyan College, in Cincinnati, where I was a pupil. I saw him in the drawing-room
of the college, and he said that was not the place to have a confidential
conversation. He asked couldn't we get up some sort of a relationship so that
I could get permission to go out. I told him it was not necessary to be
related, and we could get permission. He said, looking at a paper in his hand,
that there was a concert that evening, and we could go there. He obtained
permission to take me out from young 
Mr. Brown, the principal's son." 
</p>

         <p>"That evening Mr. Breckinridge came back in
a closed carriage to take me out. It was a warm, sultry June evening, and I
objected to going in a closed carriage, but he said he had a throat affection,
so we went out."</p>

         <p>"When
did you see him again?"</p>

         <p>"The
next morning at the public library, by appointment. He said he wanted to take
me to Lexington. We went to Lexington Friday."</p>

         <p>"Where did you go after reaching Lexington?"</p> 

		<p>"To Sarah Gess's."</p>

         <p>"What time was it that you arrived in Lexington?" </p>

         <p>"About dusk."</p>

         <p>"How long did you stay there?" </p>

         <p>"Until Monday morning."</p>

         <p>"Who
was with you at Sarah Gess's from Friday night until Monday morning?"</p>

         <p>"Mr. Breckinridge was there most of the
time."</p>

         <p>"What did Colonel Breckinridge say to you
on the evening of your arrival in Lexington about Mr. Rodes?"</p>

         <p>"Nothing."</p>

         <p>"What
did he say about Mr. Rodes on the following Monday morning?"</p>

         <p>"Mr. Breckinridge
came to Sarah Gess's terribly frightened. He said that Mr. Rodes had been to Cincinnati
and found out that I had gone with him, and that I must catch a train and go to
Frankfort, where my mother lived, which I did."</p>

         <p>"Who
suggested that you leave Cincinnati and go to Sayre Institute?" </p>

         <p>"Mr. Breckinridge."</p>

         
         <p>Miss Pollard told of going to see a female
physician, Dr. Mary Street, in Cincinnati, in 1885, at the direction of Mr.
Breckinridge, to make arrangements for the birth of her first child. She gave
Dr. Street the name of Mrs. Burgoyne. She took lodgings over a mattress factory,
and stayed about a month; then, after moving further up the street and remaining
there for awhile, she went to St. Joseph's Asylum at Norwood, where she registered
as "Mrs. Burgwynn." Her baby was born on May 29, 1885, and two
weeks later she went to the house of Drs. Perry and Buchanan to recuperate.
Miss Pollard identified the four volumes of Washington Irving that have figured
in the trial. They were given her by Mr. Rodes at Christmas, 1884, and she gave
them to Sister Cecilia at the foundling asylum.</p>

         <p>Miss Pollard had given her testimony without any
noticeable marks of nervousness, except in a rising tendency of her voice at
times, and an inclination to talk too fast. She looked Col. Breckinridge
squarely in the eyes while giving her testimony without appearing to do so.</p>

         <p>Taking up her life at Lexington after the birth
of her baby, Mr. Carlisle asked Miss Pollard who paid for her tuition and board
while she was at Sayre Institute.</p>

         <p>"Mr.
Breckinridge, of course," was the reply.</p>

         <p>"Miss
Pollard," was the next question, "who was the father of the child
born on the 29th of May, 1885?"</p>

         <p>"Mr.
Breckinridge," was the answer, long drawn out for the sake of emphasis.</p>

         <p>"Miss Pollard, did you
ever at any time or place, prior to meeting Col. Breckinridge, have any sexual
relations with any man?"</p>

         <p>"No;
never; never."</p>

         <p>"Miss
Pollard, have you at any time or place, after meeting Col. Breckinridge, had
sexual relations with any other man?" </p>

         <p>"No;
never; never."</p>

                  <p>"Were you ever at the house of Sarah Gess
with any other person than Colonel Breckinridge?"</p>

         <p>"Why, certainly not," said Miss
Pollard, with an inflection of surprise.</p>

         <p>Miss Pollard said she came to Washington from Lexington in September, 1887, at Mr. Breckinridge's desire. "I had to go
somewhere," she said. Mr. Breckinridge took her to the boarding-house here
that is now the Elsmere, and then, after a few days, to a boarding-house at
Thirteenth and F streets, where she was known as Mrs. Charles Foster. Mr.
Breckinridge stayed there also, but they went away when it became known that
"Mr. Sam Walter," a boarder at the house, was no other than Colonel Breckinridge. Then Miss
Pollard went to St. Ann's Foundling Asylum in Washington, where she used to go
out every night to meet Mr. Breckinridge until the Sister in charge objected,
when Colonel Breckinridge took her away, saying if he couldn't meet her she
couldn't stay here. He took her to a little house in South Washington occupied by an
old woman called "Aunt Mary," and she remained there until her second
baby was born, in February, 1888. After her
confinement she went to live at a convent on Massachusetts avenue, and remained there for two years and six months. During part of this time she was employed in the
government service, the rest in studying. She saw the defendant three or four
times each week during that period.</p>

         <p>
After leaving the convent she went to live at Mrs. Fillette's, corner of
Thirteenth and L streets; then to No. 1 B street, Northwest; then to Jefferson Place. Miss Pollard told of other frequent changes in residence while she resided in Washington.</p>

         <p>Mr. Carlisle produced the little wicker
sewing-work basket, which the late Mrs. Breckinridge had given her sister, Miss
Desha, and asked Miss Pollard if she knew it. "Yes," she said. "He
brought it to me just after his wife died, saying, 'Madeline, she cared for this, and won't you have it?' I
appreciated it very much," with a doleful little voice.</p>

         <p>"Now,
Miss Pollard,"
said Mr. Carlisle, "what was your condition in May, 1893?"</p>

         <p>"I&#8212;I wasn't well"&#8212;falteringly. </p>

         <p>"What was the matter with you?" </p>

         <p>"I&#8212;I was&#8212;was pregnant again." </p>

         <p>"By Colonel Breckinridge?"</p>

         <p>"Why,
of course," this with a sad voice. </p>

         <p>"What
was the result of that pregnancy?" </p>

         <p>"A
miscarriage."</p>

         <p>"When did it occur?" </p>

         <p>"On May 24th, I believe." </p>

         <p>"Where?"</p>

         <p>"At 1819 H Street." </p>

         <p>"Who attended you?" </p>

         <p>"Dr. Tabor Johnson."</p>

         <p>Such
a case is not complete without the conventional packages of love letters, and
they were produced next for Miss Pollard's examination. "Those are
all Mr. Breckinridge's letters," she said. She was also shown twelve
telegrams, addressed to her. "Yes, all Mr. Breckinridge's
telegrams," was her comment. </p>

         <p>In
answer to Mr. Carlisle, Miss Pollard said Colonel Breckinridge last left Washington
on Wednesday night, May 17, 1893, Then Mr. Carlisle read telegrams and letters
from Colonel Breckinridge to Miss Pollard, written while he was away on this
trip from Lexington, Covington, and other places. Nearly every day he
telegraphed her asking if she were well, telling her to make herself comfortable,
and to occupy herself. The letters were not at all of the amorous kind; they
were friendly, but not too much so. They were signed "Yours," or
"Yours truly and sincerely," and had no heading. Some of the letters were read at the
trial the other day. They referred to some sanitarium which Miss Pollard had
mentioned, and advised her not to go there; she was better where she was at
1819 H Street. This period included the time when Miss Pollard suffered a
miscarriage. Colonel Breckinridge, Miss Pollard said, was delivering political
speeches in Kentucky and Tennessee.</p>

         <p>The
next question came near bringing on a scene.</p>

         <p>"Miss
Pollard," said Mr. Carlisle, "what were the conversations you had
with Colonel Breckinridge about going to a sanitarium?"</p>

        
         <p>"Oh, Mr. Carlisle, I hardly know how to say these
things before so many men!" said Miss Pollard, plaintively, in a rather
high voice. "I can't say them." There was a suspicion of tears in
Miss Pollard's eyes.</p>

         <p>"Never mind &#8212; don't say anything &#8212; don't
answer," said Judge Wilson.</p>

         <p>Other
letters from Colonel Breckinridge on the subject of Miss Pollard's health, and telling
that he was going to Missouri, Pennsylvania, and other places. Colonel
Breckinridge made reference to sending some papers, and Miss Pollard explained
that "some papers" meant money &#8212; they did not like to refer to money
in their letters.</p>

         <p>Mr.
Carlisle read, impressively, a letter from Lexington to Miss Pollard, in which
Colonel Breckinridge said: 'I can not go to Charlottesville, nor can you go to Washington. It will result in an
open scandal. As matters now are, your character and reputation are safe. You
owe it to yourself to remain away. It is due to you to write that I will
consider your coming to Lexington as conclusive, and you must then take the responsibility
of all that might ensue. You ought to control yourself and make yourself
comfortable &#8212; restore your health, and not destroy yourself.                             Do
not make it impossible for me to do what is best.'  Yours, WILLIAM
C. P. Breckinridge.</p>

         <p>Some of these letters and telegrams were
addressed to Miss Pollard at "The Farms," near Charlottesville, Virginia. A copy of a letter to Miss Pollard from Colonel Breckinridge, referring to the
publication of the report that they were engaged, was produced and identified
by Miss Pollard; but, before it was read, the recess hour (12:30) arrived, and
a recess was ordered until 1:15 o'clock.</p>

         <p>After
recess a letter was read from Miss Pollard to Colonel Breckinridge acknowledging
that she had published the announcement of their engagement and that she was sorry
for it. This was evidently in answer to a letter from Colonel Breckinridge,
taking her to task for the publication.</p>

         <p>This letter began, "My Dear Willie," and
was signed, "Your Loving Madeline." Miss Pollard resumed the stand as
the Court was rapped to order, with Mrs. Ellis sitting by her side; she was
directly in front of and about fifteen feet from Colonel Breckinridge. During
the morning session, while Miss Pollard was giving her testimony, the defendant
sat in a listless attitude, but not taking his eyes off his accuser.  But in the afternoon he took an active interest in the proceedings, and made
suggestions to his counsel. Miss Pollard identified several letters and
telegrams, exchanged between Colonel Breckinridge and herself.   One from Miss
Pollard inclosed "a very ugly paragraph," as Miss Pollard called it,
that appeared in the Lexington Gazette, saying that Colonel Breckinridge had
said to a friend that there was no truth in the published report of his
engagement to Miss Pollard. In this letter, which began formally, "Colonel
Breckinridge" Miss Pollard called attention to the paragraph, and demanded
that he make immediate acknowledgment of the engagement, not through the
newspapers, but in a written statement of the facts, addressed to her, and
signed with his own name. She told him if he did not do this, she would take
means to obtain justice. This letter was sent registered to make sure of its
delivery.  No answer was returned, Miss Pollard said. Miss Pollard went
on identifying letters and other papers, after acknowledging that she was
responsible for the publication of the announcement of her engagement in the
papers. A letter dated April 23, 1889, was identified by Miss Pollard
as a blind letter, one of several that it had been necessary to write to conceal the relations of Colonel
Breckinridge and herself while Mrs. Breckinridge was living. She had gone with
Colonel Breckinridge to hear him lecture on religious and quasi religious
subjects, said the witness. </p>

         <p>Reverting to the conversation of the plaintiff
and defendant in the office of the Chief of Police here, in which, according to
the Chief's testimony, Colonel Breckinridge had promised to marry Miss Pollard, the
witness said that on that occasion Colonel Breckinridge named May 31 following
(1893) as the date. Later Colonel Breckinridge had changed this date on account
of the nearness of the expected birth of her baby to that time, but he said if
she would be happier he would marry her on the date named.
</p>

       
         <p>The last question asked by Mr. Carlisle was as
to how long the illicit relationship existed between Colonel Breckinridge and the plaintiff, and Miss Pollard
answered loudly and distinctly, emphasizing every syllable: "From that
night when he took me to Sarah Gess's in 1884, there never was any suggestion
of the discontinuance of that miserable sin until Colonel Breckinridge, with
all his protestations and promises and vows of affection left me on the 17th
day of May, 1893," Major Butterworth tried to stop Miss Pollard, telling
her to simply answer the question but
he was plucked by the sleeve by Colonel Breckinridge and Colonel Thompson, and
desisted. But he could not have stopped Miss Pollard; she went right on.</p>

         <p>This
concluded the direct examination, and Major Butterworth began the
cross-examination.</p>

         <p>Major Butterworth began by an examination into
Miss Pollard's age; and she told him, as she had told Mr. Carlisle, that she
had believed, until this suit was filed, that she was born in 1864; but when
the question of her age was raised, she remembered something that her mother
and her sister told her in 1876. When her father died she had supposed, in
1876, that she was twelve years old at that time; but her mother and her sister
told her that she was born November 30th, 1866; so she was ten instead of
twelve in 1876. Miss Pollard became excited over some pertinent questions about
her early life, which she said she could not answer, because she could not
remember. Her father was not a scholarly man she said to Major
Butterworth, but he was a well-read man. He taught her what he could. He took
perfect delight in teaching his little "gyrul," who was not so high
as the table. Mr. Butterworth persisted in saying that Miss Pollard was twelve
when her father died, and Miss Pollard became annoyed. She had said she was
ten then.  "I wish you wouldn't repeat that, Mr. Butterworth," she
said; "it's very annoying." Her father had told her fairy stories;
he had read her Shakspeare, history, and pretty little poems. She was fond  of
all these things.</p>

         <p>"What else did he
teach you?" asked Mr. Butterworth. "Why, Mr. Butterworth, what would
you teach your little girl?" was the answer, and there was a laugh. "How
were you employed while living at Crab Orchard, Kentucky, with your parents?" 
"What was I doing from the time I was born until I was four years old?
Why, Mr. Butterworth, I did more playing than any little girl you ever
met." "You say your father taught you history," said Mr.
Butterworth. "Did he teach you much history?" "Not so much as Colonel
Breckinridge told me afterward," was the answer; and it took the crier
nearly a minute to stop the laughter. Miss Pollard became more annoyed as
Major Butterworth asked her minutely as to her studies, what she had read, what
she knew, and how she studied.</p>

         <p>"Now I told you that twice, Mr.
Butterworth," and she ran on rapidly, telling how, whenever she heard
anything that Major Butterworth or some other statesman had said, she got
Colonel Breckinridge to get her books from the Congressional Library to look it
up."</p>

         <p>"Did
you read Browning?" was asked </p>

         <p>"Oh,
no; I was never that deep." </p>

         <p>"Did
you read Burns?"</p>

         <p>"Oh, you know I did not; only some
selections &#8212; Cotter's Saturday Night, and all that"</p>

         <p>"Byron?"</p>

         <p>"I
never read Byron to this day."</p>

         <p>Miss
Pollard's answers were bright and sometimes witty, and kept pace with the
keen-minded Major Butterworth. Miss Pollard sketched her life at Crab Orchard,
how she had left it to go to her aunt's at Pittsburg, where she remained until
August, 1880, when she returned to her mother's in Frankfort.</p>

         <p>What she did and how she did it at Frankfort, who she knew there, what pleasures she had &#8212; all these things Mr. Butterworth
wanted to know. Miss Pollard said she did what every country girl did at home
&#8212;sweep and dusted and such things. "I was only a country girl," she
added, with the peculiar Southern twist in the last word.  She knew
absolutely nobody in the neighborhood; she had not even a bowing acquaintance
with anybody nearby.</p>

         <p>It
was while at Frankfort that James C. Rodes asked her to marry him, after having seen her
three or four times, and Miss Pollard told of the bargain through which her
education was obtained. He had asked her before her aunt and several others.</p>

         <p>"Mr.
Rodes," she said, "was not a conventional man." This caused a
laugh.</p>

         <p>"Was
this your first offer of marriage?"</p>

         <p>"No,
I had one the year before from a Mr. Woods, but I had no more to do with that
than you had, Mr. Butterworth." Colonel Breckinridge joined in the laughter
over this sally.</p>

         <p>"Where
is the paper you wrote Mr. Rodes telling him you would marry him if he would
pay for your education?"</p>

         <p>"I
don't know; perhaps Mr. Breckinridge has it."</p>

         <p>"If
Mr. Breckinridge has the paper, he should produce it," said Judge Wilson.</p>

         <p>"He's not Rodes' executor," said Colonel
Thompson. The demand of Judge Wilson was not pressed.</p>

         
         <p>Miss Pollard admitted she was engaged to Mr. Rozell
while she was at the Wesleyan College, in Cincinnati, during the continuance of
her contract with Mr. Rodes. Mr. Butterworth spoke of her contract with Rodes
as "the engagement," and Miss Pollard objected to its being put that
way. Mr. Rodes had loaned her the money to get her education on the condition
that she should pay him back or marry him.</p>

         <p>"Did
you tell of this engagement to Rodes?" </p>

         <p>"No,
sir."</p>

         <p>"Did you break off with Rozell?"</p>

         <p>"Yes, while Mr. Breckinridge was concealed
in a sitting room adjoining and heard me break my engagement with Rozell. I was
pregnant at the time by Mr. Breckinridge."</p>

         <p>There
was one sally that created a roar. Mr. Butterworth asked Miss Pollard
if Colonel Breckinridge had recognized her on the train at their first meeting,
and Miss Pollard said: "He crossed the aisle and asked me if he did not
recognize me and, by the way, that is a common trick of his, recognizing people
he doesn't know." Miss Pollard in answer to other questions said, she
had seen many things in Mr. Breckinridge during their nine years' association
that she did not like, including this trick of recognition, but she had not
found him out then. Mr. Butterworth tried to make the witness say that on the
first night Colonel Breckinridge came to see her he had brought a carriage at
her suggestion, but Miss Pollard met him with: "Now, Mr. Butterworth, you
know I never said anything of the kind."  Some more questions were
met with earnest answers that made the spectators laugh, and then at 3:15
o'clock the Court adjourned until Monday.</p>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>