<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00056">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Quadroona</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapter XXIII</title>
<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">London Journal</hi></title>
<date type="original" value="1856">1856</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            

<author name="St. John">Percy St. John</author>
        <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00056</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
This excerpt from Percy St. John's <hi rend="italic">Quadroona</hi> is transcribed from pages 129-130 of the November 1, 1856 issue of <hi rend="italic">The London Journal</hi>.
</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter XXIII</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Quadroona</hi></title>
               <author>Percy St. John</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
<hi rend="italic">London Journal</hi>

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
London

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
November 1, 1856

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="boudoir" type="setting">boudoir</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
			<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
			<term id="british" type="place">British</term>
<term id="fiction" type="media">fiction</term>

            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
  <date value="2005-08-19">19 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-10">10 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Second Round Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-25">25 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         
         <head>CHAPTER XXIII </head>

         <p>The interior cabin, which appeared
peculiarly appropriated to the use of Quadroona and her attendant, was fitted
up in a style of gorgeous splendour, which was not without its effect upon the
ardent imagination of William Linley even as he entered.</p>

         <p>Hangings of tapestry and rich Indian
silks, mirrors, a sofa in the most luxurious Louis XIV style, arm chairs, a
harp, a lute, books, nothing was wanting, while two elegant hammocks of Mexican
grass hung above all, the favourite sleeping places of Creoles and white ladies
in the hot countries of that sunny South, which, if it be the parent of much vice
and fierce, untameable passions, is also the muster of wondrous beauty in what
is living and what is inanimate.</p>

         <p>A large swinging lamp was suspended
from the upper deck, filled with a fragrant oil that diffused its odour through
every nook and cranny of the apartment. A table of elegant workmanship, covered
with a profusion of silks and satins, stood in the middle of the room, most incongruously
supported on each side by cannon; for even this delightful retreat was not
without its especial use during the hours of peril and danger. </p>

         <p>Quadroona sat in a kind of chair of
state, in a dreamy state of thought, which, at the moment, was evidently not
pleasant. Her pouting, rich lips were compressed, her brow was slightly
contracted, and she was tossing her tiny feet up and down in a way which; to
one so impulsive, denoted that she was impatient, and almost angry.</p>

         <p>Standing
beside her, in a long tunic, with bracelets on her arms and heavy earrings in
her ears, was a mulatto woman of about thirty two or three, who had certainly
none of the repulsive character which too often the unfortunate characteristic
of the pure negress, but whose mixed blood had produced a kind masculine beauty,
with an energy of character, rarely found, except under excitement, in the
genuine African, after he has been reduced beneath
the degrading yoke of slavery. </p>

         <p>William
Linley hesitated.</p>

         <p>"I
am intruding," he said, with profound respect. </p>

         <p>"I
have been expecting you." replied Quadroona, with a coldness of manner
quite unsuited to her character. "Cora, give the gentleman a seat." </p>

         <p>The
mulatto girl dropped the rich satin she had been admiring, and handed Linley a
low settee, which he accepted with a bow. </p>

         <p>"Your
arrival amongst us," said Quadroona, abruptly, "has been sudden. Do
you come in the character of Wilder?" </p>

         <p>Linley
understood her allusion. He coloured violently and rose to his feet. </p>

         <p>"I
came, madame, on board by compulsion, and the first wish of my soul is to leave
as soon as we reach any port whence England may be gained," he said, impetuously. </p>

         <p>"And
why England &#8212; always England?" asked Quadroona, with a sudden change of
manner. </p>

         <p>"Because
there are my friends, my fortune, my home!" said Linley, proudly. </p>

         <p>He
was about to have added, "<hi rend="italic">my love</hi>," but some strange instinct
checked him. Fatal error! </p>

         <p>"I know your story," she cried; "but sit down, I pray you. You are my
tutor," she added, with a smile; "we must make acquaintance."</p>

         <p>William
Linley looked at the supremely lovely apparition before him, and, as he sat
down, there was a fluttering at the heart, which he stopped not to analyze. What
young man of twenty would have not had his imagination fired by the prospect of
continual intercourse with one so beautiful? </p>

         <p>Quadroona
had all the indescribable fascinations of form and manner, the halo of
passionate impulse, which is the birthright of the children of the South,
combined with the polish which is acquired in the better circles of European
society. As he gazed at her, William Linley felt her to be a mystery.</p>

         <p>"What
do you mean to teach me?" she said, in the tones of a queen interrogating a subject. </p>

         <p>"Before
I answer, I must first ask you what you know," said William, with a smile.</p>

         <p>"I
can read!" said Quadroona, a little proudly.</p>

         <p>"Any
child would suppose that," answered Linley, with a measuring glance at the
books which lay around.</p>

         <p>There
was a strange wild flash in the eye of Quadroona, which Linley at the time was
at a loss to understand.</p>

         <p>"I
can write," she added, turning the leaves of a large kind of album which she
had suddenly caught up from the sofa near at hand.</p>

         <p>Linley
rose and looked over the book.</p>

         <p>"The
writing is as neat as the hand is pretty," he said, with a smile.</p>

         <p>Quadroona
raised her eyes, and fixed them upon him with an inquiring glance. It was
clearly meant to ask him if his speech concealed a sneer. The sensitive nature
of that strange and wayward being had evidently been aroused. The look with
which Linley met her glance was so calm and smiling, that all suspicion
vanished.</p>

         <p>"You
flatter!" she exclaimed, with a smile.</p>

         <p>"Nay!"
cried Linley, warmly, "'tis the writing of a perfect little lady. Did you
learn in England?"</p>

         <p>"In
  France," she replied, pettishly; "but the hand," she added, with a peculiar,
a very peculiar glance, "is it so white?"</p>

         <p>"No
princess ever held out a fairer one to be kissed," said Linley, gallantly.</p>

         <p>"Ay,
some dusky Moor or burnt Spanish &#8212; "</p>

         <p>"Nay,"
interrupted Linley, quickly; "the fairest daughter of France or England would be proud to own so fair a one."</p>

         <p>"But
is it <hi rend="italic">white</hi>?" asked Quadroona, laughing, but with an evident anxiety
which did not escape Linley, however much it puzzled him.</p>

         <p>"Would
you, fair lady, have me call it black?" continued he, much amused with his
wayward pupil.</p>

         <p>"<hi rend="italic">Black!</hi>"
said Quadroona, fiercely, her face turning deadly pale, her nostrils dilating,
her whole frame swelling with passion, "why should you call it black?"</p>

         <p>William
Linley looked at her with a pitying glance, such as one might naturally bestow
on one escaped from a lunatic asylum.</p>

         <p>"Him
black no such bad <hi rend="italic">cullar</hi>," said the mulatto, tartly.</p>

         <p>"Be not angry, Cora," replied Quadroona, as if remembering
herself. "I do not say that black is a bad colour, but <hi rend="italic">I </hi>have no wish
to try it."</p>

         <p>"Him
grandmudder black as one crow," said Cora, drily.</p>

         <p>Linley
was shocked to see the effect of this statement on Quadroona. Every trace of
gentle and feminine beauty departed for one moment; her eyes looked Medusa
like, her lips parted, and, by exposing her teeth, gave her a fierce expression
of hate; her skin, at first livid, showed, here and there, to the practised
eye, the smallest tinge of black blood in the veins of woman.</p>

         <p>"Cora,
it is a lie of my enemies; my father was white, my mother was white!" she
began, in choking accents.</p>

         <p>"Fader
white, certainly; so mine," continued the implacable mulatto girl: "but you
mother half caste." </p>

         <p>"Mr.
Linley!" cried Quadroona, in fierce accents, "call Captain Wharton!"</p>

         <p>"Why?"
said Linley, calmly.</p>

         <p>"I
will have this girl flogged!" almost shrieked the beautiful Quadroona.</p>

         <p>"Flogged!"
said Linley, with horror in his countenance.</p>

         <p>"No
dare!" cried Cora, coldly; "<hi rend="italic">me free now!</hi>"</p>

         <p>"Quadroona,"
interposed Linley, more calmly, "allow me to speak one moment. I know not the
reason of your anger, but this I do know, if I am to take upon myself the
responsible position of your tutor, I must begin by expostualting with you
against passion. You will never do credit to your evident high position, if
you allow yourself to give way to such terrible impulses. Beauty and charms
such as yours should surely be only the outward garb of all that is lovely
within."</p>

         <p>All
have seen the grey, cold, bleak horizon, when first tinged by the very faintest
blush of dawn. The transformation is gentle and slow, indeed, but we soon feel
the influence of the change. The dark and gloomy then, by slow degrees, is
warmed into the full efflugence of day, until all is bright, sunny, glorious.</p>

         <p>So
with Quadroona. Her pale and livid face became for a moment paler and more
livid, and then changed to freezing chillness. The voice of the young man,
however, was so gentle and persuasive that she was calmed &#8212; despite herself,
the rosy colour came to her cheeks. She was herself again.</p>

         <p>"Forgive
me, Cora," she said, half reluctantly, "but I cannot hear of that unhappy
tradition of my race without anger. It is a silly weakness, I know, but it is
beyond my power to control it. I do not hate, however, all that is black."</p>

         <p>"Me
no black!" cried Cora, who was quite as sensitive on the point as her mistress.</p>

         <p>"I
know &#8212; you are a mulatto."</p>

         <p>"My
fader all white," said Cora &#8212; "my mother real African princess in her own
country."</p>

         <p>"It
matters little what people are in their own countries," continued Quadroona,
musing &#8212; "but no more than this. Mr. Linley will pursue his catechism. I can
play," she added, in a sprightly tone.</p>

         <p>"Will
you favor me?" asked Linley, who strove as much as possible to assume the tone
of a master with his pupil.</p>

         <p>The
experiment has been a dangerous one in all ages. The history of Heloise and
Abelard is a common one. Youth and beauty on both sides &#8212; with master and
pupil &#8212; and study will proceed but slowly. It is an old tale and often told.</p>

         <p>"I
can only accompany myself," she said, with a faint blush of timidity.</p>

         <p>"Strange
being!" though Linley; "so full of life and energy, so rife with southern
passions, and yet so gentle and so timid."</p>

         <p>He
rose meanwhile and adjusted the harp. As he did so, a deadly sickness came
over him &#8212; a string gave way! Was it an omen? On the last occasion, when he
had performed the same office for Lady Frances Herbert, a string had broken.
It was truly touching a painful chord.</p>

         <p>"You
are ill?" said Quadroona, in a low, soft, seductive tone, that made the young
man's life blood rush to his heart.</p>

         <p>"No,"
he replied, hurriedly; "'twas but a spasm." </p>

         <p>He
sat down by her side and waited. Quadroona assumed her post near the harp, and
never had Linley seen form so lovely, face so perfect, as when, with a dreamy
and voluptous air of sincerity, she began chanting a kind of love ditty of the
South.</p>

         <p>Her
voice had all the softness requisite for her subject; it had also a compass and
power which delighted and surprised her hearer. When she had finished, William
Linley remained silent. His heart was too full to speak, the big tears stood
unbidden in his eyes.</p>

         <p>Quadroona
saw the effect she had produced, and, after enjoying her triumph for a moment,
burst into a loud laugh.</p>

         <p>"Pardon
me!" cried Linley, starting; "but why do you laugh?"</p>

         <p>"To
see how silent you are. You would rather say nothing about my screeching, and
therefore are dumb," she said, archly.</p>

         <p>"Madame!"
exclaimed Linley, who had not quite got rid of the spell, "I have heard many
voices, but nothing so exquisitely has ever reached my ears. I fancy myself
listening to some enchantress."</p>

         <p>"Mr.
Tutor," said Quadroona, with mock gravity &#8212; in reality, deeply gratified &#8212; "if <hi rend="italic">you
</hi>teach me to be vain, who will school me?"</p>

         <p>Linley
blushed. He had truly forgotten his relation to the fair enchantress &#8212; and
very many other things besides.</p>

         <p>"I
can dance!" cried Quadroona, rising and clapping her hands, while Cora, at a
sign from her, cleared a small open place.</p>

         <p>Linley
stepped back, still more astonished, still more spellbound, still more
fascinated than before.</p>

         <p>Quadroona
had thrown herself into the attitude of a first class opera dancer &#8212; an
attitude peculiarly calculated to show off her well rounded limbs, her full and
perfect bust. As she stood smiling at him, the master thought the pupil the
most dangerously seductive creature he had ever seen in his life. At least, he
did not think so &#8212; he felt it, while thinking her the most beautiful vision his
dreams had ever conjured up.</p>

         <p>She
began dancing &#8212; no drawing room or salon dance of formal conventionality, but a
dance in the true sense of the word. She began with slow, languishing, and
measured movements, that seemed a narrative in themselves. Her eyes darted
liquid fire, her bosom panted, her mien was all luxurious enjoyment. Then
anger seemed to rise: she started back, stood upright with a menacing mien,
and then began, with inimitiable art, to simulate an angry beauty gradually
yielding to the pressing solicitations of her lover for pardon. At last every
flash of anger vanished, and gave way to a soft, ductile, yielding look, as of
beauty vanquished, until, after whirling wildly round, she fell exhausted in
her arm chair.</p>

         <p>Linley
stood upright against the wall. He had never seen such an exhibition before.
The southern and impassioned girl was a novelty to him. A wild thought darted
through his brain &#8212; his kindled imagination compared her with the cold
daughters of the North &#8212; and again, but with redoubled vigour, came the
fluttering sensation to his heart which he had already felt so keenly. He
closed his eyes to escape the vision of so much beauty, but she appeared only
more lovely to his mind's eye.</p>

         <p>"Now,
Mr. Linley," she said, suddenly, in a natural and calm tone of voice, which
awoke him rudely from his dream, "you know my accomplishments."</p>

         <p>"That
dance came not from France?"</p>

         <p>"From
  France&#8212; no!" she cried, with considerable animation. "The dances I learned
in their schools I hate. They are so formal &#8212; so solemn. What I like is
liberty &#8212; liberty of speech, of act, of limb. I submit to the dry walking you
call dancing, but I love to cast off restraint, and find joy in the free use of
my hands and feet."</p>

         <p>"The
dance is peculiar," continued Linley; "to what clime does it belong?"</p>

         <p>"To
my native country," said Quadroona, drily.</p>

         <p>Linley
bowed, but could not avoid making mental note of the reservation with which she
spoke of her native land. It was one peculiarity among the many that
surrounded him. His ideas were in a whirl. He had, during a few hours, passed
through so much action and incident, that he had no time for thought.</p>

         <p>Who
was this beautiful and fascinating creature? Whence came she? Whither was she
going?</p>

         <p>The
questions flashed across his mind with lightning rapidity, but Quadroona, who
noticed his abstracted air, gave him no time for much reflection.</p>

         <p>"And
now, my master!" she cried, "that you know what I can do, please inform me of
the order of my studies."</p>

         <p>"Madame,"
replied Linley, quickly, "I, <hi rend="italic">too, </hi>have my duties to learn. They are
many, I believe, and arduous. My experience of the sea is confined to yachts,
so that I am no practised sailor. I must give my mornings to instruction
myself. But you have books, you can read; you have a harp, you can play; you
have a voice, you can sing." Here he hesitated.</p>

         <p>"You
would not advise me to dance?" she said, archly.</p>

         <p>"Madame,"
replied Linley, laughing to hide his confusion, "I fancy the wind will not
always be as favourable as it is now."</p>

         <p>"You
object?" said Quadroona, gravely, with a searching glance; "you fancy that
dance bold and unbecoming?"</p>

         <p>"No!"
exclaimed Linley, warmly, "not so. It is but unusual. I never saw anything so
graceful or fascinating on or off &#8212; "</p>

         <p>He
hesitated.</p>

         <p>"The
stage," put in Quadroona, gravely. "There," she added, passionately, "there
speaks the selfishness of your northern men. Women with you are painted dolls
or slaves &#8212; slaves to conventionality or custom. You love to see the graceful
dance, the rounded limb, the elegant form &#8212; but it must be the graceful dance,
the rounded limb, the elegant form, of hirelings and foreigners. You encase
your wives, sisters, and daughters, in coats of mail, and long, hideous skirts
that prevent all motion. Who would ride a spirited horse with a panoply around
fit only for a pope or cardinal? Give me the warm and sunny South, where the
spirits are high, and where cold and formal customs chain not woman."</p>

         <p>"Women
in most southern countries are slaves indeed!" said William Linley, gravely.</p>

         <p>Quadroona
started, bit her lip, and turned pale.</p>

         <p>"True,"
she said, after a moment's pause; "'tis only in the North their persons and
wills are free. But you punish them for the liberty you give, by chaining them
to social laws and rules, which make them as much slaves as in any country
where the hideous traffic is real."</p>

         <p>"You
have never been in England," replied Linley, warmly, "where at least the
influence of woman is legitimate and great."</p>

         <p>"England! Always England!" said Quadroona, warmly. "Tell me of that fabulous land which I
have never seen &#8212; shall never see," she added, with a sigh.</p>

         <p>Linley
spoke, and Quadroona scarcely ever interrupting him, he sketched, as far as was
in his power, the position of woman in our favoured isle. To him, probably, the
picture was brighter than the reality, but he was correct in estimating his
country women and their North American sisters as fortunate above all. We are
far from perfect, but the social position of the fair sex, their standing in
society, their influence is far more legitimate and real in this favoured isle,
than it is elsewhere in the whole wide world.</p>

         <p>A
superficial glance at continental countries may create another impression, but
those who have gone beyond a shallow study know the contrary.</p>

         <p>Quadroona
listened with wrapt attention. The picture evidently pleased her.</p>

         <p>"Englishwomen
should be happy!" she said, at last, with a deep sigh. "But are there no
unhappy marriages, no forced unions, no hateful conjunctions of unkindred
souls?"</p>

         <p>"Many;
but I believe fewer than people fancy."</p>

         <p>Quadroona
made no reply, and Linley, who thought the topic rather a dangerous one,
changed the subject to the less exciting subject of her studies. He had
scarcely done so when Wharton returned, and bowing gracefully to both Linley
and Quadroona, asked Cora to give them tea, a beverage which both appeared to
be fond of. Cora rang a bell, and a lad about fourteen, also a black,
appeared, bringing the necessary apparatus.</p>

         <p>"And
now, Mr. Linley," said Captain Wharton, rising; "your watch begins at twelve.
I think you will need rest. You have made your arrangements for the
prosecution of this young lady's studies? You can continue tomorrow."</p>

         <p>Linley
took the hint and retired, Captain Wharton following him in a very few minutes.
</p>





<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00120" type="image on fiction"/>
               </item>

            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>