<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00060">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Snake in the Grass</hi></title>
	<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapter XXXIX, "A Painful Discovery"</title>

		<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">The London Journal</hi></title>
<date type="original" value="1858">September 18, 1858</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
           <author name="Egan">Pierce Egan</author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00060</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
This excerpt from Pierce Egan's <hi rend="italic">The Snake in the Grass</hi> is transcribed from pages 49-51 of the September 18, 1858 issue of <hi rend="italic">The London Journal</hi>. </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter XXXIX, A Painful Discovery</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Snake in the Grass</hi></title>
               <author>Pierce Egan</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
<hi rend="italic">London Journal</hi>
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
London

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1858

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="wild" type="setting">wild</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
			<term id="british" type="place">British</term>
<term id="fiction" type="media">fiction</term>

            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
  <date value="2005-08-19">19 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-15">15 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
                  <head>A Painful Discovery</head>
         <p>A mounted messenger brought to Falkland Count
a communication from Eunice Devereux to Hester Blayre, informing her that
herself and brother had accepted an invitation from Lady Alton to pass a few
days at Alton Hall.</p>
         <p>Hester, after the agitation she had suddenly
exhibited in Falkland Park while conversing with Gertrude, had, on reaching the
old mansion, retired to her room, leaving to
Gertrude the task of entertaining Valentine Temple.
</p>
         <p>The nature of the conversation which had
taken place between Hester and Gertrude while walking together in the park had
rendered the duty, thus unexpectedly devolving on the latter, one of
considerable embarrassment. If she could have forgotten what had been said, Valentine Temple was not disposed to let it slumber on her mind.</p>
         <p>No sooner did her presence gratify his eyes
than he commenced a more than usually ardent course of attentions; for she was
now with him alone. Eunice and the ever-intrusive Murray were away, and Hester
Blayre, with her provokingly imperturbable manner and searching eyes, was
absent. He felt that it was an opportunity not to be lost; he, therefore,
although, still weak and ill, seized it in the hope that he should
be able to surmount that distant reserve she displayed towards him, and create
in her bosom an interest for him which should ripen under this cultivation into
a passionate love.</p>
         <p>He was quite aware that common means would
have no effect with one of no common mould; he had observed that she possessed
a kindly nature, and had displayed to himself and Murray equally tender
sympathy for their sufferings. He was skilful enough not to proceed by
language to woo her; but his looks and gestures superseded the necessity for
words, while they gave him the advantage of being able to make himself
understood without the risk which, if outspoken, he would have run of being
requested not to repeat again expression to which there could be no such
response as he wished.</p>
         <p>When alone with her, he artfully drew her
attention to himself, simulated acute anguish, and lamented his inability to
wander abroad in the clear fresh sunny air for want of a protecting guide and
companion. Gertrude glanced at his pale face, his wasting form, observed his
writhing contortions, and fell into the trap he laid for her.</p>
         <p>What if she were to offer to accompany him?
To tender her arm for him to lean on, to conduct him to some of those
fairy-like spots with which she had already made herself acquainted? What
could come of it?</p>
         <p>So when he looked out upon the fair landscape
spread out like a map before him, and turned his eyes upward at the broad,
bright blue sky, and sighed audibly as if heavy of hear, Gertrude asked him if
he thought he had strength enough to attempt a short walk in the park.</p>
         <p>He caught at the suggestion with such delight
that she felt glad that she had made the proposition; but when she further
suggested that she would summon his valet to attend him, an expression of such
disappointment appeared on his face, and he declined the aid of his man in such
strong terms, that when with earnest language he requested her to be his
companion, if only for a few short paces, she could not find it in her heart to
meet his solicitations with a refusal.</p>
         <p>Together, therefore, they wandered under
shadows of the broad elms and graceful beeches in the beautiful old park, with
its undulating carpet-like surface and slopes.</p>
         <p>This acquiescence of Gertrude's resulted in
morning walks, in afternoon strolls, and, as
the days grew longer, to evening rambles.
Valentine rapidly increased in strength, his languor disappeared, his manner
altogether
underwent a remarkable change. He appeared to watch every look, every motion of
Gertrude's. He studied her tastes, avoided any subject likely to prove
displeasing
to
her, and preserved an air of deference and
respect, which, while it distinctly proclaimed his passion for her, never
overstepped the narrowest limit, so as to draw from her a single observation
in
reference
to it.
</p>
         <p>She was not insensible to the position into which she gradually gliding nor to its
dangers; but it had assumed that form which left her no alternative but to
proceed, in order to
avoid an explanation
she had no wish to precipitate.</p>
         <p>One
thing she foresaw, and that was the speedy restoration of Valentine to
convalescence. This moment arriving she would be enabled with grace, and
without an invidious remark, to cease these perambulations. Then she world be absolved from the trial of having to endure, without a deprecatory word, soft loving glances, and a manner so ardent as to leave, as an expression of his sentiments towards her, nothing to her imagination. At least,
such were her anticipations, or rather her resolves. She avoided,
as far as possible, giving to the glances or the acts of Valentine the smallest
encouragement; yet, to be complaisant and courteous, to display neither
disquiet nor offence at the course he adopted, was in itself a tacit
encouragement. He considered it such: and when the favorable moment, as he foreshadowed
it, should arrive for him to declare himself, he determined to put very
strongly to her how much his hopes
had been advanced by the countenance she had extended to him; in fact, he
had long since determined that she should be his; and if this object could not
be accomplished by fair means, he resolved
that no light considerations should deter him from attempting to make her his
by far more questionable efforts.</p>
         <p>In
the meanwhile, Hester Blayre had resumed her usual appearance. Not a word had
she let fall to Gertrude in explanation of the sudden excitement she had
betrayed on beholding the person whose retreating figure Gertrude
just caught a glimpse of; but Gertrude could trace an anxious look about her
features, and an unsettled action in her eyes, which she had never before
observed. </p>
         <p>Hester
appeared to notice only with favourable eyes the form which the intimacy
between Gertrude and Valentine was assuming, and she suffered it to take its
course without remark; but at the same time it was clear that she was more
actively employed than had been the case since Gertrude had been with her. She
was much occupied with receiving and answering letters, and passed a rather
large proportion of time in her own room.</p>
         <p>Gertrude
could not but notice it; but she was unable to even guess the occasion for it. She had, however, a strong impression that the person Hester had encountered in
the park was no other than the stranger she had met in the crypt beneath the
dark firs. If this should prove to be the fact, it was evident that Hester
knew his history, and that his sudden appearance was anything but a source of
satisfaction to her. It occurred to Gertrude that this mysterious individual
might be able to throw some light upon her past history. He had already said
enough and acted in a manner to lead to such a conclusion; and she felt that if
chance again threw her in his path, she would not avoid him, but, on the
contrary, put to him questions which were the first and the nearest to her
heart.</p>
         <p>Hester
Blayre had been startled by the announcement of the presence of Lady Alton at
Alton Hall. She found it difficult to understand it.</p>
         <p>However,
it suited her schemes well for Lady Alton to be there; and she proceeded
promptly to take such steps as would enable her to secure the advantages it
might offer to her.</p>
         <p>Among
her letters from London there came one from Reuben Drake. She recognized the
handwriting; and she opened it, expecting to find within the papers she had
charged him with stealing; but there was no enclosure. Making herself certain
that the letter contained nothing beyond three closely-written sides of paper,
she held it over a taper and consumed it.</p>
         <p>"I
will not trust myself to read a word from him," she muttered &#8212; "no, not a word,
even as I dare not trust myself to see his form or hear his voice. The summit
of my wishes is too nearly within my reach for me to give way to weaknesses of
the same nature as those of which I have been guilty. Let him go: he is but
one more added to the many sacrifices this heart has made for the realization
of a project which, after all, may prove to be mere profitless delusion. No,
not that: it must not prove a chimera; no, not even if in the consummation of
my revenge I pull down destruction on myself!"</p>
         <p>She
watched the paper consume until it was all destroyed, and then she flung the
ashes into the grate. She flattered herself upon the resolution she displayed
in this. She would have recoiled from such precipitancy had she divined even
the character of the contents. It is true that she possessed some lurking
fear, some latent uneasiness, that Reuben might prove himself a troublesome
enemy; but she had so much faith in her own moral superiority, and the power
which that gave her over him, that she would not suffer any dread of him to
obtain in her mind.</p>
         <p>Immediately
after she became acquainted with the arrival of Lady Alton at Alton Hall, she,
in harmony with the details of her secret scheme, summoned Sir Giffard Falkland
to his country seat. She was all unconscious of what had passed between them
in the earlier period of their lives, and had not the slightest knowledge of
their accidental, but, as it proved, clandestine meeting in Kensington
Gardens. She, unknowing that what had passed would materially assist the fatal
purpose of her project, conceived a plan for accomplishing a series of private
interviews between them, determining when the fitting moment arrived to
introduce upon the scene Lord Alton.</p>
         <p>Hester
entertained no suspicion either of the purity of Lady Alton, nor of the honour
of Sir Giffard Falkland, but she knew that &#8212; </p>
         <lg type="poem"><l>Trifles
light as air,</l>
         <l>Are
to the jealous, confirmation strong</l>
         <l>As
proofs of holy writ.</l>
	</lg>
         <p>To
a man of the temperament of Lord Alton, of quick and sensitive pride, the mere
fact of seeing Lady Alton alone in some sequestered place, with Sir Giffard
Falkland, would be tantamount to a crime of the blackest dye. Hester did not
pause to think that in inflicting the deepest possible wounds upon the heart of
Lord Alton she might involve in the destruction of both Lady Alton and Sir
Giffard. Revenge is ever a selfish passion; and those who strive to gratify it
seldom contemplate, in striking at the object of their hatred, what other
beings may suffer from the blow.</p>
         <p>Hester
Blayre was glad to think that Murray Devereux would remain a guest at Alton
Hall. She had easily detected she was sufficiently mistress of his nature to
feel assured that he had only to be alone for a week or so, subjected to the
loving influence of a fond girl, conscious she had a rival in his affections,
to make him commit himself to her attachment, declare his love for her, and
place himself in her power beyond retraction, unless rejected by him who, as
head of the household, claimed the title to dispose of his daughter's hand.</p>
         <p>And
she cared nothing about such a result, beyond the hope of exulting in that
rejection, because she was interested only to the extent of creating dissension
between father and daughter. To her it was a matter of indifference whether
Murray and Laura married, or broke their hearts under an enforced separation;
equally her object seemed secure. She knew Lord Alton to be inflexible, when
he had formed plans for future family connections, and she thought she might
safely judge by the step Laura had taken, in quitting Winchmore Park, that she would meekly, nor without murmuring, obey the behest of her father, never to see
or think of Murray Devereux more.</p>
         <p>The
more, therefore, the fond couple were together, with opportunities for wooing
in abundance surrounding them, the better for her project.</p>
         <p>There
was many points to be, however, carefully deliberated. She had not forgotten
the part she felt it would be essential that Valentine Temple should play in
this portion of the drama she was constructing, and she had not overlooked the
fact that Valentine Temple was unconscious of the design Lord Alton had
conceived of effecting an union between him and his daughter. She thought it
was very important that he should know it, and that the information should be
conveyed to him by her lips only.</p>
         <p>Who
can convey an insinuation with such an air of frankness as an artful woman? If
a selfish man is to be possessed with an idea which may occasion his interests
to clash with his honour, and he knows that in carrying it out he will not be
any remove from a scoundrel, a designing woman can place it before him from a
point of view where he can see it through the medium best suited to his own
inclination, and at the same time the small voice of conscience is drowned by
the shouts of "common sense." No one can do it so well. A woman's advice
about woman naturally carries a very powerful influence to a man's mind; and if
it should happen to square with the promptings of selfish passions, probity has
but a poor chance.</p>
         <p>Hester was too well acquainted with human weakness not to be aware of this; she sought
for, and without difficulty obtained an interview with Valentine Temple, with no other person present but himself.</p>
         <p>Inwardly sure of Gertrude's strength of character, and her perfect immunity from any
danger of being triumphed over by the most cunning and seductive arts Valentine
could employ, she had, in what appeared to be a cursory conversation to him,
dwelt upon her character, enlarged upon what she said might be considered its
principal attributes, decision and firmness; spoke tenderly and with seeming
fondness of her; and when the attention of Valentine was intensely riveted to
her observations, she expatiated upon the soft and loving, even passionate under-current
which flowed steadily beneath that calm pool-like surface her manner exhibited
to the circle with which she came in contact.</p>
         <p>"She
is but a woman, Mr. Temple," she said, with well-acted open ingenuousness, "a
weak, loving, trusting woman; and I am quite convinced that if a man found his
way to her heart, he would discover that the crystal he had so much admired was
as pliable and as easily modeled to his views as others he had deemed of far
less rocky consistency."</p>
         <p>Valentine
drew a deep breath.</p>
         <p>"But
Miss De Brent, madam," he said hastily, "I have always considered to possess a
purity as invulnerable as adamant."</p>
         <p>"Sir!"
returned Hester, with well-affected warmth and surprise. "You misconceive the
sentiments I have expressed. I spoke of the man who won the love of Miss De
Brent."</p>
         <p>"Ten
thousand pardons, my dear Miss Hester, for a most unintentional, yet very
improper observation," interrupted Valentine, with quickness. "Of course I am
well aware that her nature is as immaculate and unsullied as snow; but I
understood you &#8212; "</p>
         <p>"No
more; let us change the subject," interposed Hester, abruptly, but with a
smile, as if to show that she was not offended. "I have a charge to make
against you."</p>
         <p>Valentine
turned a violent scarlet. He bowed his head to conceal his confusion.</p>
         <p>"Against
me?" he exclaimed, in a low tone.</p>
         <p>"Yes,"
she replied, perceiving but not noticing his confusion. Oh, she knew the
nature of the soil she was planting, that she might reap the fruitful crop to
which she looked forward!</p>
         <p>"Pray
prefer it," he said. "I have no doubt I can meet it with a satisfactory
answer."</p>
         <p>"It
is quickly made," she returned. "You studiously avoid mentioning the name of
Laura Alton; and truly if I did not happen to be conscious of your engagement
with her, I should be more than half disposed to believe you sought to form one
with my near relative, Gertrude De Brent."</p>
         <p>Valentine
gazed upon her with an air of astonishment. Laura Alton he had met several
times, but no circumstances had arisen which had induced him to take more than
common notice of her. He placed her in the same category with hundreds whom he
had met. She had won from him a passing glance; he had exchanged with her the
accustomed salutations exacted by good breeding, nothing more. When, therefore,
Hester Blayre referred to an engagement with her, she so nonplussed him, that
he at once, in plain terms, asked for an explanation.</p>
         <p>Hester
gave it him &#8212; but in her own way. She dwelt so pertinently upon the advantages
to him of forming an alliance with her, that he began to regard it in the way
she desired it, and to set in motion schemes having connection with it.</p>
         <p>Hester
carefully avoided making any allusion to the love Laura entertained for Murray
Devereux; it was part of her plan to let Valentine make that discovery for
himself; but after prolonging the conversation until it had reached the limit
beyond which she did not wish it to extend, she closed it, quitting him that he
might have the opportunity of reflecting upon what she had communicated to him,
and the course he should pursue in consequence.</p>
         <p>He
did reflect. His selfish passions were at once set in motion. An alliance
with the daughter of Lord Alton presented many advantages which had not
occurred to him before, because he had not thought anything of the lady
herself; but now he remembered that she was prepossessing in feature and
elegantly formed, and a marriage with her would not be so great a personal
sacrifice as he at first imagined it would be; yet if it had been, there were so
many considerations which would induce him to make it, that throwing himself
away would have formed only a secondary matter in the interests involved.</p>
         <p>No man, let his position be what it may, can with impunity pursue a career of profligacy without penalty. Wealth and rank may do much to shelter an individual morally base from the consequences of his dissolute practices, but they cannot wholly screen him from a punishment of some kind. Valentine almost uninterruptedly had from an early period of his life, followed a course of moral debasement, but he had employed a large amount of artifice in the pursuit of his depraved pleasures. He had endeavoured by the exercise of caution to make the world believe that the worst it could say of him was that he was a male flirt. The heavy wrongs he had done in several instances he sought to keep as quiet, as private, and unknown, as cunning precaution could accomplish; but it was the source of constant disquietude to him, and had very nearly arrived at an <hi rend="italic">expos&#233; </hi>of a most unpleasant kind, when the attack was made upon him in the vicinity of Acton. He had barely escaped it, and was still suffering from its effects. What had happened to his assailants he longed, yet dreaded to hear. His impression was &#8212; and it was only too frequently the subject of his thoughts &#8212; that he had ridden them both down. He had a dim sense that when his horse plunged madly forward the wheels had rolled over some objects above the level of the road. He could only surmise that the officer by whom he was attacked, and his friend who had sprung to his fiery animal's head, were run over by the cab; and the strange silence which followed that all-but tragical event, almost confirmed him in the impression he had formed. He hoped that it
might be so, for he knew that when that assailant, even under more favourable
circumstances for him, stood before him again, an avenger was at hand.</p>
         <p>He
had detected the change which had taken place in the manner of Murray Devereux
towards him; he felt that he owed to him an explanation, one he was only too
anxious to avoid, because he saw plainly enough that the few observations he
had made in reference to it to Murray did not carry conviction to the mind of
the latter.</p>
         <p>A marriage into the family of Lord Alton he felt would give him a stronger influence in the world, it would render his position in many ways more secure. His own future expectations might or might not be realized, but in the union so strangely suggested by Hester Blayre there was a certain security he could not so immediately obtain in any other way.</p>
         <p>He
paced his room in a state of mental excitement to which he had long been
unaccustomed. It was not only that a sudden and important opening was
presented to him, but it was that the form of Gertrude interfered with every
attempt he made to realize a vision of Laura Alton. Amid all his selfish, and
even mercenary considerations &#8212; for, gambler-like, he was hungry after wealth,
let it come from whence or how it might &#8212; his passion for Gertrude obtruded itself.</p>
         <p>To
wed Laura Alton was to abandon all thoughts of Gertrude, but to root her out of
his heart was not possible. The more the necessity for such an effort
increased in the magnitude of its importance, the less did he find himself
capable of effecting it. To part with Gertrude for ever he could not; sanguine
hopes and fancies rose up, wild schemes, fatal to her peace, presented
themselves, but her station, and then her character, were formidable obstacles
to any such fancies or schemes, and he knew it.</p>
         <p>The words of Hester had, however, taken a fast hold of his mind. "She is but a woman!" he thought; "'a loving, trusting woman': those were her words, and if I can but find the way to her heart, what has her station or her character to do with the power I could at once assume over it? By Heaven but I will try. There is yet time. I could sacrifice a thousand Lauras for her, yet not her for all the world." Remembering that Hester had told him Gertrude was in the park while they were conversing, he took his hat and cane, and made his way where he thought it most probable he might
find her.</p>
         <p>"Beneath
the purple shadows of leafy branches, in some soft grassy dell" he murmured,
soliloquising as he went, "glittering with starry-eyed and crimson-lipped flowers, or by the side of a clear, cool, winding stream, tinted with overhanging trees&#8212;the clear blue sky gleaming here and there, with no sound in the air save the low-breathed music of the rippling waters gliding over the pebbles, or the dreamy hum of bees chanting over blossoms&#8212;then a woman's heart is disposed to love: she will listen with patience to ardent words from him to whom her heart is still indifferent. In such a place a maiden
may be always wooed, and in test cases won. Gertrude is scarcely of the ordinary mould yet, even under such influencee, her reserve tones down, the expression of her eye softens, and her voice modulates to a gentle music it has not in other places. What if I find her in the elm-grove? I can, unconsciously to herself, direct her course to some such place and try those arts to win her love which, until now, I have used in pastime, but which are now&#8212;out upon me for a weak fool!&#8212;to be employed in passionate earnestness."</p>
         <p>He
groaned, and pressed his hands to his temples as the conviction that he was
madly in love forced itself upon him; as he saw there was no escape for him,
for he could not at least part with <hi rend="italic">that</hi> love for a new one, and, that
it would cling to him, tinting everything he should in future see with its own
hue. </p>
         <p>He
hated himself for being in love in spite of himself; he cursed the passion
which defied his control, and would, unless he could win Gertrude, mar all his
future happiness. If he were compelled to that course, he would marry her, if
it should prove the only means of obtaining her, in preference to Laura Alton;
but he would rather have her love than her hand, and that he resolved to try
his utmost to win.</p>
         <p>He
rambled at a slow pace through the park in the direction in which Gertrude had
usually conducted him; but he went on and on through the lonely sequestered
places with which the wood abounded with watchful eye and listening ear. He
could not, however, light upon a trace of her flowiung garments, nor perceive
the print of her small foot upon the shining grass.</p>
         <p>At
last he stood still with the intention of returning, when suddenly the love murmuring
of human voices caught his ear, and he softly moved towards the place from
whence the sounds proceeded.</p>
         <p>He
passed at a spot where he could just distinguish the words so as to catch their
meaning. He heard expressions of endearment, and he felt himself grow cold as
marble, as he recognised the tone of one of the voices.</p>
         <p>He
approached yet closer, and between a small opening he beheld, with an
astonishment no words can depict, Gertrude De Brent folded in the embrace of a
man enveloped in a military cloak. He saw with infuriated wrath Gertrude raise
the hand of him who caressed her to her lips, and imprint a fervent kiss upon
it. Then they suddenly separated, and each, with hurried footsteps, took a
different direction, Gertrude advancing with rapid steps towards the spot where
Valentine stood, yet unseen by her.</p>
         <p>Suddenly
she reached the tree beneath whose shadow he stood, and he stepped before her.</p>
         <p>She
uttered a sudden cry.</p>
         <p>"Pray be not alarmed, Miss De Brent," he exclaimed, in a sarcastic tone; "permit me to apologise for intruding upon you. I fear I intercepted a little <hi rend="italic">t&#233;te-&#225;-t&#233;te</hi>, which would have been only too agreeable had I been the hero of it."</p>
         <p>"Gracious
Heaven!" ejaculated Gertrude, "and you beheld&#8212;"</p>
         <p>She
checked herself, and for a moment remained silent.</p>
         <p>"Shall
I supply the omission, Miss De Brent, by a description of the gentleman ?" he
said in the same tone.</p>
         <p>She
displayed agitation and confusion.</p>
         <p>"Mr.
Temple," she exclaimed, hurriedly, "I confess I have a secret which I would not
for worlds at this moment have revealed. As a gentleman, may I ask you to keep
within your own breast what you have thus accidentally discovered?"</p>
         <p>"Anything
you may ask of me, Miss De Brent," he said, with strong emphasis, "you may look
upon in the light of a command, and be sure that it will meet with obedience. I
confess I had rather it had assumed any other shape; but, be assured, your
secret is safe with me."</p>
         <p>"I
thank you, sir," she said, in a colder manner than before, for she liked
neither his look nor his tone of voice. "I admit the incident has a strange
appearance, but at the proper moment it will be fully and satisfactorialy explained.
Until the period only to which I allude, I request your forbearance."</p>
         <p>"It
is yours, Miss De Brent," he replied, with a more lively air. "I only ask in
return from you, a mien less restrained, a glance more kind and words less
carefully considered before they are spoken."</p>
         <p>Gertrude,
with a haughty bow, passed on. He gazed after her.</p>
         <p>"I
care not for scornful glances, nor haughty bearing; I have her in my power; her
secret is mine. She knows not how much I have discovered, nor shall I inform
her; but I will bring her like a falcon-gentil to my wrist."</p>
         <p>So
muttering, he slowly followed her towards Falkland Court.</p>


<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00125" type="image on fiction"/>
               </item>

            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>