<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00062">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">The Rise of Respectable Society: A Social History of Victorian Britain, 1830-1900</hi>
	<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapter 3, "Marriage"</title>
	<date type="original" value="1988">1988</date>

</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author name="Thompson">F.M.L. Thompson</author>
      <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00062</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 88-89 of F.M.L. Thompson's <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Respectable Society: A Social History of Victorian Britain, 1830-1900</hi>. Published by Fontana Press, 1988.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Marriage</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Rise of Respectable Society: A Social History of Victorian Britain, 1830-1900</hi></title>
               <author>F.M.L. Thompson</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Fontana Press
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
London</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1988
</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="british" type="place">British</term>
               <term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
			<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
			<term id="premaritalsex" type="theme">premarital sex</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
  <date value="2005-08-19">19 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-04-13">13 April 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>


         
         <p>Mingling with the presumed
anti-family influences of female employment, especially factory employment,
were apprehensions about the converging pressures of large-town life. Housing
conditions, unsavoury courts, rookeries, and cellar dwellings, and overall
chronic overcrowding, were denounced throughout the nineteenth century as
inimical to domestic family life and as breeding grounds for all manner of vice
and unnatural practices, as well as of misery. Where an entire family, husband,
wife, and children of all ages and both sexes, lived in one room any notions of
modesty and decency were grotesque, and chastity was thought to be an early
casualty. Constant murmurings of incest reached the ears of polite society in
the reports of slum visitors and parish clergy, the images of
brother-and-sister, father-and-daughter relations thinly disguised in
references to 'these breeding places of disease and vice and all manner of
abomination'. If incest was at all common or prevalent, which seems most
unlikely, its consequences at least must have been massaged away into conventional
and respectable forms; the illegitimacy rate, never at all high, was tending to
fall from around 7 per cent of all births in the early Victorian years to
4 per cent or less by the close of the century. This must have been in the main
the fruits of premarital and extramarital, rather than incestuous, intercourse.
Similar goings-on, whatever they may have been, were probably more characteristic,
and traditional, in rural areas than in the large towns, where in any case
overcrowding was quite as prevalent as in the cities. Nevertheless,
promiscuity, whether incestuous or not, was felt to be encouraged by urban
housing conditions and to be further stimulated by the pubs, gin palaces, music
halls, and other resorts of doubtful reputation which flourished in the larger
towns, partly at least as refuges from the inadequacies and unattractiveness of
home life. If to all this is added the virtual breakdown of organized religion
in the larger towns, of which the more earnest of early Victorians were acutely
conscious, then the full force of the supposedly pernicious effects of
large-town life upon the institution of the family can be appreciated.
</p>


         <p>Whether or not any or all of these
apprehensions were well grounded, they were the perceptions which induced, or
contributed to induce, a whole range of movements, campaigns, moral crusades,
religious, educational, and political endeavours, that were intended to reform
or correct the material and cultural environment so that, among other
objectives, the family might be preserved from the perils which appeared to
threaten it. These efforts, very largely but not totally misconceived and
misplaced, will be considered more fully in later chapters, as external
influences on working-class lives. They were, of course, very much internal
influences on the lives of the middle classes, in the sense that they were
largely generated by middle-class moralists and social reformers and
presumptively reflected what were thought to be already existing habits and
conditions within middle-class families. To this extent the content and aims of
missionary efforts intended to save the working-class family are most
informative about actual middle-class precepts and practices, and most of all
perhaps about middle-class fears of the fragility of their own family ideals
unless these were protected with constant vigilance by elaborate ramparts of
morality, modesty, reticence, sexual segregation, parental discipline and
authority, and male dominance. Any self-acknowledgement of such fragility was
customarily phrased in terms of the need for barriers of privacy and propriety
to protect the middle-class family from contamination by chance contact with
vulgar and undesirable people and their corrupting habits, people who might
include the raffish aristocracy as well as the great unwashed. The defences may
also have been required to protect the middle-class family from the
self-destructive potential of the desires and appetites of its own members. The
double standard, of strict chastity for the girls and condonation of wild-oat
sowing by the young men, never more than obliquely mentioned, was a tacit
acknowledgement of this.</p>

<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ID OF A DIFFERENT BUT RELATED FILE" type="TERM DESCRIBING NATURE OF THE RELATIONSHIP"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>