<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00003">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">Henry Ward Beecher</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Abbott">Lyman Abbott</author>
<date type="original" value="1904">1904</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00003</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 288-299 of the original 1904 publication of Lyman Abbott's <hi rend="italic">Henry Ward Beecher</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapter XII, Under Accusation</title>
               <title level="m">Henry Ward Beecher</title>
               <author>Lyman Abbott</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Riverside Press

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Cambridge                                         

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1904                          

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="history" type="media">history</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
			<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
			<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
			<term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
			<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>

	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>                                                                                             
		<date value="2005-03-24">24 March 2005</date>
		<respStmt>
			<name>Michael page></name>
		</respStmt>
		<item>Initial encoding edit</item>
		</change>

<change>                                                                                             
		<date value="2005-02-18">18 February 2005</date>
		<respStmt>
			<name>Michael page></name>
		</respStmt>
		<item>Initial encoding edit</item>
		</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

                  <head>CHAPTERXII</head>

         <head>UNDER ACCUSATION</head>

         <p>In
its immediate effect on national politics the Cleveland letter was not of great
importance. Party strife was too high to permit either faction to listen to
counsels of conciliation and moderation. But it led to an episode in the life
of Mr. Beecher, which for a time threatened permanently to becloud his before
unsullied reputation. To the narrative of that episode it is now necessary to
turn.</p>

         <p>For
the first thirteen years of its existence "The New York Independent"
had been under the editorial control of three editors, Doctors Leonard Bacon,
R. S. Storrs, and Joseph Thompson, all Congregational ministers of national
eminence. At the expiration of that time, December, 1861, they resigned, and Mr.
Beecher, who had been a frequent contributor, and whose sermons for the three
years preceding had been published in "The Independent," became its
sole editor. At his request, Mr. Theodore Tilton, a young prot&#233;g&#233; of Mr. Beecher
and a member of Plymouth Church, for whom he had almost the affection of a
father, was called in to be the assistant editor. The office work of an editor
was never congenial to Mr. Beecher. He was in constant demand during the Civil
War for public addresses, in addition to his church work. He was neither able
nor inclined to give much time to the editorial work beyond writing an occasional
"Star Paper" and editorials. When he went to England, he left "The Independent" in the charge of Mr. Tilton, and shortly after his
return, in the fall of 1863, he withdrew from the active duties of editor,
leaving his name for a time at the head of the columns, although practically
Mr. Tilton took his place. At the same time Mr. Beecher entered into a contract
with Mr. Bowen, the proprietor of "The Independent," by which he
agreed to contribute to the paper and it agreed to publish weekly his sermon or
"Lecture-Room Talk." This contract could be dissolved by either party on
three months' notice. This was in February, 1864; a year later Mr. Tilton
became editor in name as well as in fact.</p>

         <p>When
in September, 1866, the Cleveland letter appeared, there appeared
simultaneously a caustic criticism of it in the columns of "The
Independent;" and at the same time the publication of the weekly sermon
was suspended without explanation or notice to Mr. Beecher. He was forthwith deluged
with protests from subscribers who assumed that he had withdrawn his sermons
from the paper because the paper had criticised him. He endured this
misinterpretation for a little while; then he gave the notice required to close
the contract between him and "The Independent" and when urged by the proprietor to
reconsider his decision declined to do so. Three years later, on the first of
January, 1870, "The Christian Union" was started by J. B. Ford &amp;
Co., and he became its editor-in-chief. In twelve months thereafter the
circulation of the new journal had grown to 30,000, while that of "The
Independent" had sensibly decreased. For Mr. Tilton had proved to be more
brilliant as a newspaper writer than sagacious as a newspaper leader. His
utterances on religious questions were increasingly distasteful to the orthodox
churches; and the orthodox churches were the constituency to which in the past
"The Independent" had appealed. His utterances on the subject of
marriage and divorce, though possibly no more radical in theory than those of
John Milton, whom he quoted in support of them, were identified in the public
mind with American theories of socialism and free love. The religious heresy
might have been tolerated; the social heresy was far more obnoxious; protests
poured in upon Mr. Bowen from every quarter; he was finally forced to the
conclusion, to which he apparently came with reluctance, that a change of
editorial control was indispensable to the future success of his journal; and
Mr. Tilton was summarily dismissed from his editorial position.</p>

         <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Tilton's domestic
life was neither peaceful nor pleasant. The change which had taken place in his
views was an occasion of great anxiety and pain to his wife, and his mode of
expressing them would have given pain and anxiety to a woman less sensitive
than Mrs. Tilton. She was anxious to know her duty with reference to the
religious education of her children, and consulted her pastor. He advised
patience. There were other difficulties of a more personal nature, and at
length, her patience exhausted, she left her husband, sought refuge at her
mother's house, and sent her pastor a request that he would advise her as to
her duty. He consulted with one of the deacons of his church and with his wife,
and the three united in counseling a permanent separation, which, however, did
not at that time take place. Such, briefly stated, were the causes which led
Mr. Tilton to the resolve&#8212;I quote his own words&#8212;"to strike Mr.
Beecher to the heart;" such the origin of the charge preferred by Mr.
Tilton, and forming the basis of the persecution to which Mr. Beecher was
subjected for five years, which began with the resolve of Mr. Tilton in December,
1870, and may be said to have ended with the findings of the advisory council
in February, 1876.</p>

         <p>As to the charge itself, it is
difficult for the judicial historian to state it. First, Mr. Tilton affirmed
that Mr. Beecher had made improper proposals to his wife, but accompanied the
statement with the most solemn declaration of his wife's absolute innocence and
purity,&#8212;"as pure as an angel in heaven" were his words;
subsequently he converted the charge into one of criminal conduct. Mr.
Beecher's Puritan conscience, New England training, and great sensitiveness
combined to make him a purist as regards all relations between the sexes. On
the trial that subsequently took place, nothing of a suspicious character was
proved against him, except certain letters written by him. Persuaded by a
friend of Mr. Tilton that he had acted upon misinformation in counseling the
permanent separation between Mr. and Mrs. Tilton, and that his counsel had
directly aggravated Mr. Tilton's domestic difficulties, and indirectly led to
his dismissal by Mr. Bowen, and so to his social and financial ruin, Mr.
Beecher gave both verbal and written expression to the poignancy of his regret,
in language which was subsequently distorted into a confession of crime. To one
familiar with Mr. Beecher's readiness to excuse his neighbor and accuse
himself, these letters were not ambiguous; to others they might have been so.
That he kept silence concerning these charges, until they were given to the
public in a form which made silence no longer possible, was in accordance with
Mr. Beecher's lifelong principle, to pay no attention to slanders against his
name. If he had been more suspicious and less unworldly, he would not have
accepted without questioning the assertions of Mr. Tilton's friend, which led
him groundlessly to accuse himself. If he had early taken counsel of other men
more suspicious and less unworldly, he would probably not have been caught in
the net which was spread for him. But much as his friends may wish that he
could have taken such counsel, they must recognize the sentiment of honor which
forbade him both as a gentleman and as a minister to disclose to any one
secrets affecting the peace and good name of a member of his own church. That
he kept silence so long will not be counted as other than a fact to his honor
by any one who considers that the strong incentive to speak was only
counteracted by the stronger obligation of silence.</p>

         <p>Not until June, 1874, did Mr. Tilton
make any public charge against Mr. Beecher, and then in terms wholly vague. Mr.
Beecher instantly replied to it by a demand for a full and thorough
investigation. Then ensued a curious conflict, Mr. Tilton and his friend
employing all their resources to impede, thwart, and prevent an investigation,
Mr. Beecher insisting that it should be absolute, thorough, and complete. It
was not until after this investigation was begun that the charge against Mr.
Beecher was altered from one of improper proposals to one of criminal conduct.
The change was necessary in order to lay a foundation for the proceedings at
law which Mr. Tilton finally brought.</p>

         <p>I have here stated, though with
necessary brevity, all the facts essential to an understanding of this case. It
only remains to state with equal brevity the results of the three
investigations&#8212;one by Plymouth Church, one by the civil courts, and one by a
council of Congregational churches.</p>

         <p>The investigation on behalf of Plymouth Church was conducted by a special committee of six gentlemen well known in their
community and some possessing a more than local reputation. Among then were Mr.
Henry W. Sage, since known by his benefactions to Cornell University and his
services as one of its trustees; Horace B. Claflin, one of the most prominent and
influential of the great merchants of New York City; and John Winslow, a
well-known Brooklyn lawyer, who brought to the committee a recognized ability
in the examination and cross-examination of witnesses and the weighing of
evidence. The committee were appointed on the 27th of June, 1874; they
presented their report on the 27th of August; and after recounting their
endeavors to ascertain the facts, and exhaustively reviewing the evidence which
they had been able to obtain, they reported that "we find nothing whatever in the evidence that should impair the perfect confidence of Plymouth
Church or the world in the Christian character and integrity of Henry Ward
Beecher." This report, with the evidence on which it was based, was
reviewed and unanimously approved by the examining committee, and the reports
of both committees were laid before the church, after full public notice, and
unanimously adopted by fifteen hundred members, substantially the entire
resident membership of the church. This action of the church took place on the
28th of August, 1874.</p>

         <p>The second investigation was the
trial before a civil court of an action brought by Mr. Tilton against Mr.
Beecher for alienating the affections of his wife. The trial dragged on for six
months and ended in a disagreement of the jury, nine of whom, comprising all
who were men of Christian belief, affirming their belief in Mr. Beecher's innocence.
Before the trial ended, however, the chief lawyer for the prosecution was with
difficulty prevented from abandoning the case, and subsequently publicly
avowed his belief in Mr. Beecher's innocence; and the judge who presided at
the trial testified to his convictions, by presiding, eight years later, at the
meeting held in the Brooklyn Academy of Music in honor of Mr. Beecher's
seventieth birthday, and joining in the resolutions declaring that "by the integrity of his life and the purity of his character he has vanquished
misrepresentation and abuse." </p>

         <p>A year and a half after this trial
the largest and most representative council of Congregational churches ever known
in the history of the denomination was called by Plymouth Church to counsel it
respecting its action, which had been subjected to severe criticism by the
critics of Mr. Beecher. The roll of members actually in attendance was two
hundred and forty-four; they were summoned from all parts of the country and
from all schools of thought in the Congregational denomination, and included
not a few whose political or theological prepossessions would have made them
naturally suspicious of Mr. Beecher. Its sessions were presided over by the
Rev. Leonard Bacon, D. D., of New Haven, as moderator, and the Hon. Nelson
Dingley, Jr., of Maine, and General Erastus N. Bates of Illinois
 as assistant moderators. At the opening of this council Mr. Beecher appeared before it,declaring on behalf of the church that the council was desired to make whatever
investigation it might wish to make, by whatever plan of investigation it
deemed wise, and on his own behalf that an adequate and just investigation of
all the circumstances in the case was what he most coveted. After the
investigation was completed, he reappeared before the council, and was
questioned at great length, answering without reserve any question which any
delegate chose to ask; and among the delegates were not only eminent clergymen,
but laymen of national reputation, and among the latter lawyers skilled in the
art of cross-examination. Being without power to subpoena witnesses or
administer oaths, the council could not properly try the case which had been
already tried, but it conducted a public inquiry with a freedom which is
impossible in a court of law, and by its formal resolutions declared that
"we hold the pastor of this church, as we and all others are bound to
hold him, innocent of the charges reported against him, until substantiated by
proof." The closing addresses of Dr. J. W. Wellman of Massachusetts, Dr.
J. M. Sturtevant, the president of Illinois College, and Dr. Noah Porter, the
president of Yale College, assured him and the church of the unabated confidence
of the council, and of the churches which it represented. This judgment has
since been affirmed by the spontaneous expressions of Mr. Beecher's fellow citizens in the city which he made his home
for forty years; and by the verdict of the larger community at home and abroad,
to whose spontaneous expressions of confidence and esteem I shall presently
have occasion to refer.
</p>

         <p>
To
those who believe in Christ's declaration that the religious teacher is to be
known by the fruits of his work, the spiritual results of Mr. Beecher's
ministry during the years in which his enemies were continuing their frankly
avowed endeavors to drive him in disgrace from his pulpit, his city, and the
editorial chair, will serve as an even more conclusive evidence of Mr.
Beecher's character than the judgment of his church, the churches of his
denomination, and the spontaneous and unofficial verdict of his fellow
citizens. The statistics of Plymouth Church during this time show in the number
of dismissions no indication of suspicion, distrust, or dissatisfaction in
Plymouth Church; in the number of admissions by letter no indication of
lessened confidence on the part of other Christian churches; and in the number
of those received on confession of their faith no diminution in the number of
those converted to Christ through the ministry of the church and of its
pastor. Numbers alone are not significant of spiritual values. That
during these four years, 1872-75, Mr. Beecher's congregation remained
undiminished and the membership of the church was sensibly increased, might
perhaps be attributed to his oratorical gifts; that his church sustained him
with almost absolute unanimity might be, and by his critics was, attributed to
his magnetic personality. But neither Mr. Beecher's oratorical gifts nor his
magnetic personality can account for the fact that the entire work of the
church proceeded with unabated spiritual vigor as witnessed by its
Sunday-schools, its prayer-meetings, its varied philanthropic and Christian
work, the character and life of its members, and the permanence and efficiency
of the church which survived him.</p>

         <p>To this plain statement of the
wholly uncontradicted and unquestioned facts in this case, it may not be
improper for me to add an expression of my own personal opinion. I had some
special advantages for forming one. I was intimately acquainted with both Mr.
Tilton and Mr. Beecher. More than a year before the Cleveland letter I had
ventured to warn Mr. Beecher that Mr. Tilton was not the friend Mr. Beecher
thought him to be. I was personally acquainted with the incidents which led to
his withdrawal from "The Independent" and his subsequent founding of "The
Christian Union." My brother, Austin Abbott, was one of Mr. Beecher's
counsel in the trial, and I had special facilities for a careful study of the
evidence in the case, and certain editorial duties made such study a necessity.
In the advisory council subsequently held I was an active member, and my duties
as chairman of its business committee made my constant attendance at all its
sessions, both public and private, my duty. There was no proof at any time of
any act of impropriety on Mr. Beecher's part toward Mrs. Tilton or toward any
other woman,&#8212; nothing that could be called even an "indiscretion." His
only indiscretion was in allowing himself to be on terms of comparative
intimacy with men who were unworthy of his confidence, and in accepting as
true, without inquiry or investigation, statements which a man of more
practical wisdom would certainly have doubted, if he did not instantly
recognize their falsehood. After no inconsiderable hesitation I have given to
this story larger space than its real importance deserves, only because I
feared lest passing it by with mere scant attention would be misconstrued by
some reader. Personally I believe that future history will attach as little
emphasis to this episode in the life of Mr. Beecher as history now attaches to
analogous imputations, with far more to give them color, brought against John
Wesley in his lifetime.</p>

         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>

               	<item><xptr n="ls.00014" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00021" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00040" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00046" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00066" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>