<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00058">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"A Rich Breech of Promise Case"</title>
		<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
		<date type="original" value="1867">November 30, 1867</date>
            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00058</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 3 of the November 30, 1867 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         


</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>


<bibl>
               <title level="a">A Rich Breach of Promise Case</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
November 30, 1867

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-24">24 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Header Redesigning</item>
         </change>


<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>
A RICH BREACH OF PROMISE CASE</head>

	<head>
The Story of the Fair Eleanor and the Heartless Lorenzo</head>

	<head>
ELEANOR'S WOUNDS ARE HEALED WITH $8,000 DAMAGES</head>

	<head>
A Sad Story of Love and Cruelty&#8212;Seduction and Adultery in High Life</head>

            
         <p>Augusta, Me., Nov. 25, 1867.&#8212;An occurrence has recently
taken place in this city of which I find it my duty to keep the readers of the <hi rend="italic">National
Police Gazette </hi>posted, since its columns are eagerly scanned in this
vicinity for anything that is rich, rare, and racy. The item I refer to so
much overtops all other local matters, that I hardly dare to mention anything
else. It is comprised of a breach of promise case, which has been on trial for
several days, but has now been finished. It has been one of the most interesting
suits ever dragged into out Kennebec Courts, and the enormous damages which
were claimed, together with the standing of the parties, drew an immense
audience throughout the trial. The largest portion of the audience were of the
crinoline sex, and some of them had hardly got out of pinafores.</p>

         <p>The principals in this delicate difference of
opinion are Miss Eleanor Lawrence and Mr. Lorenzo D. Cook. Eleanor is a
spinster. When I say she is a spinster, I should also say a modest looking and
by no means bad looking spinster&#8212;a spinster who has seen the snows fall and
the grass grow for thirty-six winters and summers. A spinster who would not be
so had it not been for the cruel fate which has decreed that others should
enjoy the delights of the connubial state, while she should linger to an
uncertain age, ignorant of bliss which she has doubtless dreamed of, but never
felt. Lorenzo, the gay deceiver, the individual who aroused in Eleanor's breast
that unquenchable fire, and in her heart burning hopes, is a man thirty-eight
years of age. He is well to do in this world's good, a knight of the mortar
and pestle, and has about $50,000 stowed snuggly away, from which his victim
asked for a slice which to mend her broken heart. Both parties resided in
Gardiner at the time that poor Eleanor was so ruthlessly deceived. </p>

         <p>Eleanor Brought the action which has made this
trial, declaring that this compounder of pills promised to wed her and nobody
else, which promise he broke and espoused another, for which cruel and
heartless act nothing short of $10,000 would assuage her grief and make her as
good as new. Stamps, by the way, to heal a broken heart are often far more
preferable to a cup of "cold pisen." In the trial, of course Eleanor was the
important witness. In fact the promise to marry was simply a question of
veracity between her and the faithless man whom she had so fondly, but not
wisely loved. It was rich. She told the gushing story of her ardent passion,
of her interviews with Lorenzo, of his many professions of affection and his
ardent caresses, which she proved in the authority of Madame Young, a roving
fortune teller. She told him she could have wedded two others, who are not
apothecaries, but chose to stick to him; how many Sunday nights they had sat up
together in sweet converse, and how many toilet articles he had seen fit to
give her; all these tender little things she told in such a touching manner
that from the start she won the hearts of the honest jurymen. She swore by her
hopes of yet being a wife that once upon a time, when they were riding
together, the faithless Lorenzo promised to wed her within a period of four
years, which although her heart burned for a speedier consummation, she said
was satisfactory. What joy thrilled her bosom then! They were engaged, she and
her darling little son of Esculapeus. True love never runs smoothly, and at
various times they had their sweet little lovers' quarrels, particularly when
he danced and flirted with other girls, but those little ruffles were soon
smoothed down, and no harm took place.</p>

         <p>Whispers were floating in the air that Lorenzo
was untrue, and that his love was going from herself to other idols. She could
not believe herself at first, but finally the fearful truth burst upon her that
he was engaged to the lady who is now the partner of his joys, and who,
undoubtedly, does not much love Eleanor. At a public festival this alarming
truth was disclosed to Eleanor's bewildered brain. She satisfied herself,
beyond a doubt, that Lorenzo had gone back on her, and then consulted a
lawyer. Revenge was sweet and stamps were sweeter, and Lorenzo must play or
pay. Such was the story of her wrongs from her own sweet lips, in her artless and impressive manner. </p>

         <p>Lorenzo denied the soft impeachment. The idea
of marrying the maiden never entered his head, for he was not in that line of
business, when he called upon her, and so he told her once when she asked him
if he intended to lead her to the altar. His conduct toward her was the same
that it had been towards a score of other female acquaintances, and not a few
of such beauties he had upon a string, if we may judge by what he said; but
that he was a suitor, never!</p>

         <p>A host of witnesses were put upon the stand, and
several sweet scented notes of chops and tomato-sauce order were introduced,
purporting to have been written by Lorenzo. His witnesses were browbeaten,
quizzed, and bullyragged to the crimson blush, and Gen. Shepley, his counsel,
talked hard to save Lorenzo, but it was no go, and the jury brought in a
verdict of damages for Eleanor to the tune of $8,000. The amount was something
of a rib-roaster for interested parties, and made them look aghast. Exceptions
have been taken, and the case goes up to the Supreme Court.</p>

        
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>