<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00046">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"A New Niagara"

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00046</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 5-6 of the April 27, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">A New Niagara</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
April 27, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="arrangedmarriage" type="theme">arranged marriage</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>A NEW NIAGARA</head>

	<head>The Frightful Scandal of which Detroit has the Honor of Being the Place of Incubation</head>
	<head>BIGGER THAN BEECHER</head>
	<head>An Old and Reverend Episcopal Bishop Charged with Seduction, Lechery and Debauchery</head>	<head>HE STEPS DOWN AND OUT</head>

                     <p>Some weeks since the <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi> received from a correspondent
in Detroit the details of a terrific scandal involving a high church dignitary
and a young married lady of first-class social standing in that city. The names
of the parties and full details were given, but the accusations were so
startling and the scandal the revelations were certain to create, if given
publicity, of so overwhelming a character that we deemed it unadvisable to
publish the matter without a thorough investigation of it. This revealed the
fact that desperate attempts were being made to keep it out of the newspapers,
but that it was, nevertheless, gradually finding its way to the light of day
and that there was, moreover a well-grounded belief in the truth of the
charges.</p>

         <p>Meanwhile the following outlines of the scandal
appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Graphic, </hi>in which, however, all names were omitted.</p>

         <p>Detroit, April 12. &#8212; There is the very scandal
of all scandals afloat here, and one which, while it is in the mouths of a
hundred people, has been, from a number of reasons, kept out of public print.
It may, however, become public any morning, and when it does the Beecher scandal will not hold a candle to it, or, as I heard a gentleman remark yesterday,
"It will knock the Beecher scandal higher than a kite." For several days a
newspaper, in one respect, at least, well known, has had over three columns of
matter in type, which its editor has been induced, temporarily, not to publish,
but which, from my own knowledge, contains matter of much more startling
character than has ever been connected with any scandal which has become a
matter of litigation in this country. The parties to it occupy somewhat anomalous positions.  One is a divine, than whom none occupies a higher position
in his own church, or, for that matter, in any church in the West.</p>

         <p>The facts which I give to the <hi rend="italic">Graphic </hi>alone
are within my own personal knowledge, and the proofs are in such safe keeping
that they will never come to light except in connection with some legal agent.
At the same time these proofs have been seen by a dozen or more persons, and
their entire accuracy has been acknowledged by both the parties implicated.
The other party is a young lady of heretofore irreproachable character and now
married to a young gentleman actively engaged in business, and who knows
nothing whatever of the previous connection of his now wife with the
disgraceful life which cannot escape exposure after what is at present known
here and in Chicago. The relations between the young lady and the clergyman
alluded to extend over the entire years of 1874-75, and are fully shown by his
own letters. Most of these are of such a character as to render them utterly
unfit for publication, not only in any respectable paper, but in any paper
whatever. Published they would scarcely be believed. But they have been seen
by a number of persons, one or two of whom own papers and might have published
them had they not refused on the ground of public morals and public decency.
The case could scarcely be worse than it is. This dignitary of the church not
only did all and more than all that is charged against him, but went to the
extreme of arranging himself the subsequent marriage of the woman.  One half of the correspondence, that of the clergyman
alluded to, however, fell into the hands of a gentleman who had once been her
lover, and who, as much on her account as any other, with the added impetus of
fear for his own self-preservation, made its contents known to a number of
friends and then placed the papers in the vault of a bank in this city, whence
they will not be taken except upon a legal process. It is doubtless if they
now ever see the light, except through those to whom this old lover has shown
them, since the matter has been brought directly to the doors of the church of
which this clergyman is a member. A committee of three of its members traveled
several hundred miles to determine officially whether the charges based upon
the letters were true or not. They saw the letters and were convinced of the clergyman's
guilt. They returned and confronted him with the evidences. The woman, who,
throughout, had been with him <hi rend="italic">particeps criminis, </hi>had, however, informed
him that his letters, which had been sent to her from New York and many other
places to which ecclesiastical business had taken him from time to time, had
been destroyed. When he saw the proofs of his own guilt, presented to him by
members of his own church, and found that he had been deceived by her, he
begged for mercy and acknowledged the whole truth. An agreement was entered
into, out of mercy to him and her, and the friends of both, that he should
resign his office and proceed to Europe. On condition, alone, that he should
remain abroad was their mutual secret to be kept.</p>

         <p>To this he agreed.</p>

         <p>In the meantime all the facts, with most of the
proofs, has become known to the newspaper men here, and it had become,
apparently, impossible to keep the matter from the public. The gentlemen who
had forced an acknowledgment from him were influential enough to secure a
promise from the two or three persons to which all the details were known that
no publication of it should be made until he should have had sufficient time to
sail for Europe. The time granted to him for this purpose will have expired in
less than two weeks, and then the matter, which I have already stated was in
type, will appear without delay. The editor of the paper to which I alluded in
the first place, said, editorially, almost a week ago that satisfactory reasons
had been given it for temporarily withholding facts which it had, with proofs,
in its possession, and which, when published, would make almost the world
tremble. It had no desire "to blast the life of a young family and hasten to
the grave that portion of it which has passed its prime, which in fact, now
stands tottering with one foot in the grave. We have not the heart, though we
first thought we had, to bring to light a scandal which carries with it so deep
and grave a meaning. Our only reasons for not publishing the scandal are those
of humanity. We hold the destiny of thousands of people in our power and will
not use it."</p>

         <p>The matter has, however, gone too far to be much
longer kept out of sight, and when you know who the implicated parties are you
will not wonder at my statement that it is a scandal, the worst and the most to
be regretted that has occurred in our scandal-laden country.</p>

         <p>At last, however, the long threatening cloud has
burst and the result is another moral Niagara, which promises to rival in its
proportions the memorable one that flooded the country such a short time
since. In its issue of the 17th the Chicago <hi rend="italic">Times </hi>published
the following:</p>

         <p>Detroit, Mich., April 16. &#8212; Detroit has a
sensation as great as the Beecher-Tilton affair in that the party implicated is
equally as prominent in the church, and surpassing in the overwhelming
evidence, notwithstanding the last confessions of Mrs. Tilton. The hero is
none other than Samuel Allan McCoskrey, for more than forty years bishop of the
diocese of Michigan, but who has recently resigned in consequence of the
publicity of the facts about to be narrated, and will shortly sail for Europe where he hopes to escape the avenging nemesis of public opinion. The plain facts
are apparently that the Bishop has been for many years "Fasht wi fleshy lust,"
and has been decidedly promiscuous in giving vent to his inclinations. During
all these years stories have now and then been whispered abroad, but have been
suppressed by the good brethren of the Episcopal faith here, who have had to
take a supervisory interest in his affairs in more ways than one. Recently,
however, one came to their knowledge in so startling a form that it was impossible to suppress it.  The result is a vacant bishopric, a wandering ex-bishop, a
terrified family, an Episcopal community trembling lest the cloud should burst,
and a worldly crowd praying in a sinful way that the crisis may be
precipitated. A few months ago a prominent vestryman overheard two men talking
in an adjoining room about Bishop McCoskrey and heard enough to satisfy him
that something was wrong.</p>

         <p>He entered the room and after some little parley
was taken into their confidence. They showed him a number of letters evidently
written by the Bishop to a Miss Fannie Richards, a young girl of this city,
wherein were expressions that rendered it obvious that he had been and was on
terms of too great intimacy with her. The vestryman was astounded, and
concluded that it must be a deep laid scheme to blackmail the Bishop or his
friends. He was told that the letters had been left in the safe of a Michigan farmer by a printer named George McConnell. Quietly he obtained possession of the
letters and confident that he could work up a clear case of blackmail, he set
his wits to work. McConnell was sent for and responded. His story was another
astonisher. He said that for several years he had been on terms of too great
intimacy with Fanny Richards, and that he had known the Bishop was in the same
boat. A year or so before this he had been assisting the girl and her mother
to move, had discovered the Bishop's letters lying on a table, examined them,
and then placed them in his pocket for his own protection. All efforts to
extort any other story from him only excited additional particulars of his
knowledge of the Bishop's intimacy with the girl.  All that McConnell wanted was that he should be protected in
so far as he was innocent of any intent to levy blackmail, and, on receiving
the assurance desired, he surrendered the letters. The vestryman consulted
with another prominent member of the Episcopal Church, and, after they had
satisfied themselves that the letters were undoubtedly written by the Bishop,
they resolved to summon him before them. He came in all his official dignity,
but when letters were laid before him he broke down and became as a mere
supplicant.</p>

         <p>He at once acknowledged the authenticity of two
of them which bore his signature, and at first recognized a third as his, but
when told that his name was not attached to it, he attempted to retrieve his
error, and tossed it aside with an evasive remark. The two letters signed by
him showed that he was on terms of unnatural intimacy with the girl, but
nothing criminal. He scarcely deigned to look at the other letters and
pronounced them counterfeits. He nevertheless wished to obtain possession of
them at any expense. He was told that it would cost him nothing. If they
proved to be genuine he could not have them at any price, and if mere
fabrications they would be turned over to him.</p>

         <p>Being in the melting mood he swore by his mitre
that he had never laid hands on a woman except in kindness, but in the very
profuseness of his profession of innocence he frequently gave himself away to
the determined men who had summoned him to undergo this telling ordeal.  While he did not admit that he was the author of these
anonymous letters, he said he had no recollection of having written them; that
he certainly should remember them if he had written them, and all that sort of
talk.</p>

         <p>Two or three interviews transpired between these
gentlemen and the Bishop before they finally determined upon their course. Being
thoroughly convinced of the Bishop's guilt they at length placed the letters in
the hands of the standing committee of the diocese, composed of Governor Henry
P. Baldwin, Hon. Charles P. Trowbridge, and Judge James V. Campbell, laiety;
and Rev. John A. Wilson, of St. Luke's Church, Ypsilanti; Rev. Dr. George
Worthington, pf St. John's Church, Detroit; Rev. Dr. Edward Harris, of Christ
Church, Detroit, and Rev. Willis Hall, of St. Ann's Church, Ann Arbor. These
gentlemen were dumbfounded at first, and refused to believe the evidence of
their senses. It must be some horrible nightmare. They had some of them known
and loved the Bishop for forty years, and their families were on terms of the
closest intimacy with him and his, and besides, as they thought, the very
foundations of the great Episcopal church would be threatened with utter
annihilation were they to entertain these seemingly positive proofs of his
guilt.</p>

         <p>The first surprise over, however, they calmly
surveyed the situation like candid men, found their first fears fully realized
in the positive nature of the proofs and then decided to act. They accordingly
waited on Bishop McCorskey in a body, laid the case before him in a calm but
determined way and demanded his unconditional resignation.  He did not fully admit his guilt, but sought to prevaricate
as before, and suggested that he be relieved ostensibly on the ground of age
and infirmities, and that an assistant should be appointed to administer the
duties of the episcopate. To this the committee would not consent. Nothing
short of an unconditional surrender would meet their views. They would not
even agree that a resignation should stand in the way of a subsequent trial
before the court of bishops. One pledge, however, they would make him, and
that was that in case he should resign instantaneously the offending letters
should be sacredly kept in their possession, doubly sealed and secretly locked
in the vault of a bank, never again to be seen by mortal man unless demanded by
the diocese in convention, in which case they were only to be shown in
executive convention under pledge of the strictest secrecy, and then resigned
to the silent vault, pending the proposition. The Bishop advised to go to Buffalo immediately, there to remain for a short time, and then go to Europe and spend the
balance of his days in the society of his only daughter, Mrs. Stanton, now
residing abroad. He was assured that ample means would be furnished him by the
sympathizing members of the church. They hoped to be able to suppress all
information concerning the cause of his resignation, and even if the facts did
eventually come out, by that time he would have placed the broad Atlantic between him and them, and his remaining days could be passed in peace. Bishop
McCoskrey accepted the terms, and about a month ago the Episcopal world was
surprised to read his formal card of abdication.  He went to Buffalo, and to-morrow his aged, and respected
wife, who is as yet in blissful ignorance of the terrible facts, will leave
Detroit in company with her son-in-law, Major Stanley, for New York, whence
they three will sail for Europe on the 27th. Thus will terminate
Bishop McCorskey's career in this country unless perchance he should, after
finding himself fully exposed, with that bull-dog pertinacity for which he is
noted, determine to stay and stand trial.</p>

         <p>"In that event," said a gentleman intimately
acquainted with him, "his personal presence is so commanding that he would be
likely to overpower any ordinary jury, and by main strength and awkwardness,
secure a verdict of acquittal."</p>

         <p>Another chapter in this singular drama is that which records
the career of the girl Fannie Richards. She is a petite brunette, now scarcely
more than twenty years of age, and is something of a rattlehead, although with
a decided predisposition to beauty. At the time that this story opens, less
than four years ago, she was a school-girl, living with her mother. The
Bishop, as it is said, was attracted by her sprightly ways and employed her to
act as his amanuensis. It was while acting in this capacity, as report has it,
that the Bishop had induced her to yield to his wishes, although it would
appear that she had prior to that time been too free with McConnell. But it
seems that the Bishop, after a time, either tired of the responsibility, or
wish to make an exchange. He had, meanwhile, given out that Fannie was his
ward, and, it is said, had caused the information to be communicated to certain
parties that she was distantly related to him. Fannie met a young man named
Bannister, about her own age, and a clerk in a hardware store, and took something of a fancy to him.  The Bishop encouraged his fancy, and held out, it is
alleged, glowing pictures of the beauties of wedded bliss for the inspection of
the swain. To a poor clerk the idea of being wedded to a ward and reputed
relative of a Bishop was dazzling. He plied a suit to willing ears, and in a
brief time the nuptials were heralded. Something over a year ago St. John's Episcopal Church was crowded of an evening to witness the imposing ceremony.
The Bishop himself presided and performed the ceremony, assisted by two or
three prominent clergymen. After the ring had been placed and blessed, a
brilliant reception was given at the residence of Mr. Willard on Ninth street, at which the happiest man of all that merry throng was Bishop McCorskey, who
paid for the carriages, the supper, the wedding trousseau, etc. Frequently, it
is said, after the wedded pair was established in quarters, did the good Bishop
call to pay his respects and manifest an interest in their welfare, not taking
any special pains to make his calls when the husband was at home.  Banister was a mere youth, and the honor of having for a
wife a Bishop's ward did not, he found to his sorrow, pay the butcher and
grocer, to say nothing of the tailor, and he has since then had more or less
trouble in making both ends meet and is now domiciled at the Grand Trunk
junction, three miles from this city, and employed as a clerk in the offices of
that company.</p>

         <p>As to the letters on which the standing
committee based their demand for the Bishop's resignation, they are seven in
number. One of them was a drop letter. Another was evidently sent by a
messenger. One was sent from Saginaw City, one from Mount Clemens, and the
remaining three from New York, in the latter part of 1874, when the Bishop was
there attending in his official capacity.</p>

         <p>The drop letter, which bears the Bishop's
signature and which he admitted on sight to be genuine, alludes to his
disappointment in Fannie's not keeping her engagement to meet him in his study
at the appointed hour, chides her for her dereliction of duty, appoints another
meeting at half-past two o'clock on that same day, and closes by assuring her
that he is pleased to learn of her improved health and says he knew he could
cure her as he had promised to do. The letter from Mount Clemens acknowledges
the receipt of her very sweet letter, tells how anxious he is for the time to
come when he can return, urges her to write and tell him her inmost feelings of
mind and body, tells her that her kindly offer of half the bed and all the cover; she knows he will accept, cautions her to write at once,
directing to Saginaw City, and is freighted with a world of love and any number
of dashes, which are intended to represent kisses. He concludes by being hers
"very affectionately and trusting that she will burn this letter" as well as
all others. The signature to this, as to the remainder, is a sort of
quirligig, resembling the letter "H."</p>

         <p>The first letter from New York is dated October
8. He acknowledges the receipt of her very sweet letter, and says her words
are very sweet to him, as he knows this will be to her. He says he has
experienced such feelings on the receipt of her message, both of mind and body,
as he had never experienced before. He wishes he could see her just then, and
see her all "undiscovered." He thinks of her night and day. He imagines he
sees her at the piano, playing such sweet music, and thinks how happy he ought
to be. He also thinks how much they have confided in each other. He has given
her all and she has given him all. They must not deceive each other. Their
whole hopes depend on this. She must write again immediately, as her letters
are so sweet to him and their love is so great for each other that it consumes
the whole person. From New York, October 18, he writes again, acknowledging
receipt of her letter in which she has confided her innermost feeling of mind
and body. She must have no fears for the future, as he will take care of her.
He is pleased to learn that her health continues good, and that his cure is
permanent. He will take care of her so long as he lives. She has created and
excited in him desires which he never before felt for any other person. Their
union is forever and is sanctified by the highest solemnities. He then adds: 
"Oh, how I would like to see you and see you all in your loveliness! ! ! Be
cautious, and remember that secrecy alone can protect me, and burn this letter at once!  !  !"  Here follows a number of dashes, understood to represent
more kisses. The last letter from New York bears the date of October 29. He
acknowledges the receipt of her ever welcome letter and says although in the
midst of business and excitement he cannot refrain from sitting down and
answering her very sweet missive. "Every day," he continues, "passes pleasantly
because it brings me one day nearer my little wife. Your renewed offer of
one-half the bed and all the clothes will be accepted. I think of you in all
your loveliness. How lovely you look when your head falls on my bosom and you
realize the joy of affection. Oh, isn't it sweet darling, to feel the touch of
love? I send you a trifle of spending money. I intended giving you some
before leaving home, but neglected doing so. Buy whatever you want and have it
charged to me.</p>

         <p>"Remember that you are mine, and that I own you
all. You will see when I am home again the window open at my house as you pass
by. Come in as you go to school, for my whole happiness depends upon whether
you are keeping your promise with me, as I shall certainly keep mine with you.
We must not and cannot betray each other. My own sweet darling wife, I send
you " (here followed fifty crosses, meaning as many kisses). Among these
letters was one which the Bishop had written to the girl for her to copy and
send, in her own handwriting, to McConnell as coming from her. It would seem
that the pathetic Bishop had become jealous of his printer-rival, and desired
Fanny to inform him in as delicate a way as possible that she no longer desired
to encourage his attentions. The girl did as she was bidden, but immediately
thereafter hastened to inform McConnell of the ruse and to make herself solid with him.</p>
         <p>Another letter was one written to McConnell by the Bishop,
evidently in answer to a solicitation, in which the Bishop promised to use all
of his influence to secure the printer a good situation and manifested a lively
interest in his temporal welfare. McConnell, although reputed to be an honest,
straitforward man, was in humble life. This evident intimacy on the part of
the distinguished Bishop would alone give cause for suspicion that it cloaked
something deeper. Throughout all these letters there are expressions peculiar
to the Bishop, such as "sweet pleasure" and the like, which would establish the
identity of documents, it is said, among those familiar with him, even were
they not all written in that peculiar chirography which is unmistakably his.
Suffice it to say that there is not the least doubt in the minds of any member
of the standing committee as to McCorskey's guilt.</p>

         <p>Right Reverend Samuel Allen McCorskey, D.D.C.L.,
for such are his titles, was born in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, in 1804, graduated
in Dickenson College, in that town, and afterward at West Point Military
Academy, with high rank. Shortly after leaving the latter institution, he studied
and practiced for a time, only to renounce it in turn for the church. He was
ordained deacon in 1828, and was afterwards rector of St. Paul's, one of the
leading Episcopal churches of Philadelphia. In 1836, he was elected Bishop of
the new diocese of Michigan, being the first incumbent. He came to Detroit, where he has resided ever since, and has exercised the functions of his office
for forty-two years. Next to Bishop Smith, of Kentucky, he was the senior
Bishop of the Protestant Episcopal church in the United States.</p>

         <p>He is seventy-four years of age, very tall and
very portly, weighing nearly if not quite three hundred pounds. He has always
been a good liver and a man of the world, in the sense that he would rather
tell or listen to a good story than to discuss saintly topics, and could bear a
hand at emptying a bottle or cracking a joke. He was, although jovial and
jocular, exceedingly sticklish as to the prerogatives of his office, and was
quick to take affront when his dignity was called into question. He never
seemed to have any idea of the value of money, and although his pay was ample
he was everlastingly running in debt, and time and again has the church
contributed thousands of dollars to help him out of trouble. The more
charitable attributed this to his benevolence, while the knowing once were
confident that women were at the bottom of it.  He was proverbially broke, and although he is said to have
ordered goods such as pianos, carpets, boots and clothing, etc., with the
utmost prodigality, for various women, to be charged to him, he has seldom been
known to pay the bill. The city is literally alive with rumors of lascivious
happenings between the Bishop and divers women, most of the scenes being
located in the Bishop's study, where he is said to have provided himself with
peculiar facilities. A certain collector tells of having caught him with a
woman on his lap, when he went to collect a bill for carpets. Some of these
stories, equally as well authenticated as that on which the committee based
their demand for his resignation, date back more than a quarter of a century.
A determined effort has been made here to keep the expose out of the papers,
and it has been so far successful that not one of the leading papers dare touch
it.</p>

         <p>It has been charged that money has been freely
used, and at a late hour to-night your correspondent was informed by the
proprietor of a whisky paper, which proposes to publish some of the facts
shortly, that he had been offered $2,500 within an hour to suppress it. The
leading members of the church, however, are now satisfied that the facts must
be made public, sooner or later, and they regret that any measures were taken
at the start to suppress them. They realize that it would have been far better
to have prepared an official, full and candid statement for the press and are
only too glad that it is now published. </p>

         <p>My Lord Bishop of Michigan is a tall, stalwart,
fine-looking man, and when in England some time ago he was shown much attention
by the number of bishops and well-know clergymen. Your English parson has not
to bear the burden of as many canting, conventional shams as are common to
preachers in America, the world being perfectly satisfied as long as he is a
man of honor, piety, and manliness, that he should live as well as the rest of
mankind.</p>

         <p>Mispronunciation of American proper names and
titles is a very common thing among the English, and the ecclesiastical title
of "My Lord Bishop of Michigan," was invariable rendered so as to sound "My
Chicken." On one occasion when a feast of good things had loosed the tongues
and ripened the wit of a number of clerics, one celebrated divine, alluding to
the fine appearance and social and almost jovial qualities of the prelate from
the "Wolverine" state, remarked to some others that he didn't see anything at
all appropriate in calling him "My Chicken," as he thought from his appearance
that he looked like a "gamey old cock."</p>

         <p>Many a jest has proved a prophecy.</p>

         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00003" type="same subject"/></item>
               	<item><xptr n="ls.00014" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00021" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
	
			<item><xptr n="ls.00040" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00066" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>