<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00039">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">The Maniac in the Cellar: Sensation Novels of the 1860s</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Hughes">Winifred Hughes</author>
<date type="original" value="1980">1980</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00039</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 166-168 of Winifred Hughes' <hi rend="italic">The Maniac in the Cellar: Sensation Novels of the 1860s</hi>, Princeton University Press, 1980.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Influences of the Sensation Novel</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Maniac in the Cellar: Sensation Novels of the 1860s</hi>
</title>
               <author>Winifred Hughes</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Princeton University Press
</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Princeton
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1980
</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
<!-- ISBN, IF APPROPRIATE -->

</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="british" type="place">British</term>
               <term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
						<term id="fictioninpress">fiction in press</term>
			<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-04-13">13 April 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <p>The wrathful cry of
sensationalism, "that Cry of cries" for the 1860s, made the rounds of the critical journals and became established in their lexicon as a fashionable slogan, with
automatic, if somewhat vague, connotations. The word itself, with its aura of
patronizing disapproval, became an instrument of the status quo, in world view
as well as fictional practice. In fact, according to <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round, </hi>it
took on the quality of an "orthodox stone," convenient for the
"flinging at any heretic author who is bold enough to think that life has
its tremendous passes of anguish and crime, as well as its little joys and
little sorrows." By 1864, M. E. Braddon had already
begun to feel its effect as a "bitter term of reproach...invented for
the terror of romancers." One reviewer in <hi rend="italic">Belgravia</hi>, Miss
Braddon's publication, objected to the slogan as a "hollow, windy,
worthless ululation," and it is certainly true that both sides used the
term loosely, stretching its original application to a specific genre for
their own polemical purposes. For the critics, sensationalism was apt to
include the lower reaches of <hi rend="italic">Reynolds' Miscellany </hi>and the Newgate
Calendar, yellow journalism, Coburg melodrama, and spasmodic poetry&#8212;anything,
in short, from "mere trash" to "something worse." For the
apologists, with their loftier conception, it encompassed Shakespeare and
Sophocles as well as the Poet Laureate, whose popular verse "Enoch
Arden" turns on the heroine's unintentional bigamy. Both sides pointed to
Dickens, in triumph or in accusation. <hi rend="italic">Belgravia </hi>claimed him as the
"founder" of the sensation school, while <hi rend="italic">Blackwood's </hi>reviewed <hi rend="italic">Great Expectations 
</hi>along with all the other
current sensation novels, judging it much inferior to <hi rend="italic">The
Woman in White </hi>as a specimen of the genre: "With the most fantastic
exaggeration of means, here is no result at all achieved, and no sensation
produced upon the composed intelligence of the reader. ... In every way, Mr.
Dickens's performance must yield precedence to the companion work of his
disciple and assistant."</p>

         <p>During the 1860s, both readers and reviewers were on the lookout for
sensation, whether to devour it in shilling numbers or to denounce it from
literary pulpits. For some, like Charles Reade, it is the constitutive element
of fiction: "Without sensation there can be no interest." For others,
like the worthy Dean Mansel in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly, </hi>the only sensation
provoked is a distinctly unpleasant one, as certain popular novels "with
or without the intention of the writer, are strongly provocative of that
sensation in the palate and throat which is a premonitory symptom of
nausea." In any event, sensation was in the air, a part of the temper of
the times.</p>

         <p>As a separate
genre, the sensation novel now looks irretrievably minor in the context of
literary history. It became a genre in its own right through the process of
revising the ancient verities of romance and melodrama, and through the
same process, abolished itself as a viable and relevant means of expression.
Still, there are remnants of its brief popular reign even in the major realist
works of the sensation decade. One obvious way for its influence to surface is
in the form of parody, to which the sensation novel was particularly susceptible
because of its transitional status. As early as 1864, the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
Review </hi>was reporting that "two or three years ago nobody would have
known what was meant by a Sensation Novel; yet now the term has already passed
through the stage of jocular use ... and has been adopted as the regular
commercial name for a particular product of industry for which there is just now
a brisk demand." The jocular meaning seems to have
coexisted quite comfortably with the serious one, diminishing neither the sales
nor the impact of the sensation genre. In fact, the irreverent imitations in <hi rend="italic">
Punch

</hi>appear to have attracted a following of their own; at one
point, the<hi rend="italic">
Examiner 
</hi>ironically recommended that
Mrs. Henry Wood, to keep up her standing in the public favor, ought to
read "the thrilling romance of 'Mokeanna,' and write something like that."
And of course, M. E. Braddon, who sometimes wrote for <hi rend="italic">
Punch,

</hi>enjoyed poking fun at the very conventions she had done so
much to establish in the first place.</p>

<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00037" type="commentary on same author"/>

               </item>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00160" type="image on commentary"/>

               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>