<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00037">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Griffith Gaunt</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapters XVII, XIX, XXII, and XXV</title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Reade">Charles Reade</author>
<date type="original" value="1866">1866</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00037</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 189-192, 201-202, 229-233, 248-251 of the E.R. Dumont 1890 edition of Charles Reade's <hi rend="italic">Griffith Gaunt</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">from Chapters XVII, XIX, XXII, and XXV</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Griffith Gaunt</hi></title>
               <author>Charles Reade</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
E.R. Dumont

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1890?

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="garden" type="setting">garden</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
			<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
			<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
			<term id="fictioninpress">fiction in press</term>
			<term id="british" type="place">British</term>
<term id="fiction" type="media">fiction</term>

            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
  <date value="2005-08-19">19 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-22">22 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

<head type="editorial">Selected Scenes from Charle's Reade's <hi rend="italic">Griffith Gaunt</hi></head>

<div>
<head type="editorial">Scene
One: Catherine encounters Brother Leonard in the Grove
</head>
         
         <p>But her meditations were no longer so calm and
speculative as heretofore. She found her mind constantly recurring to one
person, and, above all, to the discovery she had made of her portrait in his
possession. She had turned it off to Betty Gough; but here, in her calm solitude
and umbrageous twilight, her mind crept out of its rave, like wild and timid
things at dusk, and whispered to her heart that Leonard perhaps admired her
more than was safe or prudent.</p>

         <p>Then this alarmed her, yet caused her a secret
complacency: and that, her furtive satisfaction, alarmed her still more.</p>

         <p>Now, while she sat thus absorbed, she heard a
gentle footstep coming near. She looked up, and there was Leonard close to her,
standing meekly with his arms crossed upon his bosom.</p>

         <p>His being there so pat upon her thoughts,
scared her out of her habitual self-command. She started up with a faint cry,
and stood panting as if about to fly, with her beautiful eyes turned large upon
him.</p>

         <p>He put forth a deprecating hand, and soothed
her. "Forgive me, madam," said he; "I have unawares intruded on
your privacy: I will retire."</p>

         <p>"Nay," said she falteringly, "you are
welcome. But no one comes here, so I was startled." Then,
recovering herself, "Excuse my ill manners. 'Tis so strange you should
come to me here, of all places."
</p>

         <p>"Nay,
my daughter," said the priest, "not so very strange: contemplative
minds love such places. Calling one day to see you, I found this sweet and
solemn grove: the like I never saw in England; and to-day I returned in hopes
to profit by it. Do but look around at these tall columns: how calm, how
reverend! 'Tis God's own temple, not built with hands."</p>

         <p>
"Indeed it is," said Mrs. Gaunt earnestly. Then, like a woman as she
was, "So you came to see my trees, not me."</p>

         <p>Leonard blushed. "I did not design to
return without paying my respects to her who owns this temple, and is worthy of
it; nay, I beg you not to think me ungrateful."</p>

         <p>His
humility, and gentle but earnest voice, made Mrs. Gaunt ashamed of her
petulance. She smiled sweetly, and looked pleased. However, ere long she
attacked him again. "Father Francis used to visit us often," said
she. "He made friends with my husband, too. And I never lacked an adviser
while he was here." </p>

         <p>Leonard
looked so confused at this second reproach that Mrs. Gaunt regretted having
uttered it. Then he said humbly that Francis was a secular priest, whereas he
was convent-bred. He added, that by his years and experience Francis was
better fitted to advise persons of her age and sex, in matters secular, than he
was. He concluded timidly that he was ready, nevertheless, to try and advise
her, but could not, in such matters, assume the authority that belongs to age
and knowledge of the world.</p>

         <p>"Nay,
nay," said she earnestly, "guide and direct my soul, and I am
content."</p>

         <p>He
said yes; that was his duty and his right.</p>

         <p>Then,
after a certain hesitation, which at once let her know what was coming, he
began to thank her, with infinite grace and sweetness, for her kindness to him.</p>

         <p>She looked him full in the face, and said she
was not aware of any kindness she had shown him worth speaking of.</p>

         <p>"That
but shows," said he, "how natural it is to you to do acts of goodness. My
poor room is a very bower now, and I am happy in it. I used to feel very
sad there at times; but your hand has cured me."</p>

         <p>
Mrs. Gaunt colored beautifully. "You make me ashamed," said
she. "Things are come to a pass indeed if a lady may not send a few
flowers and things to her spiritual father without being &#8212; thanked for it. And,
oh, sir, what are earthly flowers compared with those blossoms of the soul you
have shed so liberally over us?  Our immortal parts were all asleep when you
came here, and wakened them by the fire of your words. Eloquence! 'twas a
thing I had read of, but never heard, nor thought to hear.  Methought
the orators and poets of the Church were all in their graves this thousand
years, and she must go all the way to heaven, that would hear the soul's true
music. But I know better now."</p>

         <p>Leonard
colored high with pleasure. "Such praise from you is too sweet," he
muttered. "I must not court it. The heart is full of vanity." And
he deprecated further eulogy, by a movement of the hand extremely refined and,
in fact, rather feminine.</p>

         <p>Deferring
to his wish, Mrs. Gaunt glided to other matters, and was naturally led to speak
of the prospects of their Church, and the possibility of reconverting these islands.
This had been the dream of her young heart; but marriage and maternity, and the
universal coldness with which the subject had been received, had chilled her
so, that of late years she had almost ceased to speak of it. Even Leonard, on
a former occasion, had listened coldly to her; but now his heart was
open to her. He was, in fact, quite as enthusiastic on this point as ever she
had been; and then he had digested his aspirations into clearer forms. Not
only had he resolved that Great Britain must be reconverted, but had planned
the way to do it. His cheek glowed, his eyes gleamed; and he poured out his hopes
and his plans before her with an eloquence that few mortals could have
resisted.</p>

         <p>As
for this, his hearer, she was quite carried away by it. She joined herself to his
plans on the spot; she begged, with tears in her eyes, to be permitted to support
him in this great cause. She devoted to it her substance, her influence, and
every gift that God had given her: the hours passed like minutes in this high
converse; and, when the tinkling of the little bell at a distance summoned him
to vespers, he left her with a gentle regret he scarcely tried to conceal, and
she went slowly in like one in a dream, and the world seemed dead to her
forever.</p>

         <p>Nevertheless, when Mrs. Ryder, combing out her
long hair, gave one inadvertent tug, the fair enthusiast came back to earth,
and asked her, rather sharply, who her head was running on.</p>

         <p>Ryder, a very handsome young woman, with fine
black eyes, made no reply, but only drew her breath audibly hard.</p>

         <p>I do not very much wonder at that, nor at my having to
answer that question for Mrs. Ryder. For her head was at that moment running,
like any other woman's, on the man she was in love with.</p>

         <p>And the man she was in love with was the
husband of the lady whose hair she was combing, and who put her that curious
question &#8212; plump.</p>
</div>
<div>
         <head type="editorial">Scene
Two: Ryder spies on Catherine while she strolls with Brother Leonard
</head>
                  <p>So
the afternoon before she was to leave, Caro Ryder came to her mistress's room
on some imaginary business. She was not there. Ryder, forgetting that did not
matter a straw, proceeded to hunt her everywhere and at last ran out with only
her cap on to "the Dame's Haunt," and there she was; but not alone:
she walking up and down with Brother Leonard. Their backs were
turned, and Ryder came up behind them. Leonard was pacing gravely, with his
head gently drooping as usual. Mrs. Gaunt was walking elastically, and discoursing
with great fire and animation.</p>

         <p>Ryder glided after, noiseless as a serpent,
more bent on wondering and watching now than on overtaking; for inside the
house her mistress showed none of this charming vivacity.</p>

         <p>Presently
the keen black eyes observed a "trifle light as air" that made them
shine again.</p>

         <p>She
turned and wound herself amongst the trees, and disappeared. Soon after she
was in her own room, a changed woman. With glowing cheeks, sparkling eyes, and
nimble fingers, she uncorded her boxes, unpacked her things, and placed them
neatly in the drawers.</p>

         <p>What
more had she seen than I have indicated?</p>

         <p>Only
this: Mrs. Gaunt, in the warmth of discourse, laid her hand lightly for a
moment on the priest's elbow; that was nothing, she had laid the same hand on
Ryder; for, in fact, it was a little womanly way she had, and a hand that
settled like down. But this time, as she withdrew it again, that delicate hand
seemed to speak; it did not leave Leonard's elbow all at once, it glided slowly
away, first the palm, then the fingers, and so parted lingeringly.</p>

         <p>The other woman saw this subtle touch of womanhood,
coupled it with Mrs. Gaunt's vivacity and the air of happiness that seemed to
inspire her whole eloquent person, and formed a harsh judgment on the spot,
though she could not see the lady's face.</p>

         <p>When Mrs. Gaunt came in she met her, and
addressed her thus : "If you please, ma'am, have you any one coming in my place?"</p>

         <p>Mrs.
Gaunt looked her full in the face. "You know I have not,"
said she, haughtily.</p>

         <p>"Then,
if it is agreeable to you, ma'am, I will stay. To be sure the place is dull;
but I have got a good mistress &#8212; and" &#8212; </p>

         <p>"That will do, Ryder: a servant has
always her own reasons, and never tells them to her mistress. You can stay this
time; but the next, you go; and once for all. I am not to be trifled with."</p>

         <p>Ryder
called up a look all submission, and retired with an obeisance. But, once out
of sight, she threw off the mask and expanded with insolent triumph. "Yes,
I have my own reasons," said she. "Keep you the priest, and I'll
take the man."</p>

         <p>From that hour Caroline Ryder watched her
mistress like a lynx, and hovered about her master, and poisoned him slowly
with vague insidious hints.</p>
</div>
<div>
         <head type="editorial">Scene Three: Brother Leonard's
obsession with Mrs. Gaunt</head>
         
         <p>And now it is time to visit that extraordinary
man, who was the cause of all this mischief; whom Gaunt called a villain, and Mrs.
Gaunt a saint; and, as usual, he was neither one nor the other.</p>

         <p>Father Leonard was a pious, pure, and
noble-minded man, who had undertaken to defy nature with religion's aid: and,
after years of successful warfare, now sustained one of those defeats to which
such warriors have been liable in every age. If his heart was pure, it was
tender; and nature never intended him to live all his days alone. After years
of prudent coldness to the other sex, he fell in with a creature that put him
off his guard at first, she seemed so angelic. "At Wisdom's gate
Suspicion slept;" and by degrees, which have been already indicated in
this narrative, she whom the Church had committed to his spiritual care, became
his idol. Could he have foreseen this, it would never have happened; he
would have steeled himself, or left the country that contained this sweet
temptation.   But love stole on him, masked with religious zeal, and
robed in a garment of light that seemed celestial.</p>

         <p>When
the mask fell, it was too late: the power to resist the soft and thrilling
enchantment was gone. The solitary man was too deep in love.</p>

         <p>Yet
he clung still to that self-deception, without which he never could have been
entrapped into an earthly passion: he never breathed a word of love to her. It
would have alarmed her; it would have alarmed himself. Every syllable that
passed between these two might have been published without scandal. But the
heart does not speak by words alone: there are looks, and there are tones of
voice that belong to Love, and are his signs, his weapons; and it was in these
very tones the priest murmured to his gentle listener about "the angelic
life" between spirits still lingering on earth, but purged from earthly
dross; and even about other topics less captivating to the religious
imagination. He had persuaded her to found a school in this dark parish, and
in it he taught the poor with exemplary and touching patience. Well, when he
spoke to her about this school, it was in words of practical good sense, but in
tones of love; and she, being one of those feminine women who catch the tone
they are addressed in, and instinctively answer in time, and, moreover,
seeing no ill but good in the subject of their conversation, replied sometimes,
unguardedly enough, in accents almost as tender.</p>

         <p>In truth, if Love was really a personage, as
the heathens feigned, he must have often perched on a tree, in that quiet
grove, and chuckled and mocked when this man and woman sat and murmured
together in the soft seducing twilight about the love of God.</p>

         <p>And
now things had come to a crisis. Husband and wife went about the house silent
and gloomy, the ghosts of their former selves; and the priest sat solitary,
benighted, bereaved of the one human creature he cared for. Day succeeded to
day, and still she never came. Every morning he said, "She will come
to-day," and brightened with the hope. But the leaden hours crept by and
still she came not.</p>

         <p>Three sorrowful weeks went by; and he fell
into deep dejection. He used to wander out at night, and come and stand where
he could see her windows with the moon shining on them, then go slowly home,
cold in body and with his heart aching, lonely, deserted, and perhaps
forgotten. Oh, never till now had he known the utter aching sense of being
quite alone in this weary world.</p>

         <p>One day, as he sat drooping and listless,
there came a light foot along the passage, a light tap at the door, and the
next moment she stood before him, a little paler than usual, but lovelier than
ever, for celestial pity softened her noble features.</p>

         <p>The priest started up with a cry of joy that ought to have
warned her; but it only brought a faint blush of pleasure to her cheek, and the
brimming tears to her eyes.</p>

         <p>"Dear
father and friend," said she. "What! have you missed me? Think,
then, how I have missed you. But 'twas best for us both to let their vile
passions cool first."</p>

         <p>Leonard
could not immediately reply. The emotion of seeing her again so
suddenly almost choked him.</p>

         <p>He needed all the self-possession he had been
years acquiring, not to throw himself at her knees and declare his passion to
her.</p>

         <p>Mrs.
Gaunt saw his agitation, but did not interpret it aright.</p>

         <p>She came eagerly and sat on a stool beside
him. "Dear father," she said, "do not let their insolence
grieve you. They have smarted for it, and <hi rend="italic">shall</hi> smart till they make their
submission to you, and beg and entreat you to come to us again. Meantime, since
you cannot visit me, I visit you. Confess me, father, and then direct me with
your counsels. Ah! if you could but give me the Christian temper to carry them
out firmly but meekly ! 'Tis my ungoverned spirit hath wrought all
this mischief, <hi rend="italic">mea culpa ! mea culpa! </hi>"</p>

         <p>By this time Leonard had recovered his self-possession,
and he spent an hour of strange intoxication, confessing his idol, sentencing
his idol to light penances, directing and advising his idol, and all in the
soft murmurs of a lover.</p>

         <p>She
left him, and the room seemed to darken.</p>

         <p>Two days only elapsed, and she came again.
Visit succeeded to visit; and her affection seemed boundless. The insult he had
received was to be avenged in one place, and healed in another, and, if
possible, effaced with tender hand.</p>

         <p>So
she kept all her sweetness for that little cottage, and all her acidity for Hernshaw Castle.</p>

         <p>It was an evil hour when Griffith attacked her
saint with violence. The woman was too high-spirited, and too sure of her own
rectitude, to endure that; so, instead of crushing her, it drove her to
retaliation, and to imprudence.</p>

         <p>These
visits to console Father Leonard were quietly watched by Ryder, for one thing.
But, worse than that, they placed Mrs. Gaunt in a new position with Leonard,
and one that melts the female heart.  She was now the protectress and the
consoler of a man she admired and revered. I say if anything on earth can
breed love in a grand female bosom, this will.</p>

         <p>She had put her foot on a sunny slope clad
with innocent looking flowers; but more and more precipitous at every step, and
perdition at the bottom.</p>
</div>
<div>
         <head>CHAPTER XXIII.</head>

         <p>FATHER LEONARD, visited, soothed, and petted by his idol, recovered his spirits, and, if he pined during her absence, he was always so joyful in
her presence that she thought of course he was permanently happy; so then,
being by nature magnanimous and placable, she began to smile on her husband again,
and a tacit reconciliation came about by natural degrees.</p>

         <p>But
this produced a startling result.</p>

         <p>Leonard,
as her confessor, had only to follow precedents and ask questions his Church
has printed for the use of confessors, and he soon learned enough to
infer that their disunion had given way.</p>

         <p>The consequence was that one day, being off
his guard, or literally unable to contain his bursting heart any longer, he
uttered a cry of jealous agony, and then, in a torrent of burning, melting
words, appealed to her pity. He painted her husband's happiness, and his own
misery and barren desolation, with a fervid passionate eloquence that paralyzed
his hearer, and left her pale and trembling, and the tears of pity trickling
down her cheek.</p>

         <p>Those
silent tears calmed him a little; and he begged her forgiveness and awaited
his doom.</p>

         <p>"I pity you," said she angelically.
"What? <hi rend="italic">you </hi> jealous of my husband! Oh, pray to Christ and our Lady to cure
you of this folly."</p>

         <p>She rose, fluttering inwardly, but calm as a
statue on the outside, gave him her hand, and went home very slowly; and the
moment she was out of his sight she drooped her head like a crushed flower.</p>
</div>
<div>
                     <head type="editorial">
Scene Four: Griffith accosts Catherine and Brother Leonard
in the Grove
</head>
         
         <p>As he rode into the stable-yard be caught
sight of Ryder's face at an upper window. She looked pale and agitated, and her
black eyes flashed with a strange expression. She made him a signal which he
did not understand; but she joined him directly after in the stable-yard.
</p>

         <p>"Come
quietly with me," said she, solemnly.</p>

         <p>He
hooked his horse's rein to the wall, and followed her trembling.</p>

         <p>She took him up the back stairs, and, when she
got on the binding, she turned and said, "Where did you leave her?"</p>

         <p>"In
her own room."</p>

         <p>"See
if she is there now," said Ryder, pointing to the door.</p>

         <p>Griffith tore the door open: the room was empty.</p>

         <p>"Nor
is she to be found in the house," said Ryder; "for I've been in every room."</p>

         <p>Griffith's face turned livid, and he staggered
and leaned against the wall. "Where is she?" said he hoarsely.</p>

         <p>"Humph!"
said Ryder fiendishly. "Find <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, and you will find <hi rend="italic">her</hi>."  </p>

         <p>"I'll
find them if they are above ground," cried Griffith furiously; and he
rushed into his bedroom and soon came out again, with a fearful purpose written
on his ghastly features and in his bloodshot eyes; and a loaded pistol is his
hand.</p>

         <p>Ryder was terrified; but instead of succumbing
to terror, she flew at him like a cat and wreathed her arms round him.</p>

         <p>"What would you do?" cried she. "Madman, would you hang for them and break my heart;
the only woman in the world that loves you.  Give me the pistol. Nay,
I will have it."
</p>

         <p>And,
with that extraordinary power excitement lends her sex, she wrenched it out of
his hands.</p>

         <p>He gnashed his teeth with fury, and clutched her
with a grip of iron; she screamed with pain: he relaxed his grasp a little at
that: she turned on him and defied him.</p>

         <p>"I won't let you get into trouble for a priest
and a wanton," she cried; "you shall kill me first. Leave me the
pistol, and pledge me your sacred word to do them no harm, and then I'll tell
you where they are. Refuse me this, and you shall go to your grave and
know nothing more than you know now."</p>

         <p>"No,
no: if you are a woman have pity on me; let me come at them. There, I'll use
no weapon. I'll tear them to atoms with these hands. Where are
they?" </p>

         <p>
"May I put the
pistol away, then?"
</p>

         <p>"Yes,
take it out of my sight; so best. Where are they?"</p>

         <p>Ryder locked the
pistol up in one of Mrs. Gaunt's boxes. Then she said in a trembling voice,
"Follow Me."</p>

         <p>He
followed her in awful silence.</p>

         <p>She went rather slowly to the door that opened on the lawn; and then she hesitated. "If you are a man, and have any feeling
for a poor girl who loves you; if you are a gentleman, and respect your
word &#8212; no violence." </p>

         <p>"I promise," said he. <hi rend="italic">"Where
are they?"
</hi>
         </p>

         <p>"Nay,
nay. I fear I shall rue the day I told you. Promise me once more: no bloodshed
&#8212;upon your soul." </p>

         <p>"I
promise. <hi rend="italic">Where
are they?
</hi>"</p>

         <p>"God
forgive me; they are in the grove."</p>

         <p>He
bounded away from her like some beast of prey; and she crouched and trembled on
the steps of the door and, now that she realized what she was doing, a sickening
sense of dire misgiving came over her and made her feel quite faint.</p>

         <p>And
so the weak but dangerous creature sat crouching and quaking, and
launched the strung one.</p>

         <p>Griffith was soon in the grove; and the first
thing he saw was Leonard and his wife walking together in earnest conversation.
Their backs were towards him. Mrs. Gaunt, whom he had left lying on a sofa, and
who professed herself scarce able to walk half a dozen times across the room,
was now springing along, elastic as a young greyhound, and full of fire and
animation. The miserable husband saw, and his heart died within him.</p>

         <p>He
leaned against a tree and groaned.</p>

         <p>The
deadly sickness of his heart soon gave way to sombre fury. He came softly after
them, with ghastly cheek, and bloodthirsty eyes, like red-hot coals.</p>

         <p>They stopped; and he heard his wife say,
"'Tis a solemn promise, then; this very night." The priest bowed
assent. Then they spoke in so low a voice, he could not hear; but his wife
pressed a purse upon Leonard, and Leonard hesitated, but ended by taking it.</p>

         <p>Griffith uttered a yell like a tiger, and
rushed between them with savage violence, driving the lady one way with his
wrists, and the priest another. She screamed; he trembled in silence.</p>

         <p>Griffith stood a moment between these two pale faces, silent and awful.</p>

         <p>Then
he faced his wife. "You vile wretch!" he cried: "so
you <hi rend="italic">buy </hi> your own dishonor and mine." He raised his hand high
over her head; she never winced. "Oh! but for my oath, I'd lay
you dead at my feet. But no; I'll not hang for a priest and a wanton. So,
this is the thing you love, and pay it to love you." And with
all the mad inconsistency of rage, which mixes small things and great, he tore
the purse out of Leonard's hand: then seized him fully by the throat.</p>

         <p>At
that the high spirit of Mrs. Gaunt gave way to abject terror.  "Oh, mercy! mercy!" she cried; "it is all a mistake." And she clung to his
knees.</p>

         <p>He
spurned her furiously away. "Don't touch me, woman," he cried; "or
you are dead. Look at this!" And in a moment, with gigantic strength and
fury, he dashed the priest down at her feet. "I know ye, ye proud
devil," he cried; "love the thing you have seen me tread upon! love
it &#8212; if you can."  And he literally trampled upon the poor priest with
both feet.</p>

         <p>Leonard
shrieked for mercy.</p>

         <p>
"None, in this
world or the next," roared Griffith; but the next moment he took fright at
himself. "God!" he cried, "I must go, or kill. Live, and be damned
for ever, the pair of ye." And with this he fled from them, grinding
his teeth and beating the air with his clenched fists.
</p>

         <p>He darted to the stable yard, sprang on his horse,
and galloped away from Hernshaw Castle, with the face, the eyes, the gestures,
the incoherent mutterings, of a raving Bedlamite.</p>
</div>


<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="commentary on fiction"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on fiction"/></item>

<item><xptr n="ls.00039" type="commentary on fiction"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00160" type="image on fiction"/></item>

            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>