<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00015">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from the "Introduction" to <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi>, by E.D.E.N. Southworth

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Baym">Nina Baym</author>
<date type="original" value="1997">1997</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00015</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
 Transcribed from pages xi-xiii of the 1997 Oxford University Press publication of E.D.E.N. Southworth's <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Introduction</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi></title>
               <author>Nina Baym</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Oxford University Press

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Oxford
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1997

</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
0192832530

</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
<term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
<term id="courtship" type="theme">courtship</term>
<term id="commentary" type="media">commentary</term>
<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
  <date value="2005-08-18">18 August 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
	<name>Michael Page</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Proofreading corrections</item>
</change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-15">15 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

        
         <p>Louisa May Alcott, for example,
whose work clearly registers Southworth's influence, depicts the literary
career of Jo March in <hi rend="italic">
Little Women</hi> (1869) as getting off to a bad start on account of Southworth. Eager to publish,
Jo begins a career by writing stories in imitation of the extremely popular Mrs
S. L. A. N. G. Northbury (an allusion so obvious that nobody at the time could
have missed it). In chapter 27, 'Literary Lessons,' Jo first encounters what
Alcott calls Mrs. Northbury's 'trash' at a typically high-brow Boston lecture
on the Egyptian pyramids, where she is sitting next to a 'studious-looking'
youth reading an illustrated paper called <hi rend="italic">
The Weekly Volcano. 
</hi>Glancing at the illustration, Jo
wonders 'what unfortuitous concatenation of circumstances needed the melodramatic
illustration of an Indian in full war costume, tumbling over a precipice with a
wolf at his throat, while two infuriated young gentlemen, with unnaturally
small feet and big eyes, were stabbing each other close by, and a disheveled
female was flying away in the background, with her mouth wide open.' The story
turns out to be one of 'that class of light literature in which the passions
have a holiday, and when the author's invention fails, a grand catastrophe
clears the stage of one-half the <hi rend="italic">
dramatis personae, 
</hi>leaving the other half to exult over their
downfall.'</p>

         <p>Hearing from her studious-looking neighbour that the story
is first-rate and that its author makes excellent money, Jo takes Mrs Northbury
as her 'model' (ch. 34) and submits her own sensational efforts to <hi rend="italic">
The Weekly Volcano. 
</hi>'Eager to find material,' the
inexperienced author reads up on incidents of 'folly, sin, and misery,' thereby
unconsciously 'beginning to desecrate some of the womanliest attributes of a
woman's character,' feeding 'heart and fancy on dangerous and unsubstantial
food,' and 'fast brushing the innocent bloom from her nature by a premature
acquaintance with the darker side of life, which comes soon enough to all of
us.' Fortunately for Jo, at least in the narrator's view, she is rescued from
the nefarious influence of Mrs Northbury by the exhortations of the middle-aged
German intellectual who will become her husband, Professor Bhaer, who advises
her 'to study simple, true, and lovely characters, wherever she found them.'</p>

         <p>Since Alcott herself had begun her
career by publishing numerous potboiling melodramas under an assumed name
(melodramas whose authorship remained unknown for many decades), she was
obviously both alluding to and disavowing her own past through this critique.
But unless one has read <hi rend="italic">
The Hidden Hand, 
</hi>one cannot realize that Jo March herself, arguably the nation's most
famous tomboy heroine&#8212;Jo characterizes herself at the novel's outset by
bitterly complaining over not being a boy&#8212;derives directly from Capitola,
heroine of <hi rend="italic">
The
Hidden Hand. 
</hi>This
heroine, who enters
the novel in boy's clothing and romps through it disrupting numerous
expectations for womanly behaviour, is not only the first of a long line of
tomboy heroines in American fiction, but one of only a few in the nineteenth
century who never relinquishes nor apologizes for her tomboy character. She is
also the progenitor of the many female action heroines, especially female
detectives, who populate fiction today. These are the women characters whose
energy, curiosity, sass, street savvy, and above all compelling<hi rend="bold"> </hi>sense of
justice lead to adventures where they uncover secrets, right wrongs, and defend
true morality over social custom. The basic message of these popular novels
now, like the message of <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi> then, is that the essence of
true womanhood lies within and can never be compromised by merely
unconventional behaviour.</p>

         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">
The Hidden Hand
</hi> takes place mostly in rural
Virginia, after the urban street waif Capitola, who was mysteriously brought to
New York City from Virginia as an infant by a domestic trying to save her life,
returns there as ward of Ira Warfield, 'Old Hurricane.' Not content with life
as the plantation belle Old Hurricane wants her to be, Capitola ranges around
the countryside on horseback looking for adventures, a self-styled female
version of Don Quixote. Even as she battles with the notorious bandit Black
Donald and his gang, fights a mock duel, and rescues an imprisoned maiden, she
is herself the target of much covert villainy, because although she does not
know it she is heiress to a vast fortune misappropriated by the villainous Le
Noirs, father and son, who live on the adjoining plantation. Like most of
Southworth's novels, <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi> contains numerous initially
unconnected plots and a large cast of apparently unrelated characters, all of
which mesh in the denouement. Undoubtedly some of the fun in reading a
Southworth serialization involved waiting to see how the author would weave all
these seemingly loose strands into a single pattern.</p>

         <p>Unlike the far more genteel Jo
March, whose womanly character is apparently besmirched merely by reading about
crime and passion, Capitola has genuine 'premature acquaintance' with the
darker side of life. We meet her as a street child trying to survive in New York City by masquerading as a boy. Also unlike Jo, Capitola's experiences and
behaviour never even remotely begin to 'desecrate' her womanly character. Her
reason for cross-dressing is, precisely, to preserve that character. 'While all
the ragged boys I knew could get little jobs to earn bread, I, because I was a
girl, was not allowed to carry a gentleman's parcel, or black his boots, or shovel
the snow off a shopkeeper's pavement, or put in coal, or do anything that I
could do just as well as they. And so, because I was a girl, there seemed to be
nothing but starvation or beggary before me,' she explains. 'I felt bitter,'
she goes on, 'against fate for not making me a boy!' Then, 'all of a sudden, a
bright thought struck me: and I made up my mind to be a boy!' Disguised as a
boy, Capitola can support herself by doing anything an 'honest lad' can do&#8212;the
phrase making clear that no honest work was available to a 'lass'. 'The only
thing that made me feel sorry, was to see what a fool I had been, not to turn
to a boy before'.</p>

         <p>Since Capitola's masquerade would
admittedly be difficult if not impossible to maintain as she matured, and since
Southworth does not want to cut her story's ties to reality entirely, she
rescues her heroine from life as a boy at the start of the novel. Except for
her tendency to express herself in slang, and her continuing relation with her
best friend, a young sailor named Herbert Greyson, Capitola loses touch with
her street associations. But the issues of womanliness and gender introduced by
this opening segment of the novel continue to frame the fiction. 'Come, come,
my little man!&#8212;my good little woman, I mean,' says Hurricane to Capitola as she
explains why she chose to put on boy's clothing; and late in the novel he is
still calling her 'a New York newsboy,' complaining that she'll never be a
woman, and addressing her alternately as sirrah and Miss.</p>

         <p>Certainly <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Hand</hi>
could not have been the wildly popular work it was if it had been merely
serious and sober; at its core, this is an action comedy with a female lead.
Yet readers in the United States before the Civil War expected a good moral as
part of the package, and Southworth has several good morals to offer concerning
women, men, and society. Throughout the novel Capitola continues to reject most
rules of female decorum as humbug at best, perniciously hypocritical at worst.
The author regularly attributes Capitola's attractiveness as a character, as
well as her success within the plot where other female characters fail, to her
recognition of the dangers of false ideologies of true womanhood. Although
Southworth thereby attacks what seem to her destructively influential
ideologies of the feminine, she also powerfully affirms her belief in an
undeniable, real womanliness, and this is crucial to Capitola's appeal. From
the start we realize that Capitola has put on boy's clothes to preserve her
virginity; the point is made that conventional stereotypes, far from preserving
female virtue, are inimical to it. Southworth's criticism of female stereotypes
assumes that they injure women not only as human beings in general but as women
in particular; hence, whatever women have to offer as women is lost not only to
them but to society as well.</p>

<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00024" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00067" type="same subject"/></item>
              	<item><xptr n="ls.00004" type="same subject"/></item>
                           </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>