<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00206">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Anna Karenina</hi>
</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter">Part VI, Chapter 21</title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Tolstoy">Leo Tolstoy</author>
<date type="original" value="1877">1877</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00206</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 566-569 of the 1970 Norton edition of Leo Tolstoy's <hi rend="italic">Anna Karenina</hi>.  Originally published in 1877.  This translation by Louise and Aylmer Maude.
</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Part VI, Chapter 21</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Anna Karenina</hi></title>
               <author>Leo Tolstoy</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>Norton1

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>New York
</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>1877
</date>
                          </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="countrywalk" type="setting">country walk</term>
               <term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
			<term id="class" type="theme">class</term>
						<term id="russian" type="place">Russian</term>
<term id="fiction" type="media">fiction</term>

            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-09-27">27 September 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Coding</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
<head>Scene Two: Vronsky consults with Dolly on the grounds of the estate</head>
<p>'No, I think the Princess Darya Alexandrovna is tired and horses do not interest her,' said Vronsky to Anna, who was suggesting that they should go to the stud farm where Sviyazhsky wanted to look at a new stallion. 'You go, and I will see the Princess back to the house and will have a talk with her&#8212;if you do not mind?' he added, turning to Dolly.</p>

<p>'I don't understand anything about hroses, and shall be very pleased to,' answered Dolly, taken rather by surprise.</p>

<p>She saw by Vronsky's face that he had wanted something of her. She was not mistaken. As soon as they had passed through the gate back into the garden, he glanced in the direction Anna had taken, and having assured himself that she could not hear or see them, he began.</p>

<p>'You have guessed that I want to talk to you,' he said, looking at her with laughter in his eyes. 'I know that you are a friend of Anna's.' He took off his hat, and with his handkerchief mopped his head, which was getting bald.</p>

<p>Dolly did not reply and only looked at him with alarm. Alone with him she suddenly felt frightened: his laughing eyes and stern expression scared her.</p>

<p>Many diverse suppositions as to what he was about to say flitted through her brain. 'He will ask me to come and stay with them and bring the children, and I shall have to refuse; or to get together a circle for Anna in Moscow. . . . Or maybe it's about Vasenka Velovsky and his relations with Anna? Or possibly about Kitty, and that he feels guilty toward her?' Everything she surmised was unpleasant, but she did not hit on what he actually wished to speak about.</p>

<p>'You have so much influence over Anna and she is so fond of you,' he said. 'Help me!'</p>

<p>Dolly looked with timid inquiry at his energetic face, which was now wholly and now partly in the sunlight that fell between the lime trees, and then was again darkened by their shadow. She waited for what more he would say; but he walked by her side in silence, prodding the gravel with his stick as he went.</p>

<p>'As you have come to see us&#8212;and you are the only one of Anna's former friends who has (I do not count the Princess Barbara)&#8212;I feel you have done so not because you consider our position normal, but because, realzing all the hardship of that position, you love her as before and wish to help her. Have I understood you rightly?' he asked, turning toward her.</p>

<p>'Oh, yes!' answered Dolly, closing her sunshade, 'but . . .'</p>

<p>'No,' he interrupted; and forgetting that he was placing his companion in an awkward position, he stopped, so that she was obliged to stop also. 'No one feels all the hardship of Anna's position more than I do; and that is naturally so, if you do me the honour of regarding me as a man with a heart. I am the cause of that position and therefore I feel it.'</p>

<p>'I understand,' said Dolly, involuntarily admiring him for the frank and grim way in which he said it. 'But just because you feel you have caused it, I'm afraid you exaggerate it,' she said. 'I understand that her position in Society is a hard one.'</p>

<p>'In Society it is hell!' he said quickly qith a dark frown. 'It is impossible to imagine greater moral torments than those she endured for two weeks in Petersburg . . . I beg you to believe me!'</p>

<p>'Yes, but here, so long as neither Anna nor you . . . feel that you need Society . . .'</p>

<p>'Society!' he exclaimed with contempt. 'What need can I have of Society?'</p>

<p>'Till then, and that may be always, you are happy and tranquil. I see that Anna is happy, quite happy, she has already told me so,' said Dolly smiling; and involuntarily while saying it she doubted whether Anna was really happy.</p>

<p>But Vronsky, it seemed, did not doubt it.</p>

<p>'Yes, yes,' he said. 'I know that she has revived after all her suffering; she is happy; she is happy in the present. But I? . . . I am afraid of what is before us. . . . I beg your pardon! You want to move on?'</p>

<p>'No, I don't mind.'</p>

<p>'Well then, let us sit down here.'</p>

<p>Dolly sat down on a seat at the turn of the avenue. He stood before her.</p>

<p>'I see she is happy,' he repeated, and the doubt as to whether Anna was really happy struck Dolly yet more strongly. 'But can it continue? Whether we acted rightly or wrongly is another question; the die is cast,' he said, changing from Russian into French, 'and we are bound together for life. We are united by what are for us the holies bonds of love. We have a child, we may have other children. Yet the law and circumstances of our position are such that thousands of complications appear at present, while resting after all her sufferings and trials, she neither sees nor wishes to see. That is natural. But I cannot help seeing them. My daughters is not mine by law, but Karenin's. I hate this falsehood!' he said with an energetic gesture of denial, and looked at Dolly with a gloomily questioning expression.</p>

<p>She made no asnwer, but only looked at him. He continued:</p>

<p>'Some day a son may be born, my son, and he will by law be a Karenin, and not heir either to my name or my property, and however happy we may be in our family life, and whatever children we may have, there will be no legal bond between them and me. They will be&#8212;Karenin's! Imagine the hardship and horror of this situation! I have tried to speak to Anna about it, but it irritates her. She does not understand and I cannot speak about it to <hi rend="italic">her</hi>. Now look at the other side of it. I am happy, happy in her love, but I need an ocupation. I have found one. I am proud of it, and consider it more honourable than the occupations of my former comrades at Court or in the Service. I certainly would not exchange my work for theirs. I am working here, remaining on the spot, and I am happy and contented, and we need nothing more for our happiness. I like my activities. <hi rend="italic">Cela n'est pas un pis-aller</hi>, on the contrary . . .'</p>

<p>Dolly observed that at this point his explanation was confused, and she could not quite understand why he had wandered from the point, but she felt that having once begun to speak of his intimate affairs, of which he could not speak to Anna, he was not telling her everything, and that the question of his work in the country belonged to the same cateogry of intimates thoughts as the question of his relations with Anna.</p>

<p>'Well, to continue!' he said, recovering himself. 'The principal thing is that when working I want the assurance that the work will not die with me, that I shall have heirs; and that I have not got. Imagine the situation of a man who knows in advance that children born of him and of the woman he loves will not be his, but some one else's&#8212;some one who will hate them and will have nothing do do with them! You know it is dreadful!'</p>

<p>He paused, evidently greatly excited.</p>

<p>'Well, this brings me to the point of my talk,' he went on, calming himself with an effort. 'Anna can do it; it depends on her. . . . Even to be able to petition the Emperor for permission to adopt the child, a divorce will be necessary, and that depends on Anna. Her husband was willing to have a divorce&#8212;your husband had almost arranged it&#8212;and I know he would not refuse now. It is only necessary to write him. He then replied definitely that if she expressed the wish, he would not refuse. Of course,' he said gloomily, 'that is one of those Pharasaic cruelities of which only heartless people are capable. He knows what torture every recollection of him causes her, and knowing her he still demands a letter from her. I understand that it is painful for her, but the reasons are so important that one must <hi rend="italic">passer par-dessus toutes ces finesses de sentiment. Il y va du bonheur et de l'existence d'Anne et de ses enfants!</hi> I do not speak of myself, !
though it's very hard on me, very hard,' he said with a look as if he were menacing some one for making it so hard on him. 'And so, Princess, I shamelessly cling to you as the anchor of salvatoin! Help me to persuade her to write to him and demand a divorce!'</p>

<p>'Yes, certainly,' said Dolly thoughtfully, vividly rememberng her last conversation with Karenin. 'Yes, certainly,' she repeated resolutely, remembering Anna.</p>

<p>'Use your influence with her, get her to write, I don't wish and am almost unable to speak to her about it.'</p>

<p>'Very well, I will speak to her. But how is it she herself does not think of it?' asked Dolly, suddenly remembering that strange new habit Anna had of screwing up her eyes. And she remembered that it was just when the intimate side of life was in question that Anna screwed up her eyes. 'As if she were blinking at her life so as not to see it all,' thought Dolly. 'Certainly I will speak to her, for my own sake and for hers,' she said in reply to his expression of gratitude.</p>

<p>They got up and went back to the house.</p>


<div1 type="file references">
            <list>
               <item>
                  <xptr n="ls.00205" type="same novel"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00203" type="same author"/></item>
              	<item><xptr n="ls.00204" type="same author"/></item>
			            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>