<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00013">
   <teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">"A Bad Case of Brown"

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name=""></author>
<date type="original" value="1878">1878</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>
            <author></author>
            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00013</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from page 6 of the May 21, 1878 issue of the <hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi>.         

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">A Bad Case of Brown</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">National Police Gazette</hi></title>
                              <imprint>
                  <publisher>
National Police Gazette

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
May 21, 1878

</date>
                           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>


<keywords>
               <term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
		<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
		<term id="prostitution" type="theme">prostitution</term>
		<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
		<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
		<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
		<term id="breachofpromise" type="theme">breach of promise</term>
		<term id="policegazette">police gazette</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-25">25 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head>A BAD CASE OF BROWN</head>

	<head>Shocking Effect of Too Much Moody and Sankey on Female Chastity</head>

                    <p>PHILADELPHIA, Pa., May 11.&#8212;An interesting breach of promise
case has just been concluded in Judge Mitchell's Court. The plaintiff was Elizabeth
MeKeown, a tall, slender woman, showing by her luminous eye and pallid cheek
that some debilitating agency has been silently at work in breaking down her
health. Her suit was to recover damages for breach of promise of marriage, the
defendant being Thomas Brown, a man who has arrived at the meridian of life.</p>

         <p>Her story, as stated under oath, was that she came
to this country about twelve years ago, and after supporting herself in various
families with her needle, she obtained a position in a clothing store. While
engaged in this establishment, in 1873, she became acquainted, with Mr. Brown, who
was employed by the firm. The acquaintance ripened very quickly into intimacy,
and night after night found him in her company.</p>

         <p>She said she thought he was an awful good man, he
presented her with two Bibles and two Moody and Sankey Hymn-books, and every
night he read a chapter from the Bible, and their voices mingled in the "sweet by and by."</p>

         <p>At last the critical moment came, and he asked
her to be his wife. To make his avowal more binding, he took the little
gilt-edged Bible which he had given her, and swore that she should be his wife,
and then, to clinch it, got her to make oath that she would be true to him.
This was as good as being married, he said, and only wanted the form to make
them one. The old, old story followed, with multiplied sins. After he had
claimed her as his own he began his letters with "My dear wife," and made use
of expressions which assured her he intended to make her Mrs. Brown.</p>

         <p>In June, 1874, it was apparent that she was in a
fair way of becoming a mother. Then it was she said he forced her to Camden, and there the operation was performed that underminded her health. When closely
questioned by the opposing counsel the witness, with many signs of emotion,
exclaimed: "If God was to stand here: now, He would say that what I have said
is true! Look at me!" she exclaimed. "My face was not pale, and my eye was not
sunken then. I am ruined in health; I am ruined every way; and do you think I
would come into this Court to be made out a common prostitute?"</p>

         <p>The defense to these general
charges was two-fold: First, that Miss McKeown was aware that Brown was
married; and second, that during this period his mental condition was such that
he was not accountable for his acts, and that she, through the blandishments of the sex, led him where she
would. The servant-girl in the family of the defendant testified that she
frequently saw the plaintiff in the vicinity of his house, and on one occasion
she entered the dwelling, fell upon her knees, and begged of Mrs. Brown that she
would ask her husband's pardon for what she had done. This was subsequently
denied, however, by the plaintiff. There was other evidence to show
that the plaintiff must have known Brown was married before their introduction,
from conversations regarding him in their workroom.</p>

         <p>Mrs. Brown was called to the stand
in behalf of her husband, but, although he was in court, he was not placed on
the stand to deny any part of the plaintiff's statement. This fact counsel for
Miss McKeown dwelt upon with great force. The charge of the Court was brief,
the point dwelt upon most being that the jury should satisfy itself that the
plaintiff was not aware of Brown being married at the time of the engagement. After
being out a brief period the jury returned with a verdict of $1,250 in favor of
the plaintiff.</p>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>