<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00043">
   <teiHeader>

<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">from <hi rend="italic">Austin and Mabel: The Amherst Affair and Love Letters of Austin Dickinson and Mabel Loomis Todd</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter"></title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Longsworth">Polly Longsworth</author>
<date type="original" value="1984">1984</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00043</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 137-138, 162, 172, 174, 185-188, 190-191, 194-195, and 393-395 of Polly Lonsgworth's <hi rend="italic">Austin and Mabel: The Amherst Affair and Love Letters of Austin Dickinson and Mabel Loomis Todd.</hi>, Farrar, Straus, and Giroux, 1984.


</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Selected Letters</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Austin and Mabel: The Amherst Affair and Love Letters of Austin Dickinson and Mabel Loomis Todd</hi></title>
               <author>Polly Longsworth</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
Farrar, Straus, Giroux

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
New York

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1984

</date>
               <idno type="ISBN">
83-20579

</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
<keywords>
               <term id="american" type="place">American</term>
               <term id="history" type="media">history</term>
			<term id="todd-dickinson">todd-dickinson</term>
			<term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
			<term id="piano" type="setting">piano</term>
			<term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>

<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
<change>
               <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-04-06">06 April 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head type="editorial">Selected Love Letters of Mabel Loomis Todd and Austin Dickinson</head>

<div>
         <head>MABEL TO AUSTIN</head>
<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">[6 December 1882]</hi> Wednesday,
9:30 p.m.</dateline></opener>

         
         <p>Several
things have occurred which have made me very happy since I left you &#8212; I will
not write of them &#8212; but I will tell you at the first opportunity. Only I
thought you would be glad to know <hi rend="italic">
my 
</hi>sky
has changed from leaden clouds to sunshine, as the day did. Even if the happy
things had not occurred, I think our walk would have made me peaceful &amp; joyous, alone. It is almost more to me than any of our previous experiences. I
told you there were episodes in it which would last for hours, and it is so.
They do not pass away from me a particle. I have had several visitors, but I
should not have felt alone if there had been none. You <hi rend="italic">
know

</hi>I
love you. I must see you in some way
tomorrow. I shall be out on various errands in the street soon after eleven. I
am so happy and proud tonight when I think &amp; know what you have given me&#8212; what I am to you &#8212; that everything is radiant. I do not think I have entirely
and fully appreciated its magnitude before, but I do now<hi rend="italic">
&#8212;thoroughly&#8212;</hi>and what I give back to you is now great in proportion.
That I could very easily prove to you if you were but here at this moment, as I
most devoutly wish you were, but you asked me to imagine your presence &#8212; always
&#8212; and I do. In fact I could not help so doing if I would. Oh I love you <hi rend="italic">
thrillingly.

</hi>Do you know it?  <hi rend="italic">
Dont you 
</hi>know
it! You brought me very close to you in that walk &#8212; so that I know I can never
leave you again, in reality. I am going to seal this letter tonight and so not
put in anything more in the morning, but you will know that I shall love you
more when I awake than I do now, and that I give you a kiss such as we know at
this moment.</p>

</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>
<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[Ca. late 1882]</hi>
</dateline></opener>

       
         <p>Dearer
nearer, sweeter every time &#8212; those forty minutes last night, the happiest
fullest most joyous yet. It seemed to me we touched bottom in that walk and
talk so far as words can do it. I have been happier in the hours since than
ever before. I do believe you, my darling, and believe you love me as I love
you. It was no fault of yours or of mine that I could not take this in at
first. My experience of life was too firm &amp; encrusted to permit it. It
contradicts everything, revolutionizes everything, overturns everything with
me &#8212; astonishes &amp; overwhelms me as much as overjoys &amp; intoxicates me. I
love you, I admire you, I idolize you. I am exalted by your love for me. I am
strong as not for a long time before &#8212; elastic, well. I walk the street airily
&amp; with high pride, for I am loved &#8212; loved as I love, loved where I love.
You fill my heart &amp; my mind &amp; my life &amp; my world x x x x Your note
has just come. Great Heavens, my darling, I am transported by it, almost
overpowered. We love.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>MABEL TO AUSTIN</head>

        <text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[ca. early June 1883]
</hi>
</dateline></opener>

         <p>I
have thought all day about you and I want to see you more than I can express. I
love you most deeply every moment, and a drive alone with you seems radiant joy
even in anticipation. I have looked with great tenderness upon two or three
places lately &#8212; where we were once together &#8212; the Mill Valley walk, and another &#8212; just beyond Mrs. Heaton's. Do you remember them?</p>

         <p>Oh!
My darling, <hi rend="italic">
sometime 
</hi>we shall go <hi rend="italic">together</hi> over
all the drives, and walks, and places of happy memory. Did you know that the
crickets have come! In every little chirp I seem to hear one expression of your
wonderful love for me. It is a love which cannot fail to move circumstances and
conditions, and bring its reward.</p>

         <p>It
is of God &#8212; true and marvelously tender and rare. And I love you! How can I
help it. You understand me. You appreciate every little fineness. You bring out
every truest part of my nature.</p>

         <p>I
feel very hopeful and happy today. As I have told you before &#8212; something is
coming to bring us nearer together &#8212; and that soon. I have no idea what, but
that does not matter &#8212; I love you.</p>

         <p>Will you <hi rend="italic">
please 
</hi>burn
this today! I know you will, because I ask you. I have so many things to say to
you, but I hope this one note will say a little to you.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>
<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[November 1883]
</hi>
</dateline></opener>

        
         <p>Love, Love, dear
love. This is our second Thanksgiving. I loved you a year ago, and I know it. I
love you a great deal more now though. My love and your love have expanded and
exceeded one. All I am &#8212; and all I can be &#8212; I give to you. I want to write now &#8212; I have.</p>

         <p>Yes, darling I <hi rend="italic">
have

</hi>something to be thankful for, and grateful for, this sad
day, with my boy gone, and except for you, alone. I have you. Would to God I
had you closer &#8212; in my house, at my hearth, in my arms! Would not this be too
much?  Would it!</p>

         <p>Darling,
I love you in all the ways I have ever told you, and in all the ways love has,
but my love for you today is a more solemn and sacred thing than ever before.</p>

         <p>I
realize that it is you and your love that stand behind it &#8212; and are revealed by it. We have indeed come to the holy of holies. </p>

         <p>I
know you will not change either. You are beyond your years &#8212; vastly, in
knowledge and experience of the human heart, and in subtle distinction and
realization of the deepest secrets of human life.  If anything is true &#8212;
and real, our love is. We were made to give joy to each other. I love you &#8212; I
love you.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[ca. early December 1883]
</hi>
</dateline></opener>

         <p>Written
words alone are too insufficient now. We have come too near together. We want
the true quick speech of the eye &#8212; the personal presence which allows the wild life
current to throb back and forth from one to the other, with its subtle messages
of information and response in no other wise to be imparted or conveyed, as we
stand just before the veil of closest intimacy. We must wait for these&#8212;we will
get them as soon as we can. Meanwhile, my beloved &amp; my own, soul of my
soul, &amp; life of my life, rest assured of everything&#8212;everything that I am,
can say, or think, or do, or be&#8212;all are yours. And my business must be to keep
the white heat which engulfs my being from flaming in the surface.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[20 December 1883]</hi></dateline>
<dateline>Thursday eve</dateline>
<dateline>By Lamp Light</dateline>
</opener>

                  <p>What
words are adequate now! Wonderful and beautiful and inspiring as they have been
in these months and days of the last year and a half, we are beyond them now.
We can hardly more than repeat with them. There is more now in the deep silent
look down each other's eyes &#8212; in the consciousness of nearness, even to
absolute unison of being. What language is to measure our last experiences! We
know them &#8212; they are a part of us forever more &#8212; they are ourselves &#8212; and they
are ours.</p>

         <p>I understand them,
darling, I appreciate them, even to the finest shade &#8212; all their greatness, all
their solemnity, all their sublimity. I do &#8212; and for what you have given me I
give you the whole devotion of my soul for time and for eternity. Can I say
more!</p>

         <p>As
the darkness of the evening deepens I find I am to miss you terribly, more than
I had thought before. But I shall have a great stay in my near memory &#8212; and I
shall try to bear it bravely. I shall know that at 5 every evening, the time
we have had for walking and smiling, and at nine again, and at ten in the morning,
you are thinking wholly of me and that you know I am thinking wholly of you. We
shall probably think of each other at several other times in the day.</p>

         <p>Now I must leave
to find you at the station. </p>

         <p>I love you&#8212;how! <hi rend="italic">As
I can love</hi>.</p>

         <p>One more goodbye dear, dear heart &#8212; </p>

         
            <closer><hi rend="italic">
Sweet
goodbye &#8212; 
</hi></closer>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>
         <text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">[early
1884]</hi></dateline></opener>

       
         <p>Yes, my darling,
I did promise you that sometime I would put into your hands the story of my life,
to use as a shield, if ever &#8212; when I am not here to answer for myself &#8212; any
attack shall be made upon my love for you, or yours for me, or our relations to
each other.</p>

         <p>And yet is it
not better and nobler that I say nothing which involves any other, reflects
upon any other! may offend or wound. Is it not better to begin with my meeting you, and for the first time feeling clear
sunshine! What is the past in the face of the present and the future, as we now
see it!
</p>

         <p>Is
it not better, and enough, for me to say, simply, what I have said so many
times before, that I love you, love you, love you with all my mind,
and heart, and strength! and that I know what I mean when I say this, that with
you my real life began! That with you I have found what life may mean! That in
you I have found the sweetest, richest dreams of my boyhood, youth, and early
manhood more than realized! That I have found in you what a woman may be to a
man, hope, courage, joy, inspiration, rest, peace, religion! That in you I have
found my perfect soul-mate, for time and eternity....</p>

         <p>
Conventionalism
is for those not strong enough to be laws for themselves, or to conform
themselves to the great higher law where all the harmonies meet. I love you,
love you, now and for ever, and it is my great joy that my love is as much to
you as yours to me. The fullness and sweetness and brightness &#8212; and excellent
happiness &#8212; and hope, and thrill, and ecstasy of the days since in that sudden
flash of light when we stood revealed to each other, through and through, and
saw that each was, in the divine order, the other's world &#8212; are part of our existence
forevermore.</p>

         <p>
How
much we have to be grateful for, even though we have been obliged to defer some
of our hopes &#8212; everything will come in good time.</p>

         <p>Once more I love
you &#8212; and again I love you, my dearest, dearest Mabel, and without my will, and
with my will am your</p>

         <closer><hi rend="italic">own</hi>
  Austin.</closer>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>MABEL TO AUSTIN</head>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[2 March 1884] 
</hi></dateline>
<dateline>Sunday afternoon
</dateline></opener>

        
         <p>. . . Your "new idea" is another dainty touch of poetry &#8212; it is
exquisite. But I feel with you that our present experience is richer and
greater than the childish idyl could have been. There is a strength now of
which that other phase could not have dreamed. And the end will be infinitely
larger and more satisfying &#8212; <hi rend="italic">dear. </hi>
Instead of wandering hand in
hand through actual woodland ways, in the freshness of morning, we &#8212; you and I
&#8212; had watched the sweet unfolding of nature's heart to us, alone. You, as you
said to me, had walked on through clouds and sunshine &#8212; all alone, and oh!
grateful am I beyond words, that the lonesomeness and the grey skies have not dimmed
your clear eyes to any of nature's sweet, half-told stories. That uncurling
ferns and open-eyed daisies, and far blue hills speak with just as much
response and tenderness to your dear heart now, as when you first felt their
wonderful charm &#8212; and it has spoken volumes to me of your rare nature that all
these lovable things meant so much to you in the well-nigh fatal absence of
other things which should have sweetened your life. I loved you for it &#8212; I
revered you for it before I saw all those other phases for which I also &#8212; now &#8212;
love and revere you. And in those dewy "by-paths," you either stopped
and waited for me, or I ran, with a strength divinely inspired, and overtook
you &#8212; because here we are, together. The hand you took does not seek to go
away&#8212;rather it clasps yours tightly, and with an infinite love and trust goes
whither soever you shall lead. . . . You have deepened my life, and broadened
it, and exalted it. Your marvelous love for me would have done that to some
extent, even if I had not responded to it. But now all the best in my soul
stretches forth its hands to you. And what has always seemed to me like the
dear God's love, is embodied to me in yours &#8212; magnificent, all-embracing; true
and noble and divinely tender. Oh! my love, my dear love, God will forgive me
if I see Him in you and through you principally, now, for it is surely a
revelation to me of Himself. And I <hi rend="italic">
know 
</hi>He
did it. This wonderful companionship and sweet, sweet knowing of each other
never emanated from this world solely. Dear, it was heaven-born, heaven-guided
and sent. And it is sacred forever. You have come into my life and changed it
all. I look upon the outer and the inner world with clearer vision because of
you....</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">
[March 1884]
</hi>
</dateline></opener>

                  
         <p>Dear,
dear, great heart, to have even that letter is enough for a life. With that
trophy alone on my breast I could face death undaunted. Where in story, in all
the ages, has portrayal of love reckoned the most superlative and exceptional,
reached the heights where we habitually move! Equalled in passion probably, but
unapproached in subtle delicacy and sympathy &#8212; mental, moral &amp; physical.
Enveloped in an atmosphere all its own, of its own creation. I read it before I
went down &#8212; came up again in the evening to read it again &#8212; and had hard
struggle not to fly straight to you before I should sleep.</p>

         <p>The full hour I had with you seemed but an
instant, time hastens so in your presence, lags so out of it. I dread to go
off even for over one night, but I shall think of you constantly.</p>

         <p>I love you &#8212; I love you, as you know I can
love. I admire you &#8212; and am yours, wholly yours, forever and forever.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>MABEL TO AUSTIN</head>

        <text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline>15 July 1884</dateline>
<dateline>Tuesday Morning</dateline></opener>

        
         <p>My darling, I am in a state of intense mental exaltation this
inspiring day. Our yesterday's experience has been an elixir to everything
which is noblest in me. A great and grand purpose &#8212; which has before been
merely an occasional impulse &#8212; has been born to me. To live for character, and
richness and depth of feeling and life &#8212; to strive every day for a loftiness
which shall fitly match, even equal, yours &#8212; has come to me as my aim and
object. It is not only that through you everything outward is changed &#8212; that
the hills are bluer, the sky serener, the bird-songs more ecstatic &#8212; but my
whole mental constitution is undergoing a transformation. I watch my actions
and my words. I scrutinize even my innermost thoughts, to be sure that there is
nothing which is unworthy of you. To be noble and true to you and my best self
have come to be the springs of my being and life. . . . Through you I am
finding my spiritual way back to God's hand, which in the darkness I had almost
lost. But I think it is still waiting for me; and with what I have already had
of your wonderful love &amp; nobleness, I could happily go to the stake, if it
were necessary.</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head>AUSTIN TO MABEL</head>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline><hi rend="italic">[15
July 1884]</hi>
</dateline></opener>
<p>I found yesterday
that I had not learned all of my love for you &#8212; even yet.</p>

         <p>That
there are depths and heights still in our natures, unrevealed, undreamed,
depths profound, and higher, sublimer, beyond any past strength &#8212; I was drawn
to you &#8212; and stirred by you as by no previous experience.</p>

         <p>It seemed to me I could not be separated from
you for a single instant ever &#8212; my whole being craved you, so I could hardly
control the action of my mind. The mighty power of this immutable passion, so
gentle at first, holding us now in bands of steel, never stood before me in
such tremendous proportion.</p>

         <p>What &#8212; what can a human soul contain!</p>

         <p>I don't dare give way for the now. Darling,
Darling, hold tight to me. Love me. Love me.</p>

         <p>I love you so ten thousand times more than my
own life! Why, why can we not be together?</p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
<head type="editorial">The End of Austin's Life</head>
<head>MABEL TO AUSTIN</head>

  <text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
                                                                     

<dateline>10th August 1895
</dateline>                                                                          <dateline>Saturday
morning
</dateline></opener>

         <p>My
darling, my darling, I must write to you, although I am sadly sure there will
be no chance to get it to you until you are enough better to see me, and then I
could tell it all to you. But I will write from day to day, and perhaps hand it
to you myself. I have already tried to get two notes to you. But the first one
was while you were at the sickest, and Vinnie could not get at you. The other
she has carried around for several days, and she professes to have no
opportunity to hand it to you. So I have both here, to give you when you are
better. What I have been through since the day, July 18th, when you were last
out and saw me, no human being can ever know. Even
you, my beloved, my king, can scarcely tell my suffering. For two weeks I could
not eat, my sleep was broken constantly, and sobs choked my throat all day. I
could not go out, or see anybody, and there was no sunshine or blue sky.
</p>

         <p>Then came the terrible day when I heard things that stopped my
breath, and I besieged God with frantic entreaties to save you, or else kill me
too. Then a sudden inspiration of help for you came into my mind, and I went at
once to Boston [to a faith healer] to carry it out. To be sure I cried all the
way there, but about at Wayland the sun shone out suddenly in the west, while
it was raining toward Boston, and a most wonderful rainbow spanned the sky ahead.
It lasted over half an hour &#8212; calm, bright, peaceful, and full of hope. It was
the first time in my life that God ever spoke to me. But He did that time, and
told me you would get well. I went to a friend's house for the night, and the
next morning arranged to have yon helped, and only then did my tears cease; but
a remarkable quiet came over me. For a day or two there was said to be no
special change in you. But on Tuesday, August 6th, Dr. Cooper reported a distinct,
and to him apparently surprising, change for the better, in your pulse and
general condition. So then I knew God meant it, and showed me how to help you.
And you have gained from that time &#8212; and my reason is saved.</p>

         <p>
And I have wondered &#8212; not <hi rend="italic">if</hi>, but what, you are
thinking of me, and if the time seems long to you since you held me in your
arms, and if you would not like to have me come in now and kiss you, and take
your dear hands in mine. I have solemnly promised God that when you are well
again, and I feel your beloved arms around me again, and I know I have you
safe, that from that hour I will live up to the best and highest there is in
me, and make you happy as I never did before. Only God has a faint conception
of how I love you &#8212; nothing human can compass such knowledge &#8212; unless you know.
If you had died it would have been the utter end of my life. I could not think
of any possibility, even of going on with life, much less any occupation. I
know I saved your life those two days when the chances were even, and I will
tell you all about it.</p>

         <p>I
have not heard from you yet this morning. I do not consider Vinnie's
information trustworthy in detail, so I send to the doctor. But yesterday you
saw Mr. Bowles, and had a comfortable day, so I slept better, but even then not
without tossing and turning a good deal. I am not yet past the strain &#8212; and I
cannot eat. I am very thin and white, but so grateful that I can only sob out
my thanks for your life.</p>

         <p>To have lived in
and by and for and through you for so many years, and then to have to face the
bitter possibility that you might have died, is a torment beyond the
imagination of fiends. My hands tremble still, and my heart throbs and jumps.
But you are getting well, oh master dear! . . .
</p>

 <dateline>Monday,
3:30 p.m., 12th August</dateline>

         <p>"For
my beloved &#8212; is mine &#8212; and I am his; </p>

         <p>                         What
&#8212;can &#8212; we &#8212; want &#8212; beside?" NOTHING!</p>

         <p>But
we do want that &#8212; each other. This morning three bunches of sweet peas were
sent you by Mr. Parmenter &#8212; they were taken to you from here, at his request;
and one of your nurses was seen, who said you were better today. <hi rend="italic">
Very

</hi>slowly, but surely, oh, my heart's
beloved, you are getting back, and you will be in life again. How simple for me
to come in to see you, and kiss you and love you into health! And yet China is nearer, in possibility. But my darling, get well and come back to me, and I will
try not to repine at any circumstance. I belong utterly to you.</p>

<dateline>Tuesday morning, 13th
August</dateline>


         <p>Do
you hear the crickets, <hi rend="italic">
our 
</hi>crickets, my beloved,
at twilight?  And when you hear them do you think of me?  I sat on the east
piazza last evening listening to them, and again in front of the house, until
it seemed to me you must be with me. Do you hear them, sweetheart?  All these
fair August days I can hardly breathe without you. <hi rend="italic">
Our 
</hi>month,
and you so ill that you are shut away from me &#8212; but only for the time, dear.
You are coming back, and then I shall tell you how lonesome the lights and
shadows were on the far, dim hills, and how the blue haze choked me, and blinded
my eyes; and how the rich odors of corn and tobacco suffocated me with
recollection and anticipation. The sunshine is hot but beautiful, the insects
are wildly happy in a heaven of sizz and buzz, the warm fragrance of grass
ascends to me from your dear meadow, and I see it and feel it all, yet as a
stranger until you are well again. My darling, my king.</p>

         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">
Wednesday, 14th
August.</hi> Good morning, my dearest love! My heart has been with you all night,
and will be all day. I am going for a little excursion today. I cannot breathe
or work here, so I am going away for the day. I love you. </p>
</body>
</text>
</div>

<div>
       
            <p><hi rend="bold">David and Mabel
then drove to Ashfield for the day, and the next morning departed from Amherst by carriage to attend a centenary celebration in New Salem. They returned to town
the next evening, August 16, just as Austin passed away.</hi></p>
</div>

<div1 type="file references">
            <list><item><xptr n="ls.00064" type="commentary on same history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00034" type="commentary on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00179" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00180" type="image on history"/></item>

                           </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>