<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="lovescenes.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//UNL Libraries::Etext Center//DTD 19thCenturyStudies.dtd (UNL Etext Center)//EN" "19thCenturyStudies.dtd" [

]>
<TEI.2 id="ls.00040">
   <teiHeader>

<fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main"><hi rend="italic">Life and Work of Henry Ward Beecher</hi>

</title>

<title level="j" type="journal"></title>
<title level="c" type="chapter">from Chapters XIX and XX, "The Great Scandal"</title>
<title level="m" type="monograph"></title>
<author name="Knox">Thomas W. Knox</author>
<date type="original" value="1887">1887</date>

            <title level="m" type="sub">electronic edition</title>

            <editor>Laura White</editor>
            <editor>Linda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Research Assistant</resp>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Advisory Committee</resp>
               <name>Stephen Behrendt</name>
               <name>Susan Belasco</name>
               <name>Wendy Katz</name>
               <name>Timothy Mahoney</name>
               <name>Christin Mamiya</name>
               <name>Harriet Turner</name>
               <name>Katherine Walter</name>
               <name>John Wunder</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>ls.00040</idno>
            <distributor>Touchstones: Interdisciplinary Curriculum Modules for Nineteenth-Century Studies</distributor>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
               <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
               <addrLine>etcenter@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright © 2005 by University of Nebraska-Lincoln, all rights reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions
of U.S. copyright law.  Redistribution or republication on other terms, in
any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and advance
notification of the publisher, the Center for Digital Research in the Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="project">
Transcribed from pages 400-435 of the original 1887 publication of Thomas W. Knox's <hi rend="italic">Life and Work of Henry Ward Beecher</hi>.

</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

<bibl>
               <title level="a">Chapters XIX and XX, "The Great Scandal"</title>
               <title level="m"><hi rend="italic">Life and Work of Henry Ward Beecher</hi></title>
               <author>Thomas W. Knox</author>
               <imprint>
                  <publisher>
The Hartford Publishing Company

</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
Hartford, Connecticut

</pubPlace>
               </imprint>
               <date>
1887

</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>

<keywords>
               <term id="seduction" type="theme">seduction</term>
               <term id="adultery" type="theme">adultery</term>
			<term id="popularpress" type="theme">popular press</term>
			<term id="history" type="media">history</term>
			<term id="american" type="place">American</term>
			<term id="parlor" type="setting">parlor</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-07-15">15 July 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit item</item>
         </change>
	<change>
            <date value="2005-06-23">23 June 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura White</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>edit headers</item>
         </change>
<change>
            <date value="2005-03-09">09 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Second Round Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-03-07">07 March 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Michael Page</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Preliminary Encoding Edit</item>
         </change>

<change>
            <date value="2005-02-08">08 February 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Brian L. Pytlik Zillig</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>XSLT batch conversion of Microsoft Word files to TEI files</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date value="2005-01-12">12 January 2005</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Andrew Jewell</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Creation of model encoding</item>
         </change>
      <change>
<date value="2005-05-23">23 July 2005</date>
<respStmt><name>Zach Bajaber</name></respStmt>
<item>Changed Terms to new format.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
	<div>	

<head>Chapter XIX:  The Great Scandal</head>

<p>In
1851, a bright young stenographer, only sixteen years of age, Theodore Tilton
by name, came into Plymouth Church to take down Mr. Beecher's sermons for
publication, a practice which was then a novelty. He was engaged by Henry C.
Bowen, one of the founders of the church, upon <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi> of which
journal Mr. Bowen was a proprietor, and in 1861 he succeeded Mr. Beecher as
editor-in-chief of the paper.  He developed considerable power as a writer and
speaker, especially in the anti-slavery contest, and gained the warm friendship
of Mr. Beecher, who regarded him as "one of my boys." Towards 1870
some difference arose between Mr. Bowen, then sole proprietor of <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi>,
and Mr. Beecher. Meanwhile Mr. Tilton's domestic life was not a happy one. In
December, 1870, Mrs. Tilton left her husband's house and sought her mother's
protection. Mr. Beecher was consulted, and finally counselled a separation,
and the rupture between Tilton and Mr. Beecher was complete. Mr. Tilton
obtained possession of his infant child in its mother's absence, and then the
mother returned to him. At this time Mr. Tilton had retired from the editorship
of <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi>, to which, however, he still continued to contribute,
and was editor-in-chief of the <hi rend="italic">Brooklyn Union</hi>, of which Mr. Bowen was
one of the proprietors. To Mr. Bowen came stories prejudicial to Tilton's moral
character, and he meditated dismissing him.</p>


<p>An interview was held on December 26, 1870, in
the course of which the conversation passed from the immediate topic to the
necessity of frequent notices of Plymouth Church and its pastor in the <hi rend="italic">Brooklyn
Union</hi>. Tilton objected, and charged Mr. Beecher with "dishonorable
conduct toward his wife." Bringing pen and paper, Mr. Bowen invited Tilton
to write a letter demanding that Mr. Beecher resign from Plymouth Church and leave <hi rend="italic">The Christian Union</hi>. Tilton did so. Mr. Bowen took the letter to Mr.
Beecher, who read it and said: "This is sheer insanity; this man is
crazy." Soon afterward Tilton was dismissed from both the positions
which he held. It was now necessary for him to submit evidence against Mr.
Beecher or to confess himself a slanderer. He sought this from his wife. As
to what the precise confession then obtained from her was the testimony
conflicted. The letter was two years afterward destroyed. The progress of
events was not rapid. Mrs. Tilton retracted in Mr. Beecher's presence every
accusation made against him; Francis D. Moulton appeared as the "mutual
friend;" Mr. Beecher made a tumultuous expression of grief and shame, of
which Mr. Moulton took down a statement; Mr. Tilton and Mr. Beecher met, and a
reconciliation was effected. A new paper called <hi rend="italic">The Golden Age,</hi> was
started, with Tilton at its head, for which purpose Mr. Beecher and friends of
Mr. Moulton contributed sums of money.</p>


<p>On April 2, 1872 the "tripartite covenant"
between Beecher, Bowen, and Tilton was signed, promising silence as to the past
and goodwill for the future. But ugly rumors began to be heard. Tilton aided
their distribution, Mr. Beecher's friends became uneasy, and in 1873 he broke
silence with a card of denial. Tilton was charged in the church with being a
slanderer of his pastor, and his name was stricken from the rolls. But more was
demanded.  An ecclesiastical council was called, nominally in regard to the
irregularity of this proceeding, really to make some attempt at an
investigation. Its work amounted to nothing, except to deepen the uneasy
feeling that some great scandal was about to be brought to light. Then Tilton,
to clear himself, published the Bacon letter, the first of the statements
preceding the trial, in which he quoted from Mr. Beecher's alleged confession
of January 1, 1871. Mr. Beecher at once took action and demanded an
investigation, which six well-known members of Ply mouth Church were appointed
to conduct. Another effort to compromise the matter was made in vain, and at
last, in August, 1874, four years and more after the wrong was charged to have
been committed, Tilton brought his suit, placing his damages at $100,000. The
charge of adultery was first publicly preferred in July, 1874, and the
complaint served in August, when issue was immediately joined. The trial was
begun in January, 1875. Subjects were dealt with extending over five or six
years. About two hundred and fifty documents were introduced and analyzed. More
than one hundred different interviews were examined into, and in respect to
many of them the sworn testimony of witnesses was in irreconcilable disagreement.  Printed
in small type, the testimony that was published filled three thousand foolscap
pages, and the report of the proceedings would fill four or five large legal
volumes. Over one hundred and fifty distinct rulings on points of law were
made by the judge, which were noted by the defendant's counsel, and nearly as
many questions were raised and decided during the defendant's presentation of
his case.</p>


<p>Judge Neilson sat upon the bench. The most
eminent counsel were employed on either side. For Tilton appeared Mr. Pryor, a
man of wide learning and active mind, Mr. Fullerton, a master of the art of
cross-questioning, and Mr. Beach, a sharp, pithy, and forcible speaker.</p>


<p>Mr. Beecher was represented by Mr. Evarts, who
gained new laurels as an advocate before a jury; Austin Abbott, distinguished
for his legal learning and the publications bearing his name, whose foresight
and system were apparent in the presentation of the defendant's case; Mr.
Porter, quick to see and decide upon knotty points; and Mr. Tracy, an effective
orator. The positions of the persons interested, the differing characteristics
of the multitudinous witnesses, the crowds of prominent men from all parts of
the country who packed the courtroom daily, and the wholesale publicity given
by the press, all conspired to make this trial a striking and unprecedented
event. From January until June the lawyers struggled, and a curious public
gloated over the daily details of the great scandal. Then came the summing up
on each side and the judge's charge.  The deliberations of the jury continued
for eight days. Fifty-two ballots were taken, the first and last being nine
for Mr. Beecher and three for Tilton. On one ballot the jury stood eleven to
one, and on another seven to five, in favor of Mr. Beecher. </p>


<p>After the close of this trial the matter was
taken up by the Grand jury, which called Mr. Beecher as a witness and found an
indictment against Francis D. Moulton for libel. The District Attorney,
however, never brought the case to trial, and after he had officially indicated
this decision by entering a <hi rend="italic">nolle prosequi</hi>, Moulton brought a suit
against Mr. Beecher for malicious prosecution. Mr. Beecher's counsel
defended him vigorously, and Moulton abandoned his suit. Questions then arose
respecting the regularity of the proceedings in Plymouth Church by which Mr.
Beecher had been acquitted, and a council of Congregational churches and
ministers, said to be the largest that ever assembled, was called to advise with
Plymouth Church respecting its proceedings. This council did not undertake a
direct examination of the charges. It simply examined into the history of the
action of Plymouth Church, and in this inquiry spent nearly a week. The result
was that Christian fellowship was extended to Mr. Beecher, the confidence of
the council in his integrity was affirmed, and a tribunal of eminent jurists
was appointed to investigate any charges that might be laid before them, though
none were ever laid.</p>

<p>To many who hated Mr. Beecher for political or
theological reasons, "the great scandal" was an opportunity to
despise him for which they were not ungrateful. But many who loved him and
honored him were obliged to feel that the evidence of his own hand convicted
him of a shameful fault. Guilty or innocent, his was a fearful trial, and
nothing in his life became him like his bearing of it. It was terrible to meet
him then upon the street, he seemed so bowed and broken; his once cheerful face
was so worn and weary with the sorrow of his heart. It is a patent fact that
never after that did he have the weight, the influence, the authority in
political or religious matters that he had before. It is equally patent that
the afterthought of many whose judgment was at first adverse to him grew less
and less so as the years went on. And it is certain that few who are not
willing to think evil of him for the basest reasons would now hesitate to say
that whatever may have been his fault, it is still true that in the general
sweep and tenor of his life he was a man devoted to all excellent and useful
ideas. It is equally certain that there are many others, and a much greater
number, who have not and who never had a doubt of his complete and perfect
innocence. And furthermore, a very great majority of those who personally knew
him believed in his innocence, while comparatively few of those who supported
the accusation were acquainted with Mr. Beecher or had ever exchanged a word
with him.</p>

<p>[The following account of the trial has been carefully
and impartially abridged from the official report.]</p>

<p>The answer to Mr. Tilton's complaint was a
general and unqualified denial, and was made August 29, 1874. On the 17th of
the following October judge Neilson, Chief justice of the City Court of Brooklyn,
granted an order requiring the plaintiff to deliver to the defendant's
attorneys a statement in writing of the particular times and places at which he
expected or intended to prove that any acts of adultery or criminal intercourse
had taken place between the defendant and the wife of the plaintiff, and of the
particular times and places at which he expected or intended to prove that the
defendant confessed any such act of adultery, or show cause why such bill of
particulars should not be delivered, and why the plaintiff should not be
precluded from giving evidence on the trial of any such acts or confessions not
specified in such bill of particulars. In the affidavit accompanying the order
attention was called to an alleged confession of Mr. Beecher and Mrs. Tilton,
and it was emphatically denied that any such confession had ever been made.</p>

<p>The motion for a bill of particulars was argued
at a special term of the City Court of Brooklyn, October 30, 1874, before Chief
justice Neilson, and was denied without costs. The defendant's attorneys
appealed from the order of Judge Neilson to the General Term of the City Court,
and the appeal was heard by Judges Reynolds and McCue. The order denying the
bill of particulars was affirmed, without costs, Judge Reynolds writing the
opinion. A dissenting opinion was written by Judge McCue.</p>

<p>From the decision of the General Term an appeal
was taken to the Court of Appeals, and the decision of the General Term of the
City Court was reversed. The counsel for the defendant then renewed their
application for a bill of particulars before Judge McCue, at a Special Term of
the City Court, December 10, 1874, and the application was granted. From this
decision the plaintiff appealed to the General Term, and the appeal having been
heard before Judges Neilson and Reynolds, an order was entered on December
29th, reversing Judge McCue's order. The order for a bill of particulars having
been finally refused, the suit went to trial upon Mr. Tilton's original
complaint, made on August 21, 1874.</p>

<p>The cause was called on Monday, January 4, 1875,
by Judge McCue, in the Brooklyn City Court, Part I. Mr. Beecher and his counsel
were present, but as the case was called two hours before the time understood
by the plaintiff's counsel, Mr. Tilton was not represented, except by Mr.
Pearsall, whose attendance was accidental. He answered to the call, but
insisted on an adjournment till the next day. Judge McCue, by right of
assignment, should have held the term, but there had been an implied understanding
that the case should be sent to Judge Neilson. In the preliminary contests in
which Judge McCue had granted a bill of particulars, and Judge Neilson had
denied it, the opinion of both judges as to the nature of the evidence to be
admitted on this particular case was foreshadowed. Naturally, Mr. Beecher's
counsel were anxious that the case should be tried before Judge McCue, while
the plaintiff preferred Judge Neilson. It was thought on this first day that
Judge McCue would preside, but in accordance with Mr. Pearsall's desire the
case was adjourned till 11 a.m. next day, and the matter left undecided. On
Tuesday, January 5th, after hearing the arguments of the counsel on both sides,
and after consulting with his associates, Judge McCue decided to send the case
to the other part of the Court, presided over by Judge Neilson. By Friday,
January 8th, the impanelling of the jury was completed.</p>

<p>The trial may be said to have really commenced
on Monday, January 11th, with the address of ex-Judge Morris. The main points
touched on in this address were the alleged confessions of Mr. Beecher and Mrs.
Tilton to Mr. Tilton, Mrs. Moulton, and others; the correspondence of Mr. Beecher;
the letters of Mrs. Tilton and Mrs. Morse; the alleged clandestine correspondence
between Mr. Beecher and Mrs. Tilton; and the circumstantial evidence in the
efforts which Mr. Beecher made for concealment.</p>

<p>Every seat in the court was occupied, admission
being allowed by ticket only. All eyes turned to the door-way as Mr. Beecher,
accompanied by Mrs. Beecher, entered the court-room.</p>

<p>The opening address was closed on the morning of
January 13th, and two witnesses were called to the stand &#8212;Augustus Maverick and
Francis D. Moulton. The former gave unimportant testimony in relation to Mr.
Tilton's marriage. Mr. Moulton's testimony related to the first meeting between
Mr. Tilton and Mr. Beecher at his house, the circumstances under which the
apology was written, and the subsequent interview between himself and Mr.
Beecher on the subject of Mrs. Tilton's retraction. He identified the various
documents, letters, etc., that had become part and parcel of the case, including
Mr. Tilton's demand that Mr. Beecher should leave the ministry, Mrs. Morse's
letter to Mr. Beecher and his reply, sundry letters from Mr. Beecher to Mr.
Moulton, Mrs. Tilton, and what were termed the <hi rend="italic">clandestine letters</hi>; also Mr.
Beecher's letter to Mr. Moulton, in which Mr. Tilton's character was analyzed.
At one point in his testimony the witness stated that Mr. Tilton threatened to
shoot Mr. Beecher if the resignation of the pastorate should be published,
because it would disgrace the Livingston Street household. The letter of Mrs.
Victoria C. Woodhull to the <hi rend="italic">World</hi>, May 22, 1871, was put in as evidence, and
Mr. Beecher's cards challenging Mrs. Woodhull or anyone else who had letters
of his to publish them; also the West specifications against Mr. Tilton, and
the tripartite agreement between Mr. Beecher, Mr. Tilton, and Henry C. Bowen. The
scenes in the Plymouth controversy were reviewed, and the effect of the
publication of the Bacon letter. It was the object of the plaintiff's counsel
to present the witness to the jury in the light of Mr. Beecher's friend;
whereas, the defence, in the cross-examination, introduced him as the school-mate
and life-long friend of Mr. Tilton. His cross-examination related to his
acquaintance with Mrs. Woodhull, his accounts with Mr. Beecher, his stock in
<hi rend="italic">The Golden Age</hi>, and other matters.</p> 

<p>Mrs. Martha A. Bradshaw, William F. West,
and Franklin Woodruff gave evidence, and then Mr. Tilton was called. The
defence at once objected, on the ground that a husband was incompetent to prove
his wife's dishonor. The senior counsel, Mr. Evarts, made the appeal, citing
authorities and examples in proof of the claim set up. General Roger A. Pryor,
of counsel for the plaintiff, answered the argument of Mr. Evarts, and was
followed by Mr. Beach, Mr. Tilton's senior counsel, in further proof of the
competency of his client to testify. Mr. Evarts replied, and Judge Neilson
decided that the plaintiff was a competent witness, but that he could not
testify to confidential communications.</p>


<p>Thereupon, on the morning of the sixteenth day
of the proceedings, Mr. Tilton was sworn, and proceeded to give his evidence.</p>

<p>He told the story of his early career, and
related the story of the memorable interviews between himself and Mr. Beecher
on December 30, 1870, and subsequently. The contents of the letter of
confession offered from memory by the witness were ruled out. He swore
that instead of being a bankrupt in 1871 he owned property valued at $30,000. He
said that on the evening in December, 1870, when Mr. Moulton had brought Mr.
Beecher to his house, he and Mr. Beecher had a private interview. He had then
told Mr. Beecher that he might consider the letter he had written demanding the
former's retirement from the pulpit as unwritten, and that the interview was
held in the confidence of his wife and in her behalf. Mr. Beecher had said
that Mr. Moulton had shown him no statement, but that he understood in general
terms the object of the interview, and he expressed his thanks for the
withdrawal of the letter. He had then informed Mr. Beecher that Mr. Bowen had
made a statement that "You have been guilty of adulteries with numerous
members of your congregation ever since your Indianapolis pastorate, all down
through these twenty-five years; that you are not a safe man to dwell in a
Christian community; that he knows numerous cases where you have shipwrecked
the happiness of Christian homes; that he is determined you shall no longer
edit <hi rend="italic">The Christian Union</hi>; that you shall no longer speak in Plymouth Church;
and he says distinctly that you are a wolf in the fold and that you should be
extirpated."</p>

<p>Mr. Beecher was amazed that Mr. Bowen should
have so spoken, as he had appeared to be friendly. Witness informed Mr.
Beecher that after his interview with Mr. Bowen he had narrated the substance
of the interview to his wife, who was ill, and the intelligence had filled her
with profound distress, and she had instantly said that he was violating the
promise he had made her&#8212;that he would never do Mr. Beecher any harm or ever
assist in any exposure of his secret to the public. She had said that if Mr.
Bowen made war upon Mr. Beecher, and if he (witness) joined in it, everybody
sooner or later would know the reason, and that would be to her shame and the
children's, and she could not endure it. Mr. Beecher had asked him what he
meant by speaking of his wife in that way, and he had then read him a copy of
Mrs. Tilton's confession, the original of which was in Mr. Moulton's
possession. That confession had been destroyed after the tripartite agreement
had been signed.</p>

<p>The next interview he had had with Mr. Beecher
was about January 3, 1871, at Mr. Moulton's house. He had not then wished to
speak to Mr. Beecher, who had ruined his wife and broken up his home, but at
Mr. Moulton's request he said "Good-morning" to him. Mr. Beecher
said that he did not marvel that witness did not feel like speaking to him, but
that he felt more dread in being spoken to than he could possibly feel
repugnance in speaking, and that he hoped witness had found it in his heart to
accept the communication which he had made through Mr. Moulton&#8212;that he had
dictated it out of heart-break and anguish.</p>

<p>The next interview with Mr. Beecher was in February,
1872, when Mr. Beecher had called at his house, and, in reply to his query, had
positively assured him that there was no dishonor attaching to the birth of the
boy Ralph. Mrs. Tilton had come into the room at that time, and bursting into
tears, had corroborated Mr. Beecher.</p>
  
<p>The witness described at length his relations
with Mrs. Woodhull, and stated that Mrs. Woodhull's biography had been written
by her husband, and that she had brought it to him and asked him to rewrite it.
He had done so, leaving out many extravagant statements, and she had been
dissatisfied. In June, 1873, there was a stormy interview between himself and
Mr. Moulton, after he had learned that Mr. Beecher had expressed an intention
to resign from Plymouth Church. Witness was very angry, and told Mr. Moulton
that if Mr. Beecher resigned at that time, thus reflecting on the children of
witness, he would shoot him. The charges of Mr. West against Mr. Tilton, as a
member of Plymouth Church, for slandering the pastor, were very fully reviewed,
and in connection therewith, a letter written by witness to Samuel E. Beecher,
as member of the Examining Committee, just before the meeting of the Church was
held at which Mr. Tilton's name was dropped from the rolls, was introduced and
read. In that letter, witness wrote that he had not accused Mr. Beecher
falsely. In relation to the Bacon letter, he had met and told Mr. Beecher that
Dr. Bacon had called him (Mr. Tilton) a knave, and a liar, and a creature of
Mr. Beecher's magnanimity, and had added that Mr. Beecher must deny Dr. Bacon's
statements or he (witness) would. Mr. Beecher had walked away without replying,
and they had not met since. In regard to any improper conduct on his part with
the young girl Bessie Turner, or Lizzie McDermott, the witness stated
emphatically that there was "not a word of truth in it, nor a fact for its
foundation."</p>

<p>Mr. Evarts took up the cross-examination of the
witness, and questioned him closely on the subject of his religious views, and
whether his change in belief had caused his wife much sorrow, and whether there
was also a great difference in the religious views of witness and Mr. Beecher.
The political controversies between the two men were next taken up, and the
events following the Cleveland Convention, when witness had severely attacked
Mr. Beecher, were reviewed. An entire day was occupied in reading the
correspondence of Mr. and Mrs. Tilton. The relations between Mr. Bowen and Mr.
Tilton were thoroughly sifted, and a searching inquiry was made into the
so-called confession of Mrs. Tilton, and the copy of it made by Mr. Tilton,
both of which, the witness said, were destroyed &#8212; the first by his wife, the
copy by himself. The witness was also minutely cross-examined as to
the subject-matter of the "True Story" written by him in the latter
part of 1872, subsequent to the publication of Mrs. Woodhull's story.</p>

<p>On his redirect examination, Mr. Tilton was
examined as to his religious views &#8212; his early belief, the cause, time, and
nature of the change in them; and finally on the question as to how he
reconciled the statement that his wife loved everything good and hated
everything bad with the fact that she was charged with adultery, he replied
that he had known his wife since she was ten years old, had married her at
twenty, and during fifteen years of married life he had held her in reverence
almost to the point of making her an idol; when she fell, it was the necessity
of his own heart to find some excuse for her, and that excuse he had found in
the fact that she had been wrapped up in her religious teacher and guide, and
had surrendered her convictions to him; she followed his lead trustingly, and
would go after him like one blinded. He thought she had sinned as one in a
trance, and she was not a free agent, and she would have done her teacher's
bidding if, like the heathen priest in the Hindoo land, he had bade her fling
her child into the Ganges or cast herself under the juggernaut. That was his
excuse for his wife. The examination of Mr. Tilton ended with the
twenty-eighth day of the proceedings.</p>

<p>Mrs. Catherine Carey, who had been nurse in Mr.
Tilton's family in 1869, was called, and gave evidence relative to the conduct
of Mr. Beecher with Mrs. Tilton.</p>

<p>Mr. George A. Bell, a member of Plymouth Church, gave evidence regarding the interview between himself, Mr. Halliday, and
Mr. Tilton.</p>

<p>Mr. Evarts made an eloquent appeal for the
admittance of testimony showing that Mr. Beecher had been called to advise in
the troubles between Mr. and Mrs. Tilton, but he was ruled out.</p>

<p>Mr. Joseph H. Richards (Mrs. Tilton's brother),
Mr. Jeremiah P. Robinson, Mr. William M. Marston, and Mrs. Francis D. Moulton
gave evidence, and on the thirty-first day of the proceedings the plaintiff's
counsel rested their case.</p>
	</div>
<div>
	
<head>Chapter XX:  The Great Scandal&#8212;Continued</head>

<p>On
Wednesday, February 24, 1875, Mr. Tracy made the opening address for the
defence. He began by tracing Mr. Beecher's life and labors from the pastorate
in the West to the culmination of his popularity in Brooklyn. Then he took up
the career of Theodore Tilton, speaking of him as one who had fallen from an
eminence seldom attained by men of his age to the very bottom of an abyss. With
stinging emphasis he referred to the plaintiff as one who, "if he could
realize the sad truth that he was morally dead, would still rejoice in this
post-mortem investigation of his character. But we propose," he added, 
"to dissect him first in the interest of truth and bury him afterward in the
interest of decency."</p>

<p>The evidence of the plaintiff was minutely
reviewed, and referring to Mrs. Tilton, who, he said, was the true defendant in
the case, the speaker drew a touching picture of her affection for her husband,
"giving her whole life to him without murmur as to her own
self-sacrifice." Mr. Tilton's views on marriage and divorce were commented
on, and it was argued that while the plaintiff was the editor of a religious
newspaper he was an advocate of free lust. The alleged trouble in Mr. Tilton's
family, on account of which Mr. Beecher was said to have advised separation,
was discussed; the plaintiff and Mr. Moulton were accused of conspiracy and
perjury; Catherine Carey-Smith was said to be a woman of bad character; and
Joseph H. Richards' testimony was criticised.</p>

<p>Referring to the so-called letter of confession
of Mrs. Tilton, Mr. Tracy remarked on its non-production, and stated that the
defence would produce an unimpeachable witness to prove that Mr. Tilton, after
the Woodhull publication, had read to the witness what he said was a copy of
the alleged confession of Mrs. Tilton, and that that copy did not contain a
charge of adultery; also that Mr. Tilton told the witness that the original
confession was in the hands of Francis D. Moulton, and this not-withstanding
Mr. Tilton and Mr. Moulton had sworn that the confession had been destroyed at
the time of the signing of the tripartite agreement some months before. Mr.
Tilton was stigmatized as a blackmailer, and Mr. Tracy concluded his address on
the thirty-fifth day of the proceedings with a long and affecting tribute to
the Plymouth pastor, and a promise to the jury of evidence that would prove him
guiltless.</p>

<p>Edward J. Ovington, the first witness for the
defence, testified that the plaintiff had told him that his wife would say
anything for her husband. Rufus E. Holmes testified to improprieties of the
plaintiff at Winsted, Conn. Mrs. Ovington related conversations she had had
with the Tiltons, and stated that Mrs. Tilton had denied to her that Mr. Beecher had offered her any impropriety. Mrs. Sarah C. D. Putnam gave evidence of the
devotion of Mrs. Tilton to her husband, and Mr. Tilton's strictures on the
church, and his waning faith in Mr. Beecher's powers. Samuel E. Beecher and Mr.
McKelway testified to the statements made by Mr. Tilton concerning the charge
against Mr. Beecher. Then followed testimony concerning the plaintiff's
relations with Mrs. Woodhull, one witness testifying that the Woodhull scandal
had been discussed in Mr. Tilton's presence before its publication.</p>

<p>The tripartite covenant was explained by Samuel
Wilkinson; Mr. Moulton's evidence was contradicted in many instances by Mr.
Archibald Baxter, who stated that in various conversations between them Mr.
Moulton had declared Mr. Beecher to be innocent. Reuben W. Ropes, Abner H.
Davis, Edward A. Biden, William B. Barber, and Charles H. Caldwell swore to Mr.
Moulton's denial of the Woodhull story about Mr. Beecher and Mrs. Tilton.
Several witnesses testified to Mr. Tilton's opinions on marriage and divorce,
and Mr. Halliday stated that in 1873 Mr. Tilton had said to him, "My case
against Mr. Beecher is wholly irrespective of my wife."  Witnesses
were examined in the Plymouth Church Records, and then Miss Bessie Turner was called,
and testified to Mr. Tilton's eccentricities and "moods," his
unkindness to his wife, and his attempts on herself. Three colored servants of
Mrs. Woodhull gave evidence of Mr. Tilton's personal relations with that lady
in support of Mr. Tracy's declaration, in the opening address, that the defence
would show conspiracy between them to publish the scandal. Evidence was given
of Mr. Tilton's determination to "smash" his wife and Mr. Beecher;
also further evidence in reference to the tripartite agreement, including the
evidence of Charles Storrs and James Freeland. Several witnesses testified
generally on the case; Mr. and Mrs. Robert T. Moore impeached Mrs. Carey; and
James Redpath related the manner in which he had obtained the "True
Story."</p>

<p>On the fifty-sixth day of the proceedings, April
1, 1875, Henry Ward Beecher was called and took the oath in the New England form &#8212; "I swear by the ever-living God." He gave an abridged history
of his early life and struggles, his subsequent religious and political
services, his domestic relations, and his intimacy with Mr. Bowen, Mr. Tilton,
and Mr. Moulton, taking in the period from the time of his birth down to
December, 1870, when, according to the theory of the defence, the conspiracy
began. The growth of Plymouth Church from embyro to its then
magnitude, with between twenty-five hundred and three thousand communicants;
the building up of <hi rend="italic">The Independent</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Christian Union</hi> (the
latter from a circulation of six hundred to thirty thousand copies in a single
year); the rapid production of thirty-five volumes&#8212;all these labors were
merely mentioned as ordinary events. The great help which his wife had given
him during all the years of their married life was, however, more fully dwelt
on and emphasized.</p>

<p>An account of his first acquaintance with Mrs.
Tilton was given. He had known of her when she was a girl, but had had no
personal acquaintance with her until her marriage to Mr. Tilton, when he had
called on her, at her husband's request. He stated that in December,
1870, he had advised Mrs. Tilton to separate from her husband on account of the
great unhappiness in the family and her treatment by her husband. He
denied in the most positive and emphatic terms the commission by him of any
offence against Mr. Tilton or of any crime against his wife. Briefly and
emphatically he denied the statements of the nurse, Mrs. Carey; he did not
remember ever having seen Mr. Richards while on a visit to Mr. Tilton's house;
and he denied the truth of Mr. Tilton's allegations concerning his acts on
October 10 and 17, 1868. During his entire acquaintance with Mrs. Tilton, there
had never been any undue personal familiarity between that lady and himself,
nor had he at any time, directly or indirectly, solicited improper favors from
her.</p>


<p>The scene with Mr. Bowen on December 26, 1870,
was rehearsed, and the witness stated that Mr. Bowen, in delivering Mr.
Tilton's letter requiring Mr. Beecher's resignation, had taken pains to
represent that he was a voluntary messenger and ignorant of the contents of the
letter. On reading that letter, Mr. Bowen had been as indignant as he was
himself, and a conversation had followed, in which it was revealed that both
gentlemen had heard of many matters discreditable to Mr. Tilton, and witness
had emphatically declared to Mr. Bowen that the retention of Mr. Tilton on <hi rend="italic">The
Independent</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Union</hi> could not but be injurious to both journals.
This, witness stated, was the first and only offence committed against Mr.
Tilton, and the injury to him professionally which followed in his discharge by
Mr. Bowen a few days later was the only injury the plaintiff had received,
although witness was led at the time of the signing the apology to imagine that
there were other grounds of complaint.</p>


<p>On the night of December 30, 1870, accompanied
by Mr. Moulton, witness had called on Mr. Tilton, who had then withdrawn the
letters he had written, and recited to witness his troubles with Mr. Bowen; he
had then charged witness with abetting in his removal by Mr. Bowen, with having
superseded him in his family, with alienating the affections of his wife, with
corrupting his wife and teaching her deceitfulness, and finally, with having
solicited her to immoral relations. After an objection by the plaintiff, the
whole conversation with Mrs. Tilton was admitted, and the witness described
with great minuteness how Mrs. Tilton, after hearing Mr. Beecher's story of
what her husband had told him, had declared that "she could not help it;"
that "she had been worried out with his importunities;" and
that the charge was "not true."</p>


<p>At his suggestion, but not at his dictation, she
had then taken a pen and written the letter of retraction, and had of her own
volition added the postscript, which specifically denied the charge of "
improper solicitation." On December 31st, in an interview at witness'
house, Mr. Moulton reproached him with having taken an unfair advantage in
getting a retraction from Mrs. Tilton, and he read a letter from her asking
that both her confession to her husband and her letter of retraction should be
returned, in order that she might destroy them. Mr. Moulton assured witness
that there would be no further trouble, and on his representations the letter
was given up.</p>

<p>In narrating the story of the interview between
himself and Mr. Moulton on January 1st, Mr. Beecher described the grief which
had overwhelmed him at that time as coming from three sources: his sorrow at
having spoken evil of Mr. Tilton, his remorse at having believed the scandalous
stories against his friend, and his self-reproach when Mr. Moulton had assured
him that they were false; and lastly, his mortification and sorrow on coming to
the conclusion, to which Mr. Moulton's declarations urged him, that through his
want of foresight and prudence he had won the affection of Mrs. Tilton and come
between her and her husband. Mr. Moulton had suggested that if Mr. Tilton could
hear him talking in the strain he had been talking that evening there would be
peace once more between them, and he asked permission of witness to make a
memorandum of what he had said, so that he might read it to Mr. Tilton.</p>

<p>Mr. Moulton had then written some sentences on
separate slips of paper, and asked witness to sign what he had written, but he
refused. Mr. Moulton had then urged him to put his name, so as to let Mr.
Tilton know that it really came from him, and without reading or knowing what
was on the paper, he had written near the bottom of the sheet, "I have
intrusted this to Frank Moulton in confidence," and had written his name
to that separate note. He denied emphatically that anything in the so-called
letter of contrition was his, beyond that foot-note, and that anything he had
said resembled or warranted the expressions therein contained. Contradictions
were given to the evidence of Mr. Tilton and Mr. Moulton on important
particulars, and it was indignantly and emphatically denied that reference had
ever been made by Mr. Tilton to the offence then charged. In reference to the
plaintiff's testimony relating to the interview about the child Ralph, the
witness said that it was a monstrous and absolute falsehood that there had been
any such conversation, or anything out of which such a conversation could be
made or imagined.</p>

<p>The witness then proceeded with an explanation
of sundry letters and interviews, Mr. Moulton's first suggestions about money
to help out Mr. Tilton, witness' acquaintance with Mrs. Woodhull, and her
attempt to blackmail him previous to the publication of the Wood-hull scandal.
He further stated that until July, 1874, he had been ignorant that adultery had
been ever referred to or charged, and reference was made to attempts on the
part of Mr. Moulton and General Butler to control the Investigating Committee.
In his cross-examination, when asked whether he anticipated sudden death in
1873, the witness said that his fears of death were consequent upon periods of
depression. Counsel for the plaintiff put in an application for a policy of
insurance on the life of Mr. Beecher in March, 1874.</p>

<p>The re-direct examination followed, and on the
sixty-ninth day of the proceedings, April 21, 1875, Mr. Beecher's testimony was
concluded.</p>

<p>Henry M. Cleveland stated that his business
connection with <hi rend="italic">The Christian Union</hi> and Mr. Beecher had ceased after
January 1, 1874, and he swore that on June 2, 1873, between eleven and twelve
o'clock in the morning, he had had an interview with Mr. Beecher at <hi rend="italic">The Christian Union</hi> office in New York, and Mr. Beecher had then directed him
to address letters to him in care of Bigelow &amp; Kennard in Boston. He did
not see Mr. Beecher again until the Friday evening of the following week. The
Rev. W. H. H. Murray, of Boston, preached in Plymouth Church on the Sunday
following June 2d, and Mr. Beecher was not present. The tendency of
this evidence was to directly contradict the alleged interview between Mrs.
Moulton and Mr. Beecher on June 2, 1873.</p>

<p>Mr. Moulton was recalled by the defence for
cross-examination, and was succeeded by Mr. Partridge, the former cashier of Woodruff
&amp; Robinson, who contradicted the evidence of the previous witness. General
Tracy, of counsel for the defence, testified in contradiction of statements of
Mr. Tilton and Mr. Moulton.</p>

<p>On the seventy-seventh day of the proceedings, a stir was created by Mrs. Tilton
standing up in court and desiring that a communication from her should be
read. She handed the following letter to Judge Neilson:</p>

<text type="correspondence">
<body>
<opener>
<dateline>MAY 3, 1875.</dateline>
</opener>

<p>"JUDGE NEILSON : I ask the privilege from
you for a few words in my own behalf. I feel very deeply the in-justice of my
position in the law and before the court now sitting; and while I have
understood and respected from the beginning Mr. Evarts' principle in the
matter, yet since your last session I have been so sensible of the power of my
enemies, that my soul cries out before you, and the gentlemen of the jury, that
they beware how, by a divided verdict, they consign to my children a false and
irrevocable stain upon their mother! For five years past I have been
the victim of circumstances most cruel and unfortunate; struggling from time to
time only for a place to live honorably and truthfully. Released for some
months from the <hi rend="italic">will</hi> by whose power unconsciously I criminated myself again and
again, I declare solemnly before you, without fear of man and by faith in God,
that I am innocent of the crimes charged against me. I would like to tell my
<hi rend="italic">whole</hi> sad story <hi rend="italic">truthfully</hi> &#8212;to acknowledge the frequent falsehoods wrung from
me by compulsion&#8212;though at the same time unwilling to reveal the secrets of my
married life, which only the vital importance of my position makes necessary.
I assume the entire responsibility of this request, unknown to friend or
counsel of either side, and await your Honor's honorable decision. With great
respect,</p>

<closer>"ELIZABETH R.
TILTON."</closer>
</body>
</text>

<p>Judge Neilson considered the letter, and sent
the lady a written reply in which he pointed out the impossibility of her
request being granted. Mr. Henry C. Bowen was called, and gave evidence in
rebuttal of Mr. Beecher's testimony. The plaintiff was recalled, and gave
evidence in rebuttal generally of the testimony on the side of the defence, and
the eighty-fifth day of the proceedings saw the termination of the taking of
the testimony.</p>

<p>On May 19, 1875, judge Porter began the summing
up for the defence. With emphatic denunciations of Mr. Tilton, the learned
counsel condemned in strong language Mr. Moulton and other witnesses, and
cleverly contrasted the life and character of the plaintiff and defendant. Miss
Turner's character was extolled, the scenes between herself and plaintiff were
reviewed, and her testimony favorably compared with the statements of Mr.
Tilton's witnesses. The correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Tilton was
carefully gone over, and Henry C. Bowen's evidence was analyzed in view of
showing points of agreement between that evidence and Mr. Beecher's. Referring
again to Mr. Tilton and Mr. Moulton, Mr. Tilton was declared to be the master
and Mr. Moulton the minion. The letter of contrition was analyzed, and modes
of expression therein declared to be unlike those of Mr. Beecher, and several
famous phrases were ascribed to the pen of Mr. Tilton. Mrs. Moulton was
declared to have sworn falsely on account of her husband.</p> 

<p>Six days were occupied in the summing up, the
evidence of every witness being carefully dissected and commented on, the
learned counsel concluding with a tribute to Judge Neilson, and the belief
expressed to the jury that the verdict would be one which would gladden the
hearts of many, and which would illuminate Brooklyn Heights; a verdict which
would send an electric thrill of joy through Christendom.</p>

<p>Mr. Evarts likewise summed up for the defence. His
argument commenced on the ninety-second day of the proceedings, and ended with
the close of the ninety-ninth day.</p>

<p>Mr. Beach commenced his argument for the plaintiff
on Wednesday, June 9, 1875. He eloquently described the feelings of a husband
whose wife's honor had been stolen away, and referred to the influence that had
been brought to bear in support of the defendant during the trial. "I
have seen," said the learned counsel, "the zealots and the parasites
gathering around Henry Ward Beecher in this trial, and shedding their influence
both in and out of this court in his favor." The foreman of the jury
was addressed in reference to personal appeals that had been made to him by the
counsel for the defendant, and an earnest appeal was made to the jury to decide
the case strictly according to their oaths.</p>

<p>The argument proper was mostly confined to
answering Judge Porter's summing up for Mr. Beecher. Mr. Tilton was eulogized,
but the counsel said he would not indulge in denunciations of Mr. Beecher. The
publication of Mrs. Tilton's letters was explained in a way favorable to the
plaintiff, and various points that had been touched upon by Judge Porter were
gone over in detail. Mr. Beecher was asserted to have been a party to the
policy of silence. The anticipations of triumph indulged in by the defendant's
counsel were treated with severe denunciation, and in referring to the power
possessed by the party of the defendant, the orator said that Mr. Evarts 
"had more than the hundred eyes of Argus, more than the hundred arms of
Briareus, and also the gold of Midas, which had been placed where it would have
the best effect."</p>

<p>There was an excited colloquy between Judge Porter
and Mr. Beach concerning the treatment of the charge of improper proposals, and
then Mr. Beach applied himself with renewed energy to the sifting of the
evidence and a review of Mr. Bowen's relations to the case. Mr. Moulton's
conduct was vigorously defended, and the interview of December 30th and the
alleged confession of Mrs. Tilton which had been destroyed were brought under consideration,
and the doctrines and sentiments attributed to Mr. Beecher in the corruption of
Mrs. Tilton were minutely set forth.</p>

<p>The learned counsel agreed with Mr.
Evarts unreservedly in his reverential estimate of the motive, the ability, and
the success of Mr. Beecher's grand performance in England on behalf of the
great question of servitude and freedom, but with Mr. Evarts' deductions therefrom
in regard to the present issue he was compelled to differ entirely. Was it
possible that they had become so low in the administration of justice that they
could not pronounce judgment against great and noble men for fear of the scoffs
of the aristocracy of England. In that case, he begged God to help justice
and American institutions.</p>

<p>The Woodhull publication was taken up and
discussed, and it was asserted that Mr. Tilton had no part in that publication,
nor had the information therein contained come from him concerning Mr. Tilton's
connection with Mrs. Woodhull. Mr. Beach further said that he knew of no
evidence in the case which tended to show that Mrs. Woodhull's character was so
bad as to make all association with her disreputable. A tribute of respect was
paid to Mrs. Beecher's character for her undeviating faith in her husband and
her actions as a ministering angel to him in his hour of suffering and sorrow,
and then the affirmative portion of the argument was taken up.</p>

<p>Mr. Beach censured the attendance in court of
Mrs. Tilton and Mrs. Beecher, and the alleged theatric exhibitions and displays
on the part of Plymouth Church, as all designed to influence in an indirect and
insidious mode the conclusions of the court. If Mr. Beecher were innocent, he
would have needed no such trappings or aid, but he could have bravely met the
accusations with out any of those policies or stratagems. The letters of Mrs.
Tilton to her husband were considered, their expressions analyzed, and their
bearings on the relations of the parties to the suit shown. That Christianity
was in any way at stake in the trial was altogether scouted by the counsel, and
there need be no fear, he said, of the consequences of Henry Ward Beecher's
fall upon the progress of Christian civilization or Christian influence.</p>

<p>The West charges were gone into, and the alleged
evidence of Mr. Beecher's efforts to suppress the scandal; and in relation to
the theory of blackmail, the counsel argued that all the evidence and
probabilities were against such an hypothesis. Mr. Beecher's denial of guilt
was unsupported, and they had the confronting testimony of three witnesses,
and of circumstantial evidence. The issue of the case was an action by a
husband alleging himself to have been wronged in his dearest relations against
the alleged wrong-doer. They did not ask for damages, as "Theodore
Tilton disdains the idea of touching the gold of Henry Ward Beecher."</p>


<p>The letters of Retraction and Contrition were
analyzed, and counsel argued that both were dictated by Mr. Beecher, and that
similar phrases in both documents were identical with expressions in the
defendant's early works. It was Mr. Beecher's duty to have confessed his sin
and asked forgiveness of Plymouth Church and the Christian world. Bessie
Turner's evidence was referred to as intrinsically incredible, and as being
immaterial so far as the vital point of the case was concerned.  In the closing
point of his argument, Mr. Beach called the good faith of the jury into
question, and declared that he had evidence that jurymen had been improperly
approached. This was met by indignant denials both from the jury and the
counsel of defendant.</p>

<p>Continuing, counsel charged Mr. Beecher with
perjury, and criticised the want of orthodoxy in his sermons; and in concluding
he declared that the duty he had had to perform had been most unwelcome and
painful, and he would leave the case in the hands of the jury, filled with
unaffected admiration and veneration for the magnificent genius of the defendant.
But rich as the defendant was in mental endowments, and prodigal as his labors
had been, they could shelter no offence against the law. "Genius as lofty,
learning more rare and profound, could not save Bacon. He sinned and fell, and
upon his memory history has written the epitaph, 'The greatest and the meanest
of mankind.'" With a final appeal to the jury, the learned counsel closed
his argument on the one hundred and ninth day of the proceedings.</p>

<p>On Thursday, June 24, 1875, Judge Neilson
delivered his charge, which was devoted to the nature and rules of evidence,
the character and credibility of the witnesses, and rules for the guidance of
the jury.</p>

<p>The jury retired, and on the one hundred and
twelfth day of the proceedings, July 2, 1875, they returned into court, and
stated their inability to agree on a verdict; whereupon, after receiving the
thanks of the court for the careful attention they had shown throughout the
trial, they were discharged.</p>
	</div>

         <div1 type="file references">
            <list>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00003" type="same subject"/></item>
               	<item><xptr n="ls.00014" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00016" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00019" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00021" type="history on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00023" type="history on history"/></item>
	
			<item><xptr n="ls.00033" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00046" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00047" type="fiction on history"/></item>

			<item><xptr n="ls.00063" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00066" type="same subject"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00088" type="commentary on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00139" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00140" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00148" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00149" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00150" type="image on history"/></item>
			<item><xptr n="ls.00151" type="image on history"/></item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>