<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="loveandseduction.xsl"?>

<text>

<div id="introduction"><title>General Introduction: Scenes of Love and Seduction</title>

<p>Love and seduction are ageless themes, but the conventions which rule in every era reflect the cultural practices and sexual mores of the times.  With the exception of a few underground publications, the written records of love and seduction in the popular fiction and the popular press of the nineteenth century were exclusively heterosexual (homosexuality was illegal, as was interracial marriage) and largely middle and upper class in their class representations. Morality dramas were usually built around the stories of women who had once been respectable but lost their status through sins such as pregnancy out of wedlock or adultery after they had married, or else around innocent young maidens who came to the city and could not live without sinking into prostitution.  The scandals in the popular press expand our understanding of the practices of love and seduction beyond the refinements typically in force in literary and artistic representations.  Men who broke promises to marry, women duped by declarations of intent, men who harassed the maids, women who enticed men into promises, clergymen who seduced members of the congregation, and unwanted pregnancies were frequent causes for lawsuits.  Press coverage of such stories indicate the high level of interest middle-class readers took in such gossip.  
</p>
<p>When novels began in the eighteenth century in epistolary forms, many of them told tales of seduction.  <hi rend="italics">Pamela</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Clarissa</hi> are two such examples. These seductions were almost uniformly cast in terms of good and evil, though the naivete of the woman being seduced by the salacious and worldly man often made her a pathetic figure.  By the 1850's, literary tales of love and seduction became in some cases more morally complicated; for instance, portraits of unhappy marriages were possible.  Some depictions of seduction and romance were increasingly risque.  The changing conventions about sexual behavior produced a more physically permissive representation of romantic love than the earlier novels of seduction had allowed.</p>

<p>Just how much affection could one show in mid-nineteenth-century courtship?  When were love trysts within bounds and when were they out?  The mid-Victorian woman had to know the mores of love in a carriage, a garden, a parlor, a country lane, a hay field, a park, on a horse, on a picnic, in church, by the beach, in the barn, and behind the barn.  And she needed to know the kind of man, too.  Older men were safer than young ones, members of one's own class were less likely to take advantage than men from a higher class who might not consider marriage.  Sportsmen were riskier than farmers, and all of them were better than soldiers.</p>

<p>The codes which governed love and seduction were elaborate, and the consequences for breaking those codes could be ruinous.  With no sure forms of birth control, sex outside of marriage was a grave risk for a woman.  When conventions dictated that an implied intimacy would be interpreted as conveying an intent to marry, a man had to be careful what signals he gave, or he could find himself trapped into an engagement he never intended.  Yet, for all the rigidities of the conventions, people found ways to declare love, to propose, to seduce, and even to bear illegitimate children.  The documents in this section show us the complexities of the conventions, the ways lovers found to evade those conventions, and the many romances and scandals that arose in an era we mistakenly think of as being very reserved about sex.
</p>
</div>
<div id="spatial"><title>Spatial Settings</title>

<p>The conventions governing when and how lovers and would-be lovers could meet were usually rigid and unforgiving.  The separation of the sexes, except within a family setting, made it difficult for many lovers to develop much of an actual acquaintance before making decisions about engagement or marriage.  Conventions about the geography of a scene of love often determined whether it would lead to a romance smiled on by society that would end in marriage, or a scandal that would ruin lives. To be alone in a carriage with a man, even in daylight, would cast doubt on a woman's reputation if no engagement was immediately forthcoming.  In Trollope's <xlink ref="ls.00074"><hi rend="italics">The American Senator</hi></xlink>, the ambitious Arabella Trefoil counts on the strength of this convention to extract an "offer" from Lord Rufford after she manages a long carriage ride home with him after a day of hunting.  Trollope notes that "The hunting field is by no means a place suited for real love-making. . . . But in a post chaise it would be different." </p>

<p>In the literary representations the conventions of when and how lovers were to meet was a coded clue to who was going to be the heroine/hero and who the villain.   Walks in the open countryside signaled that the lovers would suppress desire and abide by the rules.  A walk in the garden was usually fine if the lovers were in full sunshine and avoided concealment in shade or behind bushes.  A walk in the garden after dusk, however, evidenced deceit and desire.  In the house, a visit in the parlor with another family member present was honorable, even if that other person was a young sister.  A meeting alone in the parlor was reserved for accepted or nearly accepted lovers.  One remembers the maneuvers of Jane Austen's Mrs. Bennett in <xlink ref="ls.00191"><hi rend="italics">Pride and Prejudice</hi></xlink>, setting up the scenes in which her girls could get the offer of marriage she so earnestly wished them to receive. If, however, that parlor setting involved a piano, one needed to be careful.  A young woman singing a serious song alone to her own accompaniment–even if she sang badly–was usually innocent enough, but if the young man sang over her shoulder, or turned the pages, or if the song took a more jolly tone, the degree of danger increased.  The line between an angelic creature singing of the soul and a flirt using music to beguile was a tricky one for a young woman to manage.  In  William Holman Hunt's painting,  <xlink ref="ls.00100"><hi rend="italics">The Awakening Conscienc</hi>e</xlink>, the woman arises from the illicit lap of her lover who is seated at the piano.  As <xlink ref="ls.00041">George Landow's discussion of this scene</xlink> indicates, the entire painting is coded with symbols that represent the sinful ways of this couple.</p>

<p>Though scenes in literature and art encoded the site of innocent love and or sinful behavior through the spatial setting, the conventions of publishers and art dealers typically imposed limits to what might be described or pictured.  In the British and American traditions, there are few sexually explicit novels or paintings among art and literature meant for a middle-class audience, and portraits of sexual desire almost always illustrated that the wages of sin were severe.  Nonetheless, coded language, including the imagery of flowers, could intimate what could not be written directly.  For instance, Nathaniel Hawthorne's hero of <xlink ref="ls.00045"><hi rend="italics">The Blithedale Romance</hi></xlink>, Coverdale, cannot ignore the lush physical charms of Zenobia, but he reshapes her full-flowered beauty and "freedom of her deportment" as the signs that she is not innocent.  He convinces himself, "''There is no folded petal, no latent dewdrop, in this perfectly developed rose!'" </p>

<p>Continental writers were less reticent about sensuality, however, and <xlink ref="ls.00038"><hi rend="italics">Madame Bovary</hi></xlink> is only one of several French novels of the nineteenth century with memorable moments of sensuality.  The "sweetness of sensation" that produces Emma's "faintness" when she "smelt the perfume of the pomade that made his hair glossy" opens up one of the most sensual literary representations of sexual desire in the century.  Emma also reluctantly takes an indiscreet carriage ride, assured by her lover that <xlink ref="ls.00031">"It is done at Paris."</xlink>  Later Emma and Leon will cross yet another boundary to meet regularly  in a hotel room they delighted to call <xlink ref="ls.00030">"our room."</xlink></p> 

<p>Scenes from real life were often not as constrained by convention as middle-class representations of love and seduction in art and literature.  The American journal, the <hi rend="italics">National Police Gazette</hi>&#8212;the nineteenth century's version of the <hi rend="italics">National Enquirer</hi>&#8212;related stories about seductions on the floor, under tables, in clothing stores, and in the minister's office.  The Reverend G.A. Kendrick of Columbus, Georgia, for example, <xlink ref="ls.00012">seduced Miss Fannie Bush</xlink> on the sofa of his study in the church.  The day he got caught, however, they were on the floor, and he dived under a table to hide.  In addition to women who got in trouble with their pastors, women working as domestic help were also at risk of sexual assault in the homes they cleaned, or as they were attended by physicians.  One of the most lurid accounts of the latter is of Dr. Joseph E. Lowes, the physician who seduced his patient in her bed while plying her with drugs and forbidding her husband to have sexual relations with her because <xlink ref="ls.00022">"her health would not admit of it."</xlink> </p> 

<p> In artistic representations, setting gave clear signals about how culturally sanctioned the scene of romance was, but in real life such events more often followed from social and economic structures which exposed vulnerable women to predatory men, or structures that led women to follow their urges in defiance of cultural and moral constraints.  The court cases and public scandals, salacious as they often were, testify to the reality of sexual behavior in the mid-nineteenth century.  Such representations, of course, give little suggestions about erotic or romantic attractions which brought the scandals into being in the first place.  For representations of such passions, we do better to look to artistic representations, which were often charged with passion, even though the signs of such passion were coded. </p>
</div>
<div id="Boudoir"><title>The Boudoir</title>

<p>Any scene set in a boudoir was bound to be scandalous.  Aside from a husband, brother, father, minister, or physician, no man was ever to be in a boudoir with a respectable woman.  Even a bedroom scene between husband and wife would, if represented, violate the decorum that barred any suggestion of the sexual intimacies of married love.  One of the most vivid accounts of married sex in the nineteenth century came down to us in the journals and letters of Mabel Loomis Todd, wife of David Todd, and her lover, Austin Dickinson, the brother of the Amherst poet, Emily Dickinson (Mabel herself became the first editor of <xlink ref="ls.00043">Dickinson's poems</xlink>).  The journal of her sex life in marriage portrays a highly erotic couple who found ecstatic pleasure in their love-making.  For years her journal and their love letters record the mornings of  love-making just after breakfast, or in the evening, or both.  When Mabel later had an affair with Austin, David Todd, himself a man with an adventuresome sex life both before and after marriage, tolerated the goings-on.  Mabel especially enjoyed the boudoir with her husband, of course, but when with Austen Dickinson, found the Todd parlor or dining room convenient enough.</p></div>		

<div id="Country Walk"><title>On a Country Walk</title>

<p>Courting couples in the nineteenth century did not "date" as we know "dating" today.  If they were holding to the norms of their society, men and women were seldom alone together.  One convention that did allow time alone for talk (and on many occasions, a space for more than just talk) was the walk into the country.  The practice known as "walking out" required a delicate balance of the right elements&#8212;time of day, type of lanes, degree of shade, distance, and conversations–to remain "proper."  In literary representations, the country walk was evidence of a proper courtship that signaled the man's good intentions on the part of the man.  If the woman was innocent of contriving to walk out with the man and her meeting with him was accidental, readers knew she was virtuous.   In Trollope's <hi rend="italics">The American Senator</hi>, for example, the naughty Arabella manages a cozy and scandalous ride with her suitor in a <xlink ref="ls.00074">closed carriage</xlink> while the pure-hearted heroine, Mary, walks a country lane "under God's sky" with the somewhat older and reliable <xlink ref="ls.00075">Mr. Morton</xlink>.  This walk ends in a proposal and an informal but binding exchange of vows.  George Eliot's Adam Bede meets his beloved Dinah on a country lane, and their walk also concludes with vows of <xlink ref="ls.00071">eternal love</xlink>.  As both these scenes suggest, at the moment proposals are made and vows given, warm embraces and kisses are sanctioned.</p>  

<p>Even walking out "under God's sky," however, could have erotic overtones.  In Trollope's hand, the walk of the pure Mary and the ever-so-patient Mr. Morton is delicately tinted with the erotic as they hold hands when she crosses the wall and takes care of her own skirt when climbing the stile.  Passionate intensity is usually signaled by flushed cheeks and tears, and the pressure of a hand at her waist is often depicted as enough to dissolve the reserve of many a woman experiencing her first pleasure in  a man's physicality.
</p>
<p>Not all country walks were as innocent as Mary's and Mr. Morton's, however.  A long, shady walk into an isolated lane could lead to illicit sexual intercourse.  The history of trials for breach of promise tells us that not all walking out or exchanging vows ended happily in marriage.  The sexual license given engaged couples was considerable, especially among the lower classes, but defaulting on vows, given or only implied, could result in lawsuits.  A pledge under God's sky often turned into a popular and entertaining melodrama in the courts when breach of promise <xlink ref="ls.00081">charges were filed</xlink>.
</p>
<p>A rendezvous in the country was, of course, an entirely different matter from a walk in the country, as demonstrated by the scene from Trollope's <hi rend="italics">The Way We Live Now</hi> in which Sir Felix Carbury meets Ruby Ruggles, a farm girl much <xlink ref="ls.00011">below him in class</xlink>.  The half-hearted Felix thinks that such a rendezvous is allowed young gentlemen such as himself, given the lure of pretty farm-girls, but Ruby walks home alone thinking of how she will be his wife.  In this case, class differences destablize the more normal expectation that young lovers could find a lessening of restrictions in the open air.</p></div>

<div id="Garden"><title>In a Garden</title>

<p>Garden scenes inevitably resonate with the symbolism of the Garden of Eden from the Book of Genesis.  This symbolism cuts both ways, as the Garden is both the site of innocence and harmony with God, on the one hand, and of temptation and the fall of man, on the other.  Nineteenth-century lovers, well aware of the Biblical story, would have known to be cautious about their behavior in gardens.  Scenes in novels and in real life suggest the lure of the garden as a shady space where private conversations and covert touching could occur.  Such scenes also show that the garden as a place  where order, beauty, and nature could elevate romance to its proper expression, the outward sign of which was the proposal.  In Alcott's <hi rend="italics">Little Women</hi> nature says to these high-minded New England lovers, <xlink ref="ls.00005">"Little Children, love one another."</xlink>  But the "umbrageous twilight" is seductive in Reade's Griffith Gaunt as Mrs. Gaunt and her priest spend too many hours alone discussing <xlink ref="ls.00037">"the love of God."</xlink></p>

<p>The garden is the setting for some of the most famous trysts in nineteenth-century literature.  The climactic meeting between <xlink ref="ls.00020">Jane Eyre and Mr. Rochester </xlink> is perhaps the most popular, but Tennyson's <hi rend="italics">Maud</hi> the darker role of the garden in a courtship.  Since the lover who urges Maud to come into the garden was once a suitor acknowledge by Maud's family and now a suitor her family has turned away, Tennyson manages to make the garden the scene of sanctioned and illicit love in the same moment.  The lover's ambiguous mental state may seem the desirable passion of true love, or the obsession of an unstable mind, or both.</p></div>




<div id="Parlor"><title>In the Parlor</title>
<p>
The parlor was the formal space in the home where a suitor might be entertained, providing that certain conventions were observed, the most important of which was that a young lady did not receive her suitor alone unless, by common consent, they were nearly engaged.  Alas for the young man who had to try to court in the presence of other members of the family.  And alas for the young lady or her family who had to maneuver a lapse in scrutiny to give the man a moment alone with her to make his proposal!</p>

<p>The images and texts of the parlor as a spatial setting for love and seduction are primarily moments in which the conventions are violated, since little of interest could happen until the suitor could contrive to catch the lady unchaperoned.  Young ladies who contrived to be alone in the parlor were flirting with danger, for though they might be safely in their home, a man might take liberties.  In a society in which a compromising meeting could become the basis for an "understanding," both men and women needed to be careful how setting signaled intentions.</p>
<p>
The scene between the virtuous Clara Day and the iniquitous Craven Le Noir in Mrs. E.D.E.N. Southworth's novel, <hi rend="italics"><xlink ref="ls.00024">The Hidden Hand</xlink></hi>, [content.php?id=ls.00024] underlines both the presumption of the parlor's safety and its actual dangers when a woman is left alone with a dishonorable man. </p></div>


<div id="Dance or Party"><title>At a Dance or Party</title>

<p>A courting couple might walk out together, but how did one meet eligible members of the opposite sex?  Women and men were not in school or at work together, and the purposes and formalities of church made initiating a courtship from a pew rather difficult.  Socially approved events such as parties and dances were common for the middle and upper classes in both cities and villages.  They were important events because they were the sites at which couples could meet or openly exchange social greetings for the first time.  Among upper middle and aristocratic classes, the tradition of taking a debutante to London "for the season" put her on the marriage market through her appearance at balls and parties.</p>

<p>In the nineteenth century, parties and dances were attended by all ages so that older people, family members, clergy, and other friends and relations were there to chaperone these entertainments.  Dancing itself was a social convention that allowed men and women to touch slightly and exchange a few words as the dance steps kept them moving from partner to partner.  Once the waltz craze swept European and American society in the 1830s, men and women could even touch throughout the dance.  Once even a casual introduction was made, a man could appropriately pursue conversation with a lady and ask for a dance.  Such a social interaction could become the basis for asking to call on the lady and her family, an act that signaled his interest in a courtship.</p>  

<p>Dances and parties could also be the site of serious social misconduct.  The line between mildly playful flirting and acting like a coquette was thin.  John Frederick Smith's <hi rend="italics">Minnigrey</hi> illustrates the <xlink ref="ls.00044">dangerous side to dances</xlink>.   The coquettish La Pascata, a Portuguese opera singer, passes over the line at the masked ball where concealed identities allow for greater indiscretion.  Attired "in the costume of a gipsy," La Pascata is the embodiment for the young Englishman, Gus, of exotic and forbidden eroticism.  Her black hair falls long "upon her neck and shoulders," and her inappropriately short "scarlet petticoat" excites the inexperienced Gus to passionate emotion.  Her provocative dress and tantalizing conversation provide an example of how to transgress social decorum. </p> 

<p>Since a proper marriage was an arrangement of social, economic, and romantic interests for the men and women involved, their families, and the community, parties and dances often were occasions for matchmaking by one's relatives and even the community elders. Obvious matchmaking embarrassed the victims, but subtle matchmaking was an art that the whole community implicitly relied on to keep society going.  But since parties and dances often included people from somewhat different levels of the middle and upper class, they could often be the site of romantic misalliances, too.
</p>
<p><xlink ref="ls.00110">W. Gorway's drawing</xlink>, "The Party in the Drawing-Room," gives us a nuanced image of a party where the proper and the slightly improper are visible.  Most of the guests are enjoying talk, tea, games, but what of the couple in the foreground?  Are they behaving properly or not?  What do the faces of the other party-goers suggest about the social values controlling this image?  As an illustration to a serialized novel, this sketch creates anticipatory suspense for the reader about the relationships the fiction will relate.</p></div>


<div id="Piano"><title>At a Piano</title>

<p>The charms of music can be very seductive, and every era defines the style and instruments that best convey the rhythms of romance for the time.  As the guitar has been the signature instrument of popular music of our age, so was the piano for the nineteenth century.  Production of pianos made them more affordable than ever before, and many middle and upper class homes had one. Printed sheet music was available, and playing the piano was one of the skills expected of a cultivated (as opposed to educated) young woman.  The versatility of the instrument allowed it to be used for popular ballads of the day, hymns, or more classical works.  The need to have a helper to turn the pages made a piano a natural setting for a man and a woman who wished to be close to one another within a social setting.  The spell of music deepened the romantic charm of the moment.  Perhaps no single site was so common for love and seduction as the piano bench.</p>

<p>The piano so embodied romantic feelings that it was popular as a gift from a man to a woman, though if outside of marriage,  the circumstances had to be quite delicate for it to be an acceptable gift.  Henry Shaw of St. Louis gave one to Miss Effie Carstang as part of a string of gifts designed to reward her for her sexual favors.  When Shaw decided not to marry Effie, the gift of a piano was one of several signs she could claim indicated she believed they were engaged, a claim she argued in court when she later sued him for breech of promise.</p>

<p>Images of couples at the piano abound in the popular press and the art of the day.   The illustration in <hi rend="italics">The London Journal</hi>  for John Frederick Smith's <hi rend="italics">Temptation</hi> shows the scheming Miss Wyndham at the piano with the gentleman in attendance <xlink ref="ls.00116">turning pages for her</xlink>.  Holman Hunt's vivid painting of <hi rend="italics">The Awakening Conscience</hi> portrays a young woman rising from the lap of her lover who is seated at the <xlink ref="ls.00100">piano</xlink>.  The iconography of this painting casts the piano as the instrument of seduction.</p></div>  


<div id="Public Spaces"><title>In Public Spaces</title>

<p>Women outside the home were always vulnerable to circumstances that could taint their reputations, or, in extreme cases, actually result in their being cast out of the home in disgrace.  If that public space was not the market, the church, or other safe locales, a woman needed to be very careful.  Many poor young women who came to the city found themselves tricked into prostitution; many others turned to it in desperation for a way to live.
</p>
<p>Since women rarely held respected positions in the world of work or public affairs, women working outside the home had to battle assumptions that they were of questionable character. Nurses, for instance, were a subject of <xlink ref="ls.00086">social concern</xlink>.  Reform movements in nursing had to address the question of sexual contamination by nurses. Nursing pioneers such as Florence Nightingale and Clara Barton encouraged older women to become nurses in order to combat the suspicion that nurses were of questionable character.</p>

 <p>Much of the attitude about women in public spaces focused on women who were unfaithful wives or pregnant out of wedlock.  Abortion was a dangerous and shameful choice in a society that allowed no sexual activity to women except within marriage.  <xlink ref="ls.00102">Augustus Egg's triptych</xlink> provides grim images of the shame and ruin a wife's adultery could bring to her, her husband, and her children.  Adultery in a woman was a socially and morally unforgivable sin.
</p>
<p>Readers may want to ask how the literary and public  imagination of the adulteress as outcast matches up with actual lives. While there is no doubt that women were held to high standards of sexual conduct and that a double standard of judgment was often applied to them, there is also no doubt that adultery was not uncommon and did not always result in a wife's being cast into the gutter.  Mabel Loomis Todd's long adulterous affair with Austin Dickinson did not seem to damage her standing in the Amherst community, and her husband was certainly not outraged about it.  The Todd-Dickinson affair may be the other extreme of permissiveness, but we have little evidence of the possibly numerous affairs that did not result in a broken home, a bastard child in the arms of an outcast wife, or prostitution.</p></div>


<div id="Carriage or Train"><title>In a Carriage or Train</title>

<p>Industrialized society created new and more rapid forms of transportation; the growing use of cabs, carriages, and trains to travel provided as well new opportunities for seduction out of public view.  Women did travel alone, but it was considered a bold and potentially dangerous thing to do.  Ideally, a woman traveling by coach or train was in company with a family member or an esteemed family friend.  Within the city, a ride in a closed carriage with a man was risky behavior.  Such an isolated space allowed for talk and caresses could occur that were only permissible to an engaged couple.  The very fact of being alone in a carriage could be read as evidence of an engagement.  Arabella Trefoil in <hi rend="italics">The American Senator</hi> relies on this convention when she rides home alone with <xlink ref="ls.00074">Lord Rufford</xlink> after the hunt.  When he denies the engagement and cannot be pressed into it, both parties have their reputations damaged, though, as one might expect, the woman without wealth and title suffers much the harsher judgement than the man with wealth and title.
</p>
<p>Perhaps the most heated drive in a carriage occurs in Madame Bovary, where Leon takes Emma Bovary on a long ride throughout Paris, <xlink ref="ls.00030">curtains drawn throughout</xlink>.  Flaubert discreetly suggests the presumed passion within the carriage by describing the exhaustion and thirst of the poor driver sitting atop it who drives aimlessly and frantically from one part of the city to another, looking wistfully at the pubs he passes along the way. 
</p>
<p>In Greensburg, Indiana, the real life drama of Miss Hannah White and Mr. Newton Hazelrigg unfolded as well in a <xlink ref="ls.00023">scandalous carriage ride</xlink>.   Mr. Hazelrigg had more than the usual access to carriages, apparently, since he was "of the well-known carriage manufacturing firm of Crawford &amp; Hazelrigg."  He did admit that they "had taken a pleasant ride in a carriage," but denied that he could be the father of the baby she was carrying.  Miss White and Mr. Hazelrigg were no doubt miserable in this public scandal, but the town found it all very entertaining: "Of the 5,000 people in Greenburg probably about 4,900 are discussing the merits of the case.  It is, perhaps, proper to add that the fingers have all been counted in Greenburg, and it is said that on or about the 5th of next month the trouble will culminate."  Both in fiction and historical accounts, the secluded carriage ride was almost synonymous with sin and deceit, as the "elopement" with a married man in "<xlink ref="ls.00076">An Elopement in a Carriage</xlink>" indicates.  
 </p>
</div>
<div id="Urban Walkway"><title>On an Urban Walkway</title>

<p>Walks in a country lane could be innocent and "proper," but they could also offer an unseemly seclusion.  Walks on city and town streets, however, provided women a place to be in public on acceptable business, such as shopping.  In the limited range of places nineteenth-century women could go, the city street may have been one of the freest spaces for movement and pleasures beyond the home and church.  Because a street was normally peopled, the public itself served as a protective chaperone.  Public parks, sidewalk cafes, shops, museums,  and food stalls were all possible destinations.  A man seeking to further an acquaintance might hope to run into the woman of his desires on the street.  It was one of few places he could talk with her without prearrangement or a chaperone nearby.</p>

<p>The scene from <hi rend="italics">Little Women</hi> in which Jo goes into town hoping to meet Mr. Bhaer illustrates the <xlink ref="ls.00006">freedom of the street</xlink>. In this case Jo goes safely into a commercial district where women did not usually have business.  When she actually does meet up with Mr. Bhaer, the two of them continue the shopping trip, moving from store to store while Jo tries to focus on buying the things that were her excuse to go to town.  The scene culminates in the proposal that Jo has longed to hear.</p>

<p>Dante Gabriel Rossetti's painting, "Found," illustrates another side to the <xlink ref="ls.00010">urban street</xlink>. For women already "lost," the street becomes the site of prostitution, poverty, and despair. Streets after dark were as forbidden to a woman who wanted to keep her good name as were entering a closed carriage or boudoir with a man not one's husband. </p>

<p>Nineteenth-century urban life was understood as more wicked and worldly than rural or village life.  Its size and complexity provided more ways to hide sinful behavior, but in other ways, it provided lovers, and especially, women, more venues in which to meet people and compare members of the opposite sex.  Theaters, operas, concerts, cafes, shops, parks were all sites of urban life where lovers and potential lovers could meet without grave danger.</p></div>


<div id="Wild"><title>In the Wild</title>

<p>Gardens, parks, and lanes might be spaces for intimate talk and warm caresses, but lovers usually needed more seclusion than such sites afforded to consummate sexual relationships.  Beyond the borders of the cultivated spaces was the wild, thickets dense enough to provide a curtain of green, trees so close that one could not see through them.  Such settings, especially under an evening sky, could become nature's boudoir for couples whose passion demanded more than a kiss and some hand-holding.  The ever-ready Emma Bovary rides deep into the woods with Rodolphe, their horses panting, their own knees touching, the leather saddles creaking.  Amid the croaking frogs of the pond "<xlink ref="ls.00038">she gave herself up to him</xlink>–."  Younger and more innocent lovers such as Hetty and Arthur in George Eliot's Adam Bede forget their best resolves alone <xlink ref="ls.00035">in the forest at night</xlink>.</p>

<p>The wilds were much more than just a cover for sexual pleasure; the wildness of nature itself loosed the restraints of society.  The wildness of nature spoke to the passions in various settings, including the mountains, the moors, and the ocean.  Tennyson's luckless couple in "Locksley Hall"spend "many a morning on the moorland" and "many an evening by the waters" of <xlink ref="ls.00007">the sea</xlink>.  The untamed moorland and tossing ocean resonate with the "storm" in the breast of the lovers.  Arthur Hughes' painting, The Long Engagement, captures the torment of proper <xlink ref="ls.00099">engaged lovers</xlink>.  He looks to the heavens for relief from the pain of his desire while she looks sympathetically and longingly into his face.  Around them the trees, the vines, and the wild roses are too disorderly to provide the comfort of restraint.   His face is shadowed, perhaps as befits his less pure thoughts, but her face in bright sunlight will keep this couple on the right path, unless, of course, they linger til dusk and the fecundity of wild roses tempt them into illicit passion.</p></div>


<div id="Common Themes"><title>Common Themes</title>


<p>Different spatial settings could provide the stage for proper or improper conduct, but it was the actions and emotions of people in those settings that determined if the courtship would end in a happy marriage or a searing divorce, if a lover would be faithful or betray, if sexual activity was restrained or out of control. This section of Scenes of Love and Seduction explores several themes in romantic relations from literature and art and instances that illustrate these same themes in the popular press.  The expression of love and the practices of seduction sometimes led to premarital sex, sometimes to engagement and marriage, sometimes to abandonment, breach of promise suits, or prostitution.  Broken promises of engagement were of such serious import for a woman that she might well feel that exposure of her personal life in court and in the press was worth it to clear her name.  Seeking remedy for wrongs through a breach of promise suit was not uncommon, though the reporting in the press and the gossip of the community could be utterly humiliating to all parties. Many breach of promise suits grew out of pregnancies.  If a couple were engaged, they were permitted some freedom of sexual expression since it was assumed that they would soon be man and wife.  If premarital sex went too far, however, and the wedding did not follow, a woman and her family might have little choice but to sue or see her castigated by the community. </p>

<p>Marriages might come from the heart or by prearrangement.  Whether the marriage was happy or unhappy, it was unlikely to end in divorce, but some divorces occurred.  Divorce required proof of adultery, one of the nineteenth-century's greatest moral taboos.  The adulterer was romance's monster figure.  Although there was a strong double standard in sexual mores, even the culture of men did not wink at adultery, and a woman accused of it risked home, husband, and children.  Augustus Egg's triptych vividly illustrates the abject shame of the woman, the injury to her children, and her miserable fate when her lover tosses her and the bastard child into <xlink ref="ls.00104">the gutter of the city</xlink>.  This narrative implies that for an adulteress, only death or prostitution await.</p>

<p>Yet, in the reality of mid-nineteenth-century, both adultery and premarital sex were not uncommon, and not all who indulged in either sin were left at the altar or thrown out of their homes.  The literary representations are highly moralistic, and the press accounts are as lurid as the case would allow.  The letters and journals of real people, however, suggest that such behavior was often tolerated, or forgiven, or ignored, or patched up.  As we recognize today, human behavior in love and seduction is too complex to be easily sorted out and judged by social conventions alone.</p>
</div>

<div id="Adultery"><title>Adultery</title>

<p>The nineteenth century's view on adultery was that it destroyed the home and family.  In artistic representation and apparently even in casual talk between men by themselves, adultery was considered a crime and never excused.Most literary works of the nineteenth century in the United States and Great Britain found the topic too toxic even for a plot focus since the subject could be talked about in print only with the greatest reserve and discretion, while the less discreet French nonetheless charged Flaubert with obscenity for writing about Emma Bovary's adultery with relative openness.</p>

<p>Students of the period should not imagine, however, that the artistic representations and moral teachings meant that adultery was uncommon.  Sex scandals in the nineteenth century both horrified and beguiled an eager reading public.  None was more sensational than the relationship between the prominent Puritan preacher of Plymouth Church, Henry Ward Beecher, and the attractive member of his congregation, <xlink ref="ls.00063">Mrs. Elizabeth R. Tilton</xlink>.  This affair became the prototype for stories of ministers who seduced attractive women in their congregations.  The charges flew back and forth between Beecher and Mrs. Tilton's husband, Theodore. Mrs. Tilton's letter to Beecher about their "intimacy" was to some the evidence of wrong-doing, and to others an ambiguous account of their friendship.  The documented  legal proceedings, her confessions and retractions, and testimony about "criminal relations" and Beecher's stature as a leading clergyman made this trial the most widely publicized "affair" in mid-nineteenth- century America.  Readers today may still find the question of their guilt or innocence a subject for debate. Mrs. Tilton's view of her conduct was influenced by a popular novel of the time, <xlink ref="ls.00037"><hi rend="italics">Griffith Gaunt</hi></xlink>, and the relationship of real life and literary representation are wonderful intertwined in this scandal.</p>

</div>
<div id="Arranged Marriage"><title>Arranged Marriage</title>

<p>Marriage in the nineteenth century was a social convention designed to do far more than bring together people who loved each other. Nothing shows us the mercenary side of marriage more than the arranged marriage.  Marriages were often arranged in order to consolidate land, expand a fortune, obtain a fortune, avoid a lawsuit, protect a political sphere of power and, at the royal level, make peace and determine foreign policy.  Marriages were also arranged to protect a good name, to give legitimacy to a child, and to marry off a woman or man who seemed unable to manage for him or herself.  For some, matchmaking was a game, an art, and for some it was just a chance to make mischief.  Many a real-life story as well as a good novel revolved around the misery in an arranged marriage that was loveless, or the foiling of a plot to arrange a marriage for some base reason. 
</p>
<p>Modern audiences tend to be repelled by the notion of an arranged marriage, but in a society filled with strict conventions of courtship, nuanced considerations of class, and a double standard about acceptable conduct in women and men, arranged marriages could be useful in many ways.  Nevertheless, it was a practice slowly dying away as new levels of personal freedom encouraged people to make their own choices.  The arranged marriage became less and less common as the century progressed, in both Europe and in the United States. In past centuries, arranged marriages had helped stabilize the aristocracy in European class structure, and the decline of arranged marriages also meant the economic and political decline of the upper class.  Arranged marriages in America were never as popular or as useful since the American Revolution undermined their class function.  The most common kind of arranged marriage in the United States was for moral imperatives, such as saving a woman's good name or protecting a child from bastardy.
</p>
<p>Tennyson wrote more than one poem in which an arranged marriage was central to the plot.  In <xlink ref="ls.00007">"Locksley Hall"</xlink> the weak-willed Amy is "puppet to a father's threat, and servile to a shrewish tongue!"  The jilted lover is bitter about Amy, the husband she does take, her parents' interference in their romance, and "the sickly forms that err from honest Nature's rule."  In Tennyson's <hi rend="italics">Maud</hi> the narrator again is enraged that the girl he thought was promised to him when their parents were friends now finds her pressured by her family to deny the arrangement and look to make a better, <xlink ref="ls.00008">richer match</xlink>.  
</p>
<p> The section on "The Rationale of Match-making" from <hi rend="italics">Punch's</hi> "The Natural History of Courtship" gives us a humorous perspective from 1842 on the kinds and manners of <xlink ref="ls.00055">matchmakers</xlink>.Notably, the ever-present "chaperone" is also considered the chief matchmaker.  In Mrs. Couples we see the skill brought to an art.  The two examples from the United States in the <hi rend="italics">National Police Gazette</hi> illustrate the role preservation of morality plays in the cases of arranged marriages: both the wayward Episcopalian bishop from Detroit and the snobbish but irresponsible Boston family who don't want their son to marry the girl he got pregnant give in to society's strictures and allow an arranged marriage.
</p>
</div>
<div id="Breach of Promise"><title>Breach of Promise</title>

<p> Two kinds of nineteenth-century lawsuits involving lovers have almost ceased to exist today: the breach of promise suit when the engagement is no longer desired by one of the parties, and the alienation of affection suit when another lover takes one's betrothed or spouse "away." In the nineteenth century, however, women in particular lost a great deal when an engagement did not go forward to the marriage.  The greater permissiveness in conduct allowed engaged couples meant that the woman whose engagement was broken carried a sexual taint.  Thus, both her good name and her value as a commodity in the marriage market were ruined.  Such severe loss often found attempted redress in the breach of promise lawsuit.  
</p>
<p>Not all breach of promise suits came out of broken engagements, however, as the belief that one was engaged could be equally damaging if the woman had behaved with the license allowed those who planned to marry.  Consider the case of the married Mr. Brown who proposed to Elizabeth McKeown, swearing on the Bible he had given her that she would be <xlink ref="ls.00013">his wife</xlink>. He told her that their vow on the Bible was "as good as being married," but when she became pregnant, she found herself ruined.  The court agreed with her, awarding damages of $1,250.  The case of breach of promise brought by Miss Effie Carstang was more complicated and the <xlink ref="ls.00025">stakes much higher</xlink>.This case went to trial repeatedly with one different outcome after another, a happenstance which illustrates many of the pitfalls of legal efforts to resolve matters of the heart. 
</p>
<p>The conventions of engagement, marriage, and breach of promise raise many issues about the social, moral, and economic value of marriage.  Readers may wish to explore more fully the forces that made marriage so much more than a choice between lovers and to think why contemporary practices have changed so radically.
</p>
</div>
<div id="Class"><title>Class</title>

<p>In the nineteenth century, marriage could be the easiest way for a woman to change her class status.  The theme of the poor but beautiful woman who marries well is a stable in the fiction, both by major authors and in the popular novels. In one form or another, the nineteenth century was replete with Cinderella stories, such as those of Jane Eyre, poor and plain, or Hetty Sorel, beautiful milkmaid, or Ruby Ruggles, robust farm girl, or Arabella Trefoil, lady without fortune.  Such stories were endlessly popular, whether the good girl got her man or the bad girl got her comeuppance, or, just occasionally, the bad girl got her man but found the marriage not worth the misery. These stories in which class status figures as such an important element reflect two contradictory forces in the nineteenth century: the first, the vulnerability of all women to control their own fate when they had so few rights under the law and so little access to jobs, and the second, the rising claims that women should have the right to control their own fate, be treated as equals under the law, and have more options than being a governess, a wife, a spinster, or a prostitute.  <hi rend="italics">Jane Eyre</hi> is a success story of a sort– a working woman from the middle class who gets her man on her own terms–but it is a success story that must move both of them outside issues of class status to enable them to meet on somewhat level social and sexual ground.
</p>
<p>The reverse of the Cinderella story is of the man who goes slumming with a woman of ill-repute and just barely escapes with his money and honor intact.  Gus must free himself of the charms on La Pascata in <hi rend="italics">Minnigrey</hi>, and the story of Carmen sets a stereotype that functions even to this day as the tragic coquette.  
</p>
<p>The scandals from <hi rend="italics">The National Police Gazette</hi> almost always link class to seduction.  The Beecher scandal was striking in the public's eye in part because he was a prominent preacher, but also because both Beecher and Tilton were from the same upper-middleclass.  <hi rend="italics">The Police Gazette</hi> specialized in stories in which the class inequity was a factor in the seductions.  Whether deacon, minister, or employer, the villains were typically men with status and the victims young women with hopes of wedlock. Many of the women in these stories were poor, expecting a male rescuer to lift them out of their economic, emotional, and social plight.  Unfortunately, when that did not happen, many of these women were left with their virtues sullied and without other resources.
</p>
<p>Readers may want to look at how issues of class are defined differently in American literature and scandals than in the literature and scandals of British and European societies.  The interaction of class with gender complicates our assumptions about class status, too, and questions arise about the way gender undoes for women the normal protection and privileges of class.
</p></div>

<div id="Courtship"><title>Courtship</title>

<p>All forms of love and seduction involve some degree of courtship since to suspend all gestures of courtship would be to reduce even the moment of seduction to one of mere rape.  Even in Mrs. Southworth's daring <hi rend="italics">The Hidden Hand</hi>, the villainous Black Donald and the bold but virtuous "Cap" talk, eat, and make eggnog before he moves in on her for the rapacious moment he has been threatening during his <xlink ref="ls.00067">repast</xlink>. Little does he know that while he is contemplating rape, she is contemplating murder!
</p>
<p> Whether in the scandal sheets or the pages of the finest novel, much of the drama occurred in courtship.  Typically, the fictional story's happy ending was achieved when the kiss and the vows had been exchanged.  Adam Bede's late afternoon meeting with the pious Dinah ends with expressions that their love "is the Divine Will"; the chapter ends with the two kissing "each other with a <xlink ref="ls.00071">deep joy</xlink>."  Henry Ward Beecher's novel, <hi rend="italics">Norwood</hi>, end in a similar declaration of love between <xlink ref="ls.00047">Abiah Cathcart and Rachel Liscomb</xlink>.  The publishing of the banns from the pulpit evoke the Divine Will to grace their marriage, too.  Mary and Mr. Morton in Trollope's <hi rend="italics">The American Senator</hi> share a similarly blissful moment when their silent courtship finally finds words and kisses, but the future, though clearly to be happy, won't be without some problems with the <xlink ref="ls.00075">in-laws</xlink>. 
 Nineteenth-century narrative energy tends to be expended on courtship rather its results; rarely are these fictional lovers seen as they set up housekeeping and proceed to the more difficult work of making a marriage work.
</p>
<p>Fiction and art also show the agony of courtships that go awry.  Tennyson's male speakers in <hi rend="italics">Maud</hi> and "Locksley Hall" love better than they are loved, and their courtships end with the loss of the lady.  Inequalities between the class standing or the financial standing of lovers were two major reasons courtships often went sour.  In his personal life Tennyson had a long engagement before he won his bride because he could not support a wife.  Long engagements before marriage were common in an age that expected men to be fully financially independent before they could take a wife.  Arthur Hughes' painting, <hi rend="italics">The Long Engagement</hi>, registers the protracted misery of many Victorian couples in love who for various reasons could not marry.
</p>
<p>Courtship sketches in the newspapers and journals provide some vivid representations of gentlemen on their knees, or ladies modestly turning their heads away, or couples flirting in the parlor.  Typically the men are tall and lean, the women with tiny waists, wearing the voluminous skirts that had to be a barrier to close embraces.  E. L.  Andells's cartoons in <hi rend="italics">Punch</hi> satirize the whole process, especially the compliments that the fortune-hunting man had to dish out to his otherwise <xlink ref="ls.00143">unappealing romantic object</xlink>.
</p>
<p>Manners in courtship have changed dramatically since the nineteenth century, but the popularity of the courtship story seems not to have waned.  The excitement of the pursuit, the tension of passion delayed, the anxiety of misunderstood intentions, and the fear that the one we love will not love us create high drama, whatever the cultural conventions.  Difficult considerations such as lack of money, disapproving families, conflicts of class and religion, and separation by long distances all enhance the drama of heterosexual romance.  Readers might like to compare some of these scenes from the nineteenth century with such popular films of our time as <hi rend="italics">Meet the Parents</hi>, <hi rend="italics">My Big Fat Greek Wedding</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Bridget Jones's Diary</hi>.  These films may seem to suggest that the more things change, the more they stay the same.  What does it mean that so little popular fiction or film in either century focuses on the pleasures or pains of marriage?  
</p></div>

<div id="Divorce"><title>Divorce</title>

<p>Divorce in the nineteenth century was very hard to get and a quite public event if one did.  Prior to 1857 in England, it took an act of Parliament to get a divorce.  The Matrimonial Causes in Act in 1857 made divorce possible through the courts, but the proceedings were expensive and thus mainly available to the upper classes.  Divorce in France, after a period of Napoleonic leniency, was extremely difficult to obtain; in the rare cases divorce was granted, women bore most of the economic and social costs. Once divorce proceedings became a matter of a court record, they were covered by the popular press in both the United States, France, and England in all their details.  The poor wife of the Chicago man who chloroformed her and then proceeded to sexually harass the maid while his wife was unconscious had to see all the details of her abusive marriage in the paper when she sought a <xlink ref="ls.00021">divorce</xlink>.
</p>
<p>Judging from the evidence in the papers, divorce among the middle class was more common in America than in England, a case apparently related to the different class traditions in the two countries.  Protection under the law in the United States was more accessible to the middle classes, and democratic traditions perhaps made Americans less reluctant to seek those rights.  Still, except for cases of outrage, separation was a more common resolution to an unhappy marriage than divorce.  Both separation and divorce were generally considered a scandal, and many separations were never formally or openly called separations as such.
</p>
<p>With the majority of marriages ending in divorce in our contemporary society, it may be hard to believe that there were fewer than 200 divorces a year in mid-century England. The comparative inferior status of women's legal rights had much to do with these statistics.  A wife's infidelity was the most acceptable social justification for a divorce.  Despite the fact that adultery was not uncommon, few marriages ruined by adultery actually ended in divorce.  The illustrations in the popular press suggest that the most appropriate thing to do with an adulterous wife was to cast her out on the streets where she would become a common prostitute.  The reality was that the adulterous wife was likely to be the mother of the couple's children, and casting her out would create a scandal that damaged the whole family.  With divorce not much of an option for most people, there often was little else that one could do.</p></div>


<div id="Popular Press"><title>The Popular Press</title>

<p>Mid-century journalism, especially in the United States, was typically raucous and ungoverned.  Any viewer looking at the selections on this site can easily see the press's preoccupation with sensationalism in the choice of stories, the prose style of the writing, and the illustrations.  Politics, sex, and crime were featured in the newspapers, the journals, and the fiction of the era.  Best yet were the stories that combined all three!  
</p>
<p>Mass printed papers, journals, and books at affordable prices came of age in the mid-nineteenth century.  Better transportation systems allowed news to travel faster and for newspapers to get their latest editions on the street quickly.  The ethical codes many of the finest newspapers today observe had not yet been developed, and the burgeoning profession was highly competitive and largely unchecked.  By the last decade of the nineteenth century efforts were underway to suppress the sensationalism of the press and the public discussion of sexual practices, sexual crimes, and sexual scandals.  Until that repressive period, however, the idea that the "Victorians" (both British and American) didn't think or talk much about sex is easily debunked.  The popular press accounts not only document their own preoccupation with sex scandal, but also the community's delight and horror in gossiping about these scandals, taking sides, and often interfering to expose them.  The infamous <xlink ref="ls.00063">Beecher-Tilton</xlink> scandal finally broke in the press when a third party decided to expose it. ] The case of the naughty minister who was making love to his lovely young parishioner on the floor of the church parlors was exposed by a group of young men who took it upon themselves to track her movements and <xlink ref="ls.00012">peek in the window.</xlink> 
</p>
<p>Stories from the divorce courts, tales of ministers who abused women of the flock, babies born out of wedlock, husbands who assaulted the household help, and women, both married and unmarried, who yielded to desire and ruined themselves were common reading fare in the home on both continents. <hi rend="italics">The Divorce News and Police Report</hi> specialized in juicy stories of sexual misbehavior. Many of the stories mixed sexual sin with murder as injured lovers of both sexes turned guns and knives on their betrayers. The illustrations in papers like <hi rend="italics">The National Police Gazette</hi>, <hi rend="italics">New York Graphic</hi>, and the <hi rend="italics">London Journal</hi> were either sentimental or lurid. Idealized love scenes in gardens, saucy flirtations in the parlor, shame-filled dramas of the adulterer exposed, and pitiful portrayals of children being torn away from their mother's arms filled the pages of the popular press. Even serious writers, such as George Eliot, Charles Dickens, and Anthony Trollope, reflected the sensationalism of stories about bigamy, adultery, child abuse, alcohol, and bastardy.  In America, Nathaniel Hawthorne's <hi rend="italics">The Scarlet Letter</hi>, despite its moral meaning, depended on a story about a minister's adultery, a child born out of wedlock, and a woman's ruin.  
</p>
<p>A better understanding of the widespread popularity of stories about sexual misadventures common in mid-nineteenth century societies may inspire us to rethink our assumptions about the lives of the people and the literature that came out of the period. Clearly most of the scandals in the papers were about more than illicit hand-holding. Readers of the <hi rend="italics">London Journal</hi> or <hi rend="italics">The National Police Gazette</hi> read popular novels against the backdrop of the daily and weekly fare in the popular press. What were their assumptions when they read, for example, <hi rend="italics">Wuthering Heights</hi>, which intimates scandalous romance without providing details?  Mid-century people may have understood their world and the place of sex in it in a much more open and familiar way than the stereotypes of Victorian sensibilities presume.</p></div>


<div id="Premarital Sex"><title>Premarital Sex</title>

<p>The moral prohibitions against premarital sex in earlier ages were directly related to the balance of power between the sexes and the danger of unwanted pregnancies.  The only "safe sex" was no sex. In England rights to inheritance still descended through the male heirs, and securing the legitimacy of heirs by guarding women's chastity still prevailed.  Among the poor who had little to inherit, the practical prohibitions against premarital sex were not so real, but a woman in any class who indulged in sexual misadventures surrendered her moral authority, which was the primary source of her power, too. Christian morality, still in the ascendency throughout the nineteenth century, preached clearly against premarital sexual activity; chastity was a key virtue. The Hetty Sorels and Ruby Ruggles of the rural world could lose their futures as wives as easily as a lady in the upper class could lose all possibility of a good match.  In the literary and artistic representations of the fallen woman, she is typically an abject outcast, as in Rossetti's <hi rend="italics">Found</hi>, who might find forgiveness but never reinstatement in <xlink ref="ls.00101">good society</xlink>. 
</p>
<p>Evidence from real life suggests more leniency than in the literature. Premarital sex was not, after all, such a rare failing, and illegitimate children were a fixture in all classes. Accounts in the <hi rend="italics">National Police Gazette</hi> and <hi rend="italics">London Journal</hi>, for example, portrayed many of these women as preyed upon by unscrupulous men. Often the women were in powerless positions responding to a trusted minister, or trapped by an employer's sexual designs. The community liked to gossip about the scandals, but their inclination to tar and feather the cads who had injured the women suggests that the unfortunate woman was not always a pariah.
</p>
<p>Among the engaged, some degree of premarital sexual exploration was expected as part of what it meant to be engaged to marry.  Some scholars have speculated that most brides were probably still virgins when they married, but no reliable data exists for such speculation. Love letters, the popularity of Valentines, popular ballads, and the best-selling fiction all attest to the passionate intensity associated with love. Hughes's painting "The Long Engagement" portrays the pain of chastity when <xlink ref="ls.00099">marriage was delayed</xlink>. In such circumstances, premarital sex of some sort may have been common.</p></div>


<div id="Prostitution"><title>Prostitution</title>

<p>Prostitution is the evidence of the powerlessness and poverty of women in a society. Every major European city had its sections where prostitution was common. In the United States, New York City was famous for its prostitutes.  The industrial and financial changes in nineteeth-century economy moved many women out of the villages and farms to make their way in the cities. Without decent jobs and homes, these women often saw nothing else to do but make their living on the streets. Not all prostitutes were, of course, poor, and in London the fashionable section of Belgravia became a popular place for classy prostitutes such as "Skittles" (Catherine Walters) to show off her horsemanship and land her lovers.  
</p>
<p>In London and New York a variety of efforts were made to clean up prostitution.  Laws were proposed to make it a crime to seduce a woman, but to little avail.  The 1860 Contagious Diseases Act in England required medical exams of women suspected of prostitution in towns with military installations. Most of the legal efforts to contain prostitution were more designed to protect men from prostitutes and venereal disease than to provide assistance to women who were themselves prostitutes or facing prostitution because they were destitute.
</p>
<p>Attitudes about prostitution may give us insights to a society's attitudes about sexuality.  In some European countries today prostitution is legalized and regulations imposed to protect the health of customers.  In other countries, such as the United States, prostitutes are still arrested for soliciting, but in most communities the laws now make also have laws against hiring a prostitute, making their male customers open to civil punishment.
</p></div>

<div id="Scenes from Literature"><title>Scenes from Literature</title>



<p> Love and seduction stories were the staple of the nineteenth-century novel in America, Britain, and Europe.  Either among the best authors or the nearly forgotten popular novelists, the plot lines generally involved a romance that does not go smoothly for a while and then ends happily, or a moral exemplum of a wicked man or woman who tries to trick an innocent, only to get what he or she deserves in the ending.  Often novels combined these narrative lines, with one conventional romantic couple played against a transgressive couple.  Even panoramic historical epics such as Tolstoy's <hi rend="italics">War and Peace</hi> or George Eliot's <hi rend="italics">Middlemarch</hi> built substantial plot lines on romances, engagements, and infidelities.  There were few nineteenth-century novels such as <hi rend="italics">Moby Dick</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Les Miserables</hi> that contained negligible elements of romance.  The truth was that love stories sold, and whaling adventures did not.
</p>
<p>The audience for novels greatly expanded in the nineteenth century, and middle-class women were important new clients in the reading public.  Two factors were important in making novels more accessible to a wider range of readers: one was the creation of lending libraries, and the other was the advances in printing that made it possible to mass-produce affordable magazines and books.  In a society in which marriage was still fundamental to the structure of social and economic life, tales of love and marriage, and its many pitfalls, were a compelling subject for readers.  The possibility that one could change one's class status through a good marriage added to the attraction of stories of pure but poor young women who lifted up by a wealthy, virtuous hero.
</p>
<p>In the hands of fine writers such as George Eliot, Gustave Flaubert, and Anthony Trollope, love stories could achieve a powerful and complex moral status.  Flaubert's Madame Bovary tells the story of a wife who loses everything in her uncontrollable search for <xlink ref="ls.0038">extramarital romance</xlink>.  Eliot's <hi rend="italics">Adam Bede</hi> gives us two sets of lovers whose actions illustrate a wide range of human strengths and weaknesses.  The prolific Trollope wrote of lovers of every variety and class in portraits that are rarely bound entirely by stereotypes.
</p>
<p>The preoccupation with love stories led to an increasing representation in literature of the erotic side of romance.  Many nineteenth-century novels that seem tame to modern readers in their lack of explicitness.  However, these narratives actually contain, in coded and sublimated form, an intense awareness of the eroticism of love.Blushing, rapid heartbeats, weak knees, "warm" kisses, even tears, convey the sexual excitement in the lover's embrace.In the United States, Hawthorne's novels, especially <hi rend="italics">The Blithedale Romance</hi>, are often saturated with sublimated sexual desire.  The portrait of Zenobia is memorable in its evocation of a voluptuous beauty who inspires in the queasy Coverdale "feverish fantasies."Preoccupied with Zenobia's sexuality, he concludes that "'Zenobia is a wife; Zenobia has lived and loved!  There is no folded petal, no latent dewdrop, in this perfectly developed rose!'" Such language should remind us that the nineteenth century was not without erotic desire, and that the physical body of the nineteenth century was not wired differently than it is today. 
</p>
<p>Popular novels, such as those from the pen of Mrs. E.D.E.N. Southworth or Percy St. John were often built on protracted seductions that maintained the sexual tension throughout the length of the novel.  The moment of Black Donald's attempted rape of the heroine is preceded by verbal sparring and a little supper of cheese and brandy.  He is plotting her rape, but she is plotting his murder; when she drops him through the trap door to the "horrible pit," she claims she dares not "rejoice" in her "awful" but "<xlink ref="ls.00067">complete victory</xlink>!" Another attempted rape figures in Elizabeth Helme's <hi rend="italics">The Farmer of Inglewood Forest</hi>, where the villain's brutal attack on Anna goes through many phases, including drugging her, striking her servant, and dragging Anna down the stairs to a waiting carriage where he plans to rape her.  As one might expect, however, the heroine and her faithful servant are saved from the dastardly act!  Given publishing conventions and public taste, a woman novelist could only take a scene like this so far without losing her respectability–and respectable readers.  
</p>
<p>Largely left out of the literature of love and seduction, whether in the canonical or the nearly forgotten novels, were lovers from the working class.  Writers tend to write about the society they know, and most of the authors were from the educated classes.  But it is also true that the stories of working-class courtship and seduction were less interesting to most readers.  Given the weight of marriage in terms of money and class status, the courtship and marriage of a working-class couple was out of the field of interest.  Working-class women could lose their reputations, but not their fortune or their "place" in society.  A notable exception to the rule was the story of Mary and Jem in Elizabeth Gaskell's novel of Manchester life, <xlink ref="ls.00192"><hi rend="italics">Mary Barton</hi></xlink>.The Bronte sisters portrayed more than one working governess, but these were educated women who were not from the working classes.  Women who worked in mills and factories did not go to balls or wear beautiful clothes, and they did not have class mobility.  Lovers in small towns and the rural scene were often the subject of fiction, however, as the class barriers among small farmers, village shop owners, and local clergy were more permeable than in the city. If a young woman from a modest home was educated and did not work outside the house, she might dream of marrying into a family of higher standing. Yet even here, the lines were drawn sharply as soon as the romance led a farm girl to dream of marrying into the local gentry, as happens with Ruby Ruggles in Trollope's <xlink ref="ls.00011"><hi rend="italics">The Way We Live Now</hi></xlink>. 
</p>
<p>Readers today might ask themselves what changes they can see from the dominant themes of nineteenth-century fiction and those in contemporary fiction.  If there are more novels today about something other than romance, how may we account for them?  Class in the United States and in Europe was organized differently, and it may reward critical examination to explore how differing social structures affected the stories of romance in different cultures.  The nature of the technology of printing and the audience profile influenced the form and content of nineteenth-century literary production.  The vast changes in the technology and the audience profile in our contemporary world have brought changes in form and content, too.  Changes in law have dramatically altered the status of women, and they have also opened the door to subjects of romance that were taboo in the nineteenth century.  Gay romances certainly occurred in the nineteenth century, but same-sex relationships were illegal and subject to severe sentences, as the case of Oscar Wilde in the 1890's should remind us.  Mixed-race marriages were illegal in most places, and the few stories of  interracial romance were, like <hi rend="italics">Quadroona </hi>and <hi rend="italics">Carmen</hi>, typically tales of exotic and sensual seductresses whose lives could only end in shame.  To what degree have stories of love and seduction registered these powerful changes in law, culture, and society? 
</p></div>

<div id="Art and Illustration"><title>Scenes from Art and Illustration</title>



<p>Nineteenth-century art was diverse in its schools and techniques, but the art of love and seduction was unrelentingly moralistic. In France, the great painters of the Impressionist school were painting luminous canvases filled with tourists, family scenes, and nature&#8212;gardens, fields, and water.  In England, however, the Pre-Raphaelite painters were painting women with an emphasis on their beauty of their flesh.  Pre-Raphaelites sought to unify the flesh and the spirit, and their paintings often contained highly moralistic "narratives" expressed through sensual bodies and gorgeous color and detail.  Dante Gabriel Rossetti and William Holman Hunt were perhaps the most successful artists of the school, and their portraits of women within moral melodramas created stereotypes of women that are still popular.  Viewers of Pre-Raphaelite paintings need to be aware that the artists frequently used symbolic details to provide moral explanations of the scene's narrative content.. Hunt's painting, <hi rend="italics"><xlink ref="ls.00100">The Awakening Conscience</xlink></hi>, is a good example. The painting pictures a young woman arising from the lap of a young man who is seated at the piano.  The details of the decor, such as the cat on the floor with the bird and the print on the wall of <hi rend="italics">Christ and the Woman Taken in Adultery</hi>, tell us that she is a kept woman, who has just undergone an epiphany about her moral transgressions. 
</p>
<p>In contrast, Edgar Degas's painting <hi rend="italics"><xlink ref="ls.00098">The Rape</xlink></hi> may puzzle us with its subdued colors and neat bedroom. The space and postures of the people in this interior setting may challenge us to define what kind of rape scene we are seeing.Augustus Egg's triptych, however, poses few problems of interpretation in this drama of a married <xlink ref="ls.00102">woman's infidelities</xlink>.  Since divorce was virtually unavailable to a woman who had been unfaithful, the ways to resolve adultery were largely limited to forgiveness or abandonment.  Egg's paintings stress the hurt to children, both the daughters the woman must leave behind and the unwanted child of her lover, who has, apparently, abandoned her, too.
</p>
<p>Illustration in journals and newspapers burgeoned in the nineteenth century due to innovations in print technology.  Much of popular illustration was rather crude in execution with lots of black ink and little subtlety in light and dark tones.  Still, illustrations could be quite effective in achieving their purposes, to portray some melodramatic scene from a popular novel or accompany an account of an actual crime or court case.  The contemporary popularity of films and television dramas of crime, complete with the most lurid scenes of violence, should make it easy for us to understand the fascination many people in the earlier century saw in these pictures.
</p>
<p> Illustrations from papers and journals were usually designed to sell papers and journals. They are often sentimental pictures of lovers, or exaggerated scenes of conflict between men and women, occasionally with children present.  When serialized novels are illustrated, a common choice of subject is lovers in a private moment, shown with greater detail than with the delicacy and indirection the reader would find in the text. Graphic artists seemed to have more leeway to portray the intimacies of the boudoir or lovers embracing than writers had to describe such scenes. Topics for illustration were often the moment of betrayal, the dangerous flirtation, or the first meeting. Other popular illustrations were satiric in nature, focusing on the absurdities of the marriage market.
</p>
<p>Some popular novels and volumes of poetry were lavishly illustrated, and the artistic quality of the illustrations increased with the seriousness of the literary work.  The drawings for Tennyson's "<xlink ref="ls.00174">Locksley Hall</xlink>" are more explicit than the text, but not indelicate.The illustrations from <hi rend="italics">Little Women</hi> are more wholesome, as befits the young women who were a substantial part of the audience for this popular book.
</p>
<p>Art and illustration provide representations of the nineteenth century's understanding of love and seduction, but we also need to interrogate these representations.  The commercial function of illustration and the mechanics of its production play an important role in determining content.  Are these illustrations meant to depict real-life scenes, or appeal to the audience?  In trying to understand love and seduction in the nineteenth century, art and illustration can be important, but we must look at these scenes with multiple perspectives from history and literature.
</p></div>

<div id="Historical Sources"><title>Scenes from Historical Sources</title>


<p>The historical documents of love and seduction in the nineteenth century make it very clear that nineteenth-century people had active sexual lives, knew about sexual behavior, talked about sex scandals, and viewed romance as the prime subject for entertainment. While almost no country in Europe or America was untouched by war in the nineteenth century, and while great changes occurred in the political and social structures, stories of love and seduction flourished through the century.  However, they often reflected, if obliquely, the changing historical world.  The role of print media made local scandals into national entertainments.  The Beecher scandal was so widely known in the United States and England that his name became a nominer for upstanding men who debauched women. Accounts of small town scandals of ministers who seduced a member of their church–an event that apparently happened with some frequency&#8212; referred to these men as a <xlink ref="ls.00019">"British Beecher"</xlink> or a <xlink ref="ls.00014">"Badgered Beecher."</xlink> 
</p>
<p>Documenting the intimate lives of people of centuries past is especially difficult because so little related to sex and romance produced documents that were preserved.  This is especially true of the working class, but historical research in the "underlife" of societies has increasingly turned up new evidence of how ordinary people lived.  The <hi rend="italics">National Police Gazette</hi> and other popular press organs tell us many things about people's behavior in love and seduction, and about the community responses to these matters.  Likewise, newspaper accounts of breach-of-promise cases and popular editions of court transcripts provide a view into the scandalous side of love in the nineteenth century.</p></div>


<div id="Commentary"><title>Commentary</title>



<p>In the last few decades the nineteenth century has been one of the most productive areas for interdisciplinary research in all kinds of topics of cultural study. Part of the reason is that the need to understand our own contemporary world requires us to understand better how it came into being. The changes in the twentieth century in art, ethics, ideology, politics, industrialism, and international relations had their origins in the previous century. The nineteenth century was also the first era in which mass communication and steam-driven travel made it possible for larger global communities to be in touch with the cultural and historical life of other countries.  Intellectual, political, and commercial life between Europe and the United States drew all these countries into closer contact, if not always into better understanding of each other.  Now, digital scholarship is allowing us to look at more aspects of interdisciplinary study of the century by combining images and texts in ways that were once prohibited by the economic constraints of print media.
</p>
<p>The scholarly commentaries in this section are focused on the theme of love and seduction at approximately mid-century, about 1840 to 1870.  They comment as well on related subjects such as adultery, prostitution, breach-of-promise, divorce, and the like, as well as providing critical treatments of such specific events as the Beecher-Tilton case or the love affair between Mabel Todd Loomis and Austen Dickinson. </p>
</div>

</text>