<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?><text xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/strict">


<div id="genintro"><h2>Icons of Liberty</h2>

<p class="intro">
The roots of the iconography of Liberty can be found in the Roman Republic (510-44 B.C.), where Liberty was envisioned as a Goddess.  She underwent a resurgence in the 16th and 17th centuries, when neoclassical artists bonded the iconography of Greek and Roman divinities with contemporary abstract ideas, such as Servitude and Concord.  But it was not until the late 18th century that the neoclassical image of Liberty became ubiquitous and politically consequential.  The neoclassical Liberty is always a female figure, usually partially nude, sometimes wearing the liberty cap (the Phrygian or slave cap of Rome that signified a slave had been freed), bearing the liberty pole, and crushing chains or the crowns of tyrants underfoot.  Icons of Liberty were everywhere in the popular consciousness and public images of the Age of Revolutions, especially in France and in the United States.  In the nineteenth century, representations of Liberty also flourished, but they multiplied, transformed, and evolved in curious ways.  Just as the nineteenth century had to come to terms with the after-effects of revolutionary ardor, so too did nineteenth-century culture find diverging and multiform ways of representing Liberty in post-revolutionary contexts (the most important republican experiments of the nineteenth century happened in France, Great Britain, and the United States; this module's materials are therefore concentrated on these three nation's representations of Liberty).
</p>

<p class="intro">  
Transformations of Liberty as an icon are complex in this period.  We find a particular tension between pastoral and martial images of Liberty; the difference seems to follow from the artist or writer's sense of the degree to which the goals of Liberty have been achieved or the degree that Liberty is threatened by current political realities.  Throughout the nineteenth century, the neoclassical image endured, but often merged with national symbols, such as the French Marianne, the British Britannia, or the Indian Princess or Columbia of the United States.  This change reflects the widely-held beliefs of citizens of France, Great Britain, and the United States that each country uniquely expressed a commitment to political liberty in its national character.  Dissenters and challengers to such self-affirming national propaganda also used the symbol of Liberty as a rebuke.  The icon of Liberty was important to abolitionist rhetoric and visual culture, as it was to British Chartists and other opposition groups bent on political reform.  In France, Liberty becomes a symbol of what the nation has lost through its post-revolutionary governance by emperors and monarchs, and when citizens took to the streets, as in the 1830 and 1848 Revolutions, Liberty was depicted as fighting side-by-side with the patriots at the barricades.  Those who fought for national liberty for other European proto-nationalities (such as Poland, Italy, and Wales) also employed the figure of Liberty in their cause.  Consequently, we find in various nineteenth-century political cartoons and illustrations that the French Empire, Austrian-Hungarian Empire, the British Empire, and the Franco-Prussian Empire all take their turns as the iconic tyrant who threatens Liberty or whose crowns or chains Liberty breaks.  The nineteenth-century use of Liberty as an icon testifies to her flexibility-she was claimed by almost all parties and all nations, and transformed for a multiplicity of ends, even though she was honored in reality far less frequently.
</p>

</div>



<div id="locations"><h2>Geographic Locations</h2>

<p class="intro">
The geographic locations in this section give the country of origin of materials cited in each of the genres and topics.  Many paintings, sculptures, and commentaries about the American Revolution, for example, originated in European countries, and Americans created many icons in honor of French contributions to the American cause.  This site will allow students to review the contributions from different countries to the genres and topics addressing the theme of Liberty.
</p>

</div>



<div id="topics"><h2>Topics</h2>

<p class="intro">
Iconic representations of Liberty as a concept are necessarily widespread in their use and understanding and evocative of larger meanings than may be accurately ascribed to a particular historical incident or figure.  The topics in this section were selected because they function as tropes for these wider implications.  The iconic power of Liberty, or Columbia as she was often called, of  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a> or <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a>, of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> or the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American</a> and <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=frenchrevolution">French Revolutions</a>, are abstract but culturally defining, extending in their emotional impact much beyond the historical moment out of which they arose.  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">George Washington</a> as icon has, for example, come to symbolize the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a>, Independence, the Founding Father of American government, love of country, honesty, the capitol, and the success of the new nation.  He is on dollar bills, noble monuments, and sale ads in newspapers on his birthday. Whole states and countless towns bear his name.  Icons are so prevalent in a culture that people may forget the details of their meaning but retain the emotional response to what they represent. These icons of Liberty influenced the imagination of the century,  coloring the interpretations cultures made of their history.  New generations in turn revised the meaning assigned to the icons.  The most durable icons retained their power throughout the nineteenth century, altering their emphasis as historical events gave new perspectives to the idea of Liberty.
</p>

</div>




<div id="genres"><h2>Genres</h2>

<p class="intro">
Liberty as a concept was so important to the nineteenth century's way of thinking that it shows up in almost every genre and in almost every country in North America and Europe.  The consequences of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American</a> and <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=frenchrevolution">French Revolutions</a> reverberated into the new century, and the revolutions in Europe in 1830 and 1848 kept the vitality of the theme of Liberty in the forefront of the cultural imagination.  In the United States the emblems of a new nation were taking shape, and icons of liberty were on coins, state seals, buildings, and statuary.  Cartoons in the press might debunk the iconic excesses, but engravings, paintings, and sculptures institutionalized and sanctioned the glorification of the Spirit of Liberty.  By mid-century the traditional icons of liberty, such as the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> and <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Bell</a>, took on new life in the literature of the antislavery movements.  American abolitionists adapted the rhetoric of the American Revolution to justify their cause in sermons, songs, and poems.  The historical documents from the nineteenth century include some of the most noted writers who have defined our philosophical and emotional understanding of liberty: <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=mill">John Stuart Mill</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=jefferson">Thomas Jefferson</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00035">Frederick Douglass</a>, <a href="">Margaret Fuller</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Abraham Lincoln</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00065">Ralph Waldo Emerson</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00063">Alex de Tocqueville</a>, and poems by <a href="">William Blake</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00062">William Wordsworth</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00013">Lord Byron</a>, and <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00015">Percy Bysshe Shelley</a>. 
</p>

<p class="intro">
Perhaps the most resonant visual  image of revolution was <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00117">Eugène Delacroix's "The 28th of July: Liberty Leading the People,"</a> which serves as the icon for this unit of Nineteenth-Century Studies: Resources for an Interdisciplinary Curriculum.  The central figure of Liberty, wearing the pileus (<a href="">cap</a>) and draped in the white of her purity,  is the revolutionary female, young, vital, and ready to storm the Bastille to crush the tyrant. Carrying the flag of France, she rallies the people to the battle.  Either in word or image the different genres represented in this section illustrate variations on this theme.
</p>  

</div>



<div id="coins"><h2>Coins</h2>

</div>




<div id="commentary"><h2>Commentary</h2>

</div>



<div id="fiction"><h2>Fiction</h2>

</div>



<div id="history"><h2>Historical Documents</h2>

</div>



<div id="illustrations"><h2>Illustrations and Cartoons</h2>

</div>




<div id="paintings"><h2>Paintings</h2>

</div>




<div id="poetry"><h2>Poetry</h2>

</div>  




<div id="sculpture"><h2>Sculpture</h2>

</div>





<div id="seals"><h2>Seals</h2>

</div>




<div id="american"><h2>United States</h2>

</div>





<div id="british"><h2>Britain</h2>

</div>



<div id="french"><h2>France</h2>

</div>



<div id="othercountry"><h2>Belgium, Ecuador, Germany, Italy, Spain and Wales</h2>
</div>




<div id="americanrevolution"><h2>American Revolution</h2>

<p class="intro">
The irony of the iconic power of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> is that its energy derived from its revolt against England, the country which was the source of most of its ideas about liberty and its practical knowledge of the forms of  self-government, constitutions or compacts, and checks and balances in government.  Even the icon of Columbia or Liberty revised the figure of Britannia, albeit Americanized even by the earliest colonials as an <a href="">Indian Princess</a> wearing a feathered tiara and tobacco leaf skirt.  In the early nineteenth century, the long and bloody struggle of the American Revolution was still a fresh memory evoked to hold the country true to the cause for which so much had been sacrificed.  Participation in the War was a litmus test for those seeking political power.  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=jefferson">Jefferson</a>, Adams, Madison, Franklin, Hamilton, and many others in the first twenty years after the War  had all helped win the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">Revolution</a>.  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a> and Franklin were especially well known in Europe, and their names and the invocation of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> were an inspiration first to the French and later in the century to revolutionaries across Europe.  After mid-century the American Revolution was increasingly evoked to justify ending slavery and extending citizen rights, meaning the vote, to Blacks and women.  <a href="">Frederick Douglass's "What to the Slave is the Fourth of July?"</a> points to the tension between slavery and the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> while also drawing on its iconic power to advance his cause.  <a href="">Whitman's "The Centenarian's Story"</a> explicitly connects the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> and the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a> as the country's two struggles for liberty and union.
</p>

</div>


<div id="civilwar"><h2>Civil War</h2>

<p class="intro">
The divisiveness of the American <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a> (1861-65) is reflected in the different iconic images of North and South.  For the North the magic names are most often <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a>, Grant, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00027">Gettysburg</a>; for the South they are most often Jefferson Davis, Robert E. Lee, and Vicksburg.  For African Americans, the names most often heard are John Brown, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00035">Frederick Douglass</a>, Harriet Tubman,  and the 54th Massachusetts Volunteers, the Black soldiers under General Robert Shaw.  Internationally, America's closest friends and allies, England and France, were also undecided about which side to support.  The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a> violently exposed the inherent conflict in the ideal of Liberty in the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> with the status of Blacks and women in the nineteenth century. Even so familiar an icon as the <a href="">Liberty Cap</a> became controversial, as Vivien Green Fryd's study of the United States Capitol shows us.  Jefferson Davis's objections to the cap register the South's rejection of the argument that the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> meant that all people had the right to be free.
</p>

<p class="intro">
The people of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a> were often grandchildren of the generation who fought the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> and created the Union.  For them the Revolution was not remote, but people in the North and South interpreted the legacy differently. Those supporting Union saw secession by the South as destroying a nation that had sacrificed too much in the Revolution to allow anyone to break it apart.  For them the fundamental outcome of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">Revolution</a> was at stake in the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a>.  The South also took their justification from the Revolution as a war premised on the inalienable right of people to declare their independence from a government they found oppressive.  For them the fundamental meaning of the Revolution was the right to secede from a country that was trying to destroy their way of life, as the American colonies had done from England.   Slavery was the fulcrum for this debate.  The genius of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00026">Emancipation Proclamation</a> was to unite the concept of union and the right to liberty for all in a way that cut the moral ground out from under the South. Symbolically the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00026">Emancipation Proclamation</a> placed the South outside the meaning of American history: the South did not have the right to secede if the way of  life it wanted to preserve was one that denied liberty to the people.
</p>

<p class="intro">
After 1865 <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> and the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00026">Emancipation Proclamation</a>, despite the merits of the prose and poetry which <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00037">Harold Holzer</a> discusses in the selection below, became the two transcendent icons of the Civil War.  In the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00027">Gettysburg Address</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> tied together the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> ("Four score and seven years ago. . ."), the "new nation," and the proposition "that all men are created equal."  The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00026">Emancipation Proclamation</a> was the symbolic document that proved that a new generation would again die to preserve those principles.
</p>

</div>




<div id="dissenting"><h2>Dissenting Voices</h2>

<p class="intro">
Throughout the nineteenth century, the political rhetoric conjoining national pride and liberty was open to critique, especially by abolitionists in Great Britain and the United States.  British pride in "British Liberty" was assailed by abolitionist urgings:  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00069">"LIBERTY, extend thy thund'ring voice / to Afric's scorching climes,"</a> while citizens of the United States were more than embarrassed by the gap between the founding rhetoric of political liberty and the status of slaves.  It was no coincidence that the anti-abolitionist political party created in 1844 was called the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00064">Liberty Party</a>.  As Frederick Douglass proclaimed, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00049">"This Fourth of July is yours, not mine."</a>  Defenders of slavery had to insist on more labored definitions of liberty; John Calhoun, for instance, argued that <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00054">"Liberty, . . . when forced on a people unfit for it, would instead of a blessing, be a curse, as it would in its reaction lead directly to anarchy-the greatest of all curses."</a>  Much later, other groups who felt disenfranchised within the United States would also critique the rhetoric of liberty, as did Saum Song Bo, a Chinese immigrant:  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00036">"The word liberty makes me think . . . that this country is the land of liberty for men of all nations except the Chinese."</a>  
</p>

<p class="intro">
Another dark side of liberty was unregulated capitalism, attacked by Victor Hugo in <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00006">Les Miserables</a>.  Even the Statue of Liberty could be understood as a figure of capitalistic excess, as an 1885 British <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00142">political cartoon</a> makes clear.  And conservative authors saw that revolutionary fervor in the service of Liberty could make for injustices; British authors such as Elizabeth Gaskell, Charles Dickens, and Anthony Trollope write of how the pursuit of an abstract ideal of liberty is at variance with individual liberty.  
</p>

</div>




<div id="emancipation">
<h2>Emancipation</h2>

<p class="intro">
Emancipatory movements built steam throughout the nineteenth century, affecting not just slaves but women, children in the labor force, and even animals in the anti-vivisection movement in England.  The century is dotted by dates that mark the end of slavery in one country after another, often as a result of war and revolution. In the 1790s France declared an end to slavery as part of the agenda of the Revolution, but plantation owners in Saint Dominique (later Haiti) vehemently protested. Toussaint L'Ouverture led the first successful slave revolt which resulted in the free republic of Saint Dominique in 1804.  In France, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=napoleon">Napoleon</a> reinstated slavery in 1801. France would not end slavery again until the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=rev1848">1848 Revolution</a>, a year that also saw the end of slavery in several French colonies such as Martinique.  England had abolished slave trade in 1807, and in 1833 it outlawed slavery throughout the British Empire. Alexander III, drawing on the prerogatives of a monarch, ended serfdom in Russia by edict in 1808.  In America, a catastrophic civil war raged for four years, killing more soldiers  than would die in any other American War until Viet Nam.  The 13th Amendment in 1865 formally ended slavery in the United States.  By 1880 slavery had ended throughout Europe and the Americas.
</p>

<p class="intro">
While the end of slavery was the most important and successful emancipatory movement of the century, movements were also underway for the rights of women.  In the United States and England women unsuccessfully sought the right to vote but did win greater protection under the law in matters of divorce.  The participation of women in Abolitionists efforts gave women both the analogy of the submission of women to the submission of the slave and the practical experience in activist causes in the name of liberty.
</p>

</div>



<div id="frenchrevolution"><h2>French Revolution</h2>

<p class="intro">
The French Revolution (1789-1799) had cataclysmic effects throughout the nineteenth century, as both model and warning.  In particular, the Revolution's cementing of nationalistic ideals with ideals of political liberty had repercussions throughout Europe as countries such as Poland, Italy, and Greece attempted to form fully-fledged nation-states based on the abstract principle of Liberty.  Conservative reaction, especially in Britain, was severe; even liberals such as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00076">Benjamin Constant</a> early in the century described the Revolution's events as "useless experiments."  British reaction was often given to seeing the Revolution's ardor for "Liberty" as a proven hypocrisy, given its culmination in the Reign of Terror (1792-1794) and in Napoleon's empire.  But French ardor for the revolutionary possibilities of liberty had dimmed as well, and bitterness such as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00006">Victor Hugo</a>'s was common.  The century's idealism and belief in progress, however, meant that views such as Hegel's (<a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00034">"the History of the World is nothing but the development of the Idea of Freedom"</a>) ultimately prevailed; by century's end, the American John Hay could see the violence of the French Revolution as sufficiently an artifact of an unthreatening past to write cheerfully of the necessity for <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00022">"riot and war"</a> to ensure Liberty.
</p>

</div>




<div id="gender"><h2>Gendered Icons</h2>

<p class="intro">
In keeping with her Roman and neoclassical roots, nineteenth-century Liberty is almost always represented as a young woman (one of the few male representations is of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00149">"Spirit of Liberty,"</a> not of Liberty itself).  Even though female citizens of democratic republics could not vote and had limited civic rights, the gender of Liberty seemed firmly fixed as female.  Ironically, throughout the nineteenth century, the female gender was understood by most people of both genders as innately disqualifying for full political equality.  The figure's partial nudity recalls Roman figures, but also suggests her invulnerability; even in martial contexts, it is plain that she can not be threatened by weapons, though she can <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00117">wield them</a>.  The icon of Liberty becomes more humanized from its origin as a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00074">"grim Roman goddess"</a> by the end of the eighteenth century, and this softer, more realistic Liberty is common in nineteenth-century representations.  In the United States, Liberty coinage, carried in the pockets of millions of Americans from the late 1790s through the 1830s, was modeled on a real woman, a society beauty, intellectual, and feminist named Anne Willing Bingham (1764-1801).  The American representations of Liberty kept the figure up-to-date with modern fashion; she wore the diaphanous gowns with empire waists made famous by the Empress Josephine in the 1810s, but by the first decade of the twentieth century could be found outfitted as a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00074">Gibson girl</a>.  Liberty also changed throughout the century by merging with national female symbols, such as Columbia (U.S.), Britannia (Great Britain), and Marianne (France).  She found competition from more masculine figures for national identity, such as the newly-created Brother Jonathon and Uncle Sam in the United States, Hercules in France, and John Bull in Great Britain.
</p>

</div>




<div id="icon"><h2>Iconography</h2>

<p class="intro">
Liberty's iconography goes back to Roman images of the goddess of Liberty.  She was commonly depicted as carrying a slave cap (or liberty cap) on a liberty pole.  The liberty cap is modeled on the soft, red cap worn by freed Roman slaves as a sign of their manumission.  The pole is sometimes a rod or scepter, and represents the authority of Liberty (often the cap is seen hoisted on the end of the pole, rather than worn on Liberty's head).  The Roman Liberty was often accompanied by a cat (an animal understood to serve no master), flying birds, a broken yoke, crushed or trodden down chains, crowns, or yokes.  The nineteenth century generally dispensed with the cat and birds, but held to the other iconic Roman elements, most often the liberty cap and liberty pole, often combined. The liberty bell and the Statue of Liberty are the most important nineteenth-century contributions to the iconography of Liberty.
</p>

</div>



<div id="individual"><h2>Individual Liberty</h2>

<p class="intro">
The democratic hope was that political liberty involved more than the right to vote; rather, political liberty would depend on deep-ingrained personal habits.  Constant had early in the century pointed out the desired form of political liberty-not merely the franchise, the achievement of the Greeks and Romans, but also liberty in the private realm:  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00076">"Among the ancients, the individual, almost always sovereign in public affairs, was a slave in all his private relations."</a>  Early republican thinkers argued that such private habits of liberty were necessary for the continuance of public liberty.  As Jefferson wrote, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00059">"Where every man is a sharer in the direction of his ward-republic, . . . not merely at an election one day in the year, but every day, . . . he will let the heart be torn out of his body sooner than his power be wrested from him by a Caesar or a Bonaparte."</a>  A continual theme of those who wrote about political liberty during the nineteenth century, thus, was the question of individual liberty, how the democratic citizen was to maintain attitudes of freedom in his individual consciousness.  Romantic writers endorsed connecting political liberty with the liberty of the subjective consciousness, as in Byron's "Sonnet in Chillon":  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00013">"Eternal spirit of the chainless Mind! / Brightest in dungeons, Liberty, thou art."</a>  The quintessential meditation on this issue is John Stuart Mill's On Liberty (1859), in which Mill laments that citizens of democratic states, having won political liberty, make themselves slaves to conformity and the "despotism of culture." For Mill, individual liberty depends <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00075">on individuality</a>.  But even Mill felt that not everyone was capable of this fullest sort of liberty, holding that liberty applies "only to human beings in the maturity of their faculties," not to members of races he felt were less developed.  This line of thinking was anticipated, of course, in pro-slavery arguments of the 1840s and 1850s; John Calhoun, for instance, held that there were necessary contractions of liberty for those "communities" with "moral deficiencies," <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00054">"so sunk in ignorance and vice as to be incapable of forming a conception of liberty."</a>
</p>

</div>




<div id="jefferson"><h2>Jefferson</h2>

<p class="intro">
Thomas Jefferson evokes the intellectual and philosophical underpinnings of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> and the Constitution of the United States.   As a member of the Continental Congress and the third president of the new nation, the stamp of his background in Enlightenment philosophy is sounded throughout the Declaration of Independence.  His presidency opened up two of the most important events in the expanding new nation: the Louisiana Purchase, which added the lands west of the Mississippi and ended the threat of war with France, and the expedition of Lewis and Clark, which mapped the first recorded exploration of the new territory extending to the Pacific Ocean.  Jefferson's writing in speeches, letters, and public documents articulated the basic principles of government by the people, freedom of the press, and the rights of man.  He was revered as an articulate man of vision who framed much of the philosophical context in the founding documents of the new nation and then acquired the land that opened the way to America's "Manifest Destiny" to extend from ocean to ocean.  His image as the intellectual behind the Revolution was further enhanced by his architectural designs for Monticello and the University of Virginia.
</p>

</div>



<div id="liberalism"><h2>Liberalism</h2>

<p class="intro">
Classical liberalism issues from Enlightenment principles, as articulated by such thinkers as Locke, Smith, and Hume, and is marked by its advocacy of individual responsibility, natural law, and property rights, as guaranteed by the state, the protector of individual freedoms.  In Great Britain, Liberalism was a political party that flourished in the second half of the nineteenth century, led by Gladstone, who served as Prime Minister at four different points between 1868 and 1894; Gladstonian liberalism promoted individual liberty, laissez faire economics, and social reform.  French liberalism held little political power in France until 1848, when the Second Republic began after the abdication of Louis Philippe, though liberal forces had fought unsuccessfully for political power even since Napoleon's hold on power in the late 1790's.  Liberalism in the United States became problematically opposed to republicanism in the early nineteenth century, as political thinkers tried to understand the relation of liberty to civic action, as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00028">Justman</a> argues.  Similarly important were distinctions between liberty and its uses; what is <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00030">"active liberty"</a>?  In Great Britain, liberalism and its reforms throughout the nineteenth century abated revolutionary fervor, especially the extension of the franchise through the various Reform Bills (1832, 1867, and 1884-85); liberals argued that greater liberty could be achieved by gradual change than by radical reform.
</p>

</div>



<div id="libertybell"><h2>Liberty Bell</h2>

<p class="intro">
The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> in Philadelphia rang out on July 8, 1776, at the first public reading of the Declaration of  Independence.  Historically bells had been used to carol glad tidings, or to warn of danger, or to call to arms, all of which traditions played a role in the symbolism of the tolling of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> on Independence Day. The association of bells with churches also helped to deify the cause of liberty, as <a href="">Margaret Fuller</a>'s essay, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00042">"The Liberty Bell,"</a> shows us. The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> was so powerful a symbol of the <a href="">American Revolution</a> that during the War the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> was hidden near Allentown, Pa., to keep the British from taking possession of it.  In the nineteenth century the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> assumed fresh symbolic power as an important symbol to the Abolitionists.  The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> symbolically rings out <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00038">"Slavery's knell" in John Pierpont</a>'s poem, just one of many poems addressed to the iconic power of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertybell">Liberty Bell</a> to embody the meaning of freedom from tyranny, including from the slave owners of the South.
</p>

</div>




<div id="libertycap"><h2>Liberty cap</h2>

<p class="intro">
The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> was derived from its classical origins as the Phrygian Cap, or pileus, associated with Paris and the Trojan War and later with the red cap worn by  freed slaves in ancient Rome.  As a symbol in the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American</a> and <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=frenchrevolution">French Revolutions</a>, the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> was often red.  In the United States the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> frequently appears atop the Liberty Pole., often red but sometimes with a pine tree motif.  Paul Revere is thought to have used the image of a cap on a stick as early as 1766, but in 1776 in Concord, Massachusetts, the first Revolutionaries flew the flag, either red or with a pine tree motif, on a pole extending up through a tree to summon the people to a meeting. The Liberty Pole and the Liberty Tree have overlapping meanings, but the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> on a Pole was the most frequently used icon. Often the pole is replaced by a sword, rifle, or flag in the hands of the Liberty figure, especially in France.   From the time of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=americanrevolution">American Revolution</a> the <a href="">Liberty Cap</a> was part of the symbolic dress of Liberty.  The French also used the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> to symbolize the revolutionary spirit.  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00117">Delacroix's "Liberty Leading the People"</a> wears the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a>. Drawing on its ancient associations with heroism and freedom, the Liberty Cap, with its simplicity of design, was also an appropriate emblem for revolutions fought to throw off the tyranny of kings.  Images of a female Liberty often show her dressed in youthful attire, a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> atop her flowing hair, and a crushed king, his crown toppled, under her feet. During the debates leading up to the American Civil War, the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=libertycap">Liberty Cap</a> became a controversial icon with supporters of slavery because of its ancient association with freeing slaves and its Revolutionary association with American liberty.
</p>

</div>


<div id="lincoln"><h2>Lincoln</h2>

<p class="intro">
The iconic meaning of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Abraham Lincoln</a> changed dramatically after his death and the end of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=civilwar">Civil War</a>.  In his lifetime, the public images of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> were often ridiculing and grotesque, but the face that during the Civil War was often featured as ugly and apelike was afterward portrayed as suffering and compassionate. The dead <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> became the emblem of the wounded Union which had risked all to free the slaves and preserve the union.  Like <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a>, in artistic renditions <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> ascended on clouds to the heavenly stars, themselves emblems of the celestial realm and the states in the union.  Above all <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=lincoln">Lincoln</a> became the Great Emancipator.  Many of the selections on this site contrast the actual circumstances of the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00026">Emancipation Proclamation</a> with the transfiguration of it into an icon of liberty.  <a href="">Walt Whitman</a>'s poem, <a href="">"When Lilacs Last in the Dooryard Bloom'd,"</a> about Lincoln's death characterized him in as "the lustrous and drooping star with the countenance full of woe. . . ."
</p>

</div>


<div id="mill"><h2>Mill</h2>

<p class="intro">
John Stuart Mill's On Liberty (1859) was one of the most influential treatises of the nineteenth century.  Mill himself was England's leading Victorian philosopher, a member of Parliament, and the most outspoken commentator on the meaning of individual liberty and women's rights.  On Liberty grows out of the assumption that history has already settled the question about the fight for national or governmental liberty but that the harder question is defining the extent and limits of individual liberty.  Mill warned of "the tyranny of the majority," a tyranny he saw as quite possible even in the liberty-loving United States of America.  Liberty in Mill's writing was more individualistic than social, and  his concern was that society itself not subject the individual to oppression for his opinions, tastes, and private choices, that citizens be free to act upon their opinions, and that only those acts which caused others harm should be controlled by the society.  Mill's views on liberty also informed his "The Subjection of Women."  This forceful call for the rights of women was seen by many of his time as a radical work.
</p>

</div>



<div id="napoleon"><h2>Napoleon</h2>

<p class="intro">
The French emperor and military genius, Napoleon Bonaparte (1769-1821), came to be understood by the later nineteenth century as a figure of tyranny, the icon of anti-Liberty.  Defeated finally in 1815 at Waterloo, Napoleon also came to represent the dangers of revolution, in that the French Revolution had spawned conditions in which his militarism and cult of personality could flourish; an 1803 <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00121">cartoon</a> shows one of the early invocations of the theme that Napoleon's command came at the expense of French liberty.  His name became a symbol of autocracy.  For example, Beethoven renamed his Third Symphony the Eroica rather than the Buonaparte on the occasion of Napoleon's crowning himself Emperor of the French in 1804, reportedly erupting, "So he is no more than a common mortal!  Now he too will tread under foot all the rights of man."  The nineteenth-century portrait of Napoleon also delimned him as an individualist rather than a nation-builder, as Chateaubriand's 1827 comparison of Napoleon with Washington makes clear:  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00072">"he steals from a nation its independence."</a>  British opinion was harshest, even from former admirers such as Shelley, who called him a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00016">"fallen tyrant."</a>  [00016].  Napoleon's signature <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00200">cocked hat</a> became an emblem used in antithesis to the liberty cap.
</p>

</div>




<div id="radicalism"><h2>Radicalism</h2>

<p class="intro">
Radicalism, the belief that there should be fundamental and sweeping social and political changes, often invoked the figure of Liberty, and those who opposed radicalism invoked Liberty in response.  In Great Britain, radicalism was associated with the failures of revolutionary France, and thus radicals never gained much political power, even after they gained public sympathy when they were violently opposed, as in the 1819 Peterloo Massacre.  Nationalism in Great Britain in the early part of the century tempered radicalism as well, given the military threat of Napoleonic France, although British patriots also argued that France's nationalism promoted radicalism, as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00070">Banks</a> argues.  Major figures of English Romanticism were swayed by radical thought, but Wordsworth turned away from radical ideas in the wake of the Reign of Terror.  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00067">Shelley</a>, however, remained a radical to the end.  Majority opinion saw radicalism as dangerous, as an <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00019">1819 George Cruikshank cartoon</a> makes plain (in it, radical reform is called the "oldest libertine").  When, later in the century, Trollope attempts to draw a sympathetic figure of a radical in <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00001">Rachel Ray</a>, he does so by drastically curtailing his definition of radicalism.  American radicalism throughout the nineteenth century focused on the revolutionary promise of the nation's founding documents, especially the Declaration of Independence; the greatest radical act of the century, Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, was also the act most in keeping with the Declaration's principles, though Lincoln had to arrange artfully the rhetoric and public presentation of the Proclamation to <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00037">diminish its radical content</a>.  
</p>

</div>




<div id="rev1830"><h2>1830 Revolutions</h2>

<p class="intro">
The increasingly autocratic and reactionary Charles X, the last of the Bourbon monarchy, was overthrown by three days of armed revolt in July, 1830, in the streets of Paris, to be replaced by the "Citizen King," the more liberal Louis Philippe of the Orleans family.  The July Revolution of 1830 in France inspired unsuccessful revolts in Italian and German states as well as in Belgium and Poland (for as the Austrian statesman Metternich pointed out, "When France sneezes, Europe catches cold"). The fervid idealism of the July Revolution was undercut, however, by the events' resemblance to the French Revolution, understood by now largely as a failure, as well as by its restoration of monarchy.  To some extent, the July Revolution was seen as a second chance to restore the ideals of the Revolution of 1789; as Hugo's man on the barricade exults, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00009">"France bears the sublime future with her, and this is the gestation of the nineteenth century."</a>  The July Revolution allowed for disparate use of the female neoclassic icon of Liberty; in some representations, she is a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00134">hapless victim of reactionary and/or foreign forces</a>, in others, an Amazonian warrior:  <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00117">Image 1</a>, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00125">Image 2</a>.
</p>

</div>



<div id="rev1848"><h2>1848 Revolutions</h2>

<p class="intro">
French disappointment with the "Citizen King," Louis Philippe, had grown almost from the moment of his instillation in 1830.  Citizens who missed la gloire of Napoleon's empire-building rallied around his nephew, Louis Napoleon Bonaparte (Bonaparte had already attempted coups against the government in both 1836 and 1840), who ultimately prevailed months after Louis Philippe's February, 1848 abdication (more democratic formulations of government had failed in the interim).  Louis Philippe's abdication set off ultimately unsuccessful revolts throughout the Hapsburg Empire, in Hungary, the Italian province of Lombardy, and Bohemia, while German nationalists were defeated as the German Confederation overseen by Austria and Prussia was re-established.  Popular images of the day from the side of liberalism-nationalism show the proletariat as virtuous, dismissing the fear of mob rule, what Hugo calls the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00008">"great spring of the red spectre."</a>  The imagery of the liberty cap is prominent, and it has become so familiar a symbol that various reformulations of the image can be made without an apparent loss of readerly understanding (we see it as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00123">Mount Etna</a>, as a <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00202">bell</a>, and as the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00124">headgear of a serpent</a>).  One interesting choice of iconography comes in an 1848 Italian <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00200">caricature</a> showing a nude female Liberty in slave cap chained to an enormous cocked hat, symbol of Napoleon's rule (French troops had just intervened to put down a revolt in Rome and the papal states).
</p>

</div>





<div id="statueofliberty"><h2>Statues of Liberty</h2>

<p class="intro">
The <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00042">Statue of Liberty</a> in New York Harbor is the most famous of many statues of liberty erected in the nineteenth century in the United States and France.  Both countries were linked by their revolutionary traditions and  shared a desire to memorialize the triumph of liberty.  As the nineteenth century evolved, elaborate monuments increasingly became the fashion. Statuary was not one of the colonial American arts, and many of the statues of liberty in the early nineteenth century were created by European artists, such as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00112">Enrico Causici</a> whose 1825 work is in the Capitol in Washington.  Most of the American statues of Liberty  were female, but the French versions were sometimes male, as <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00149">Auguste Dumont's "La Génie de la  Liberté"</a> for the Bastille Column.
</p>

<p class="intro">
French versions of Liberty were perhaps more nubile than American ones, but the essence of these early female statues of liberty were of youth, innocence, and triumph.  Occasionally, as in <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00125">Rude's head, "The Genius of Liberty,"</a> they are fierce. The popularity of France's gift to the United States of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00141">Frédéric-Auguste Bartholdi's "Liberty Enlightening the World" (1883)</a>, gradually altered the meaning of the statue of liberty in the United States.  American statues were not usually so grave or matronly.   Instead of the defiance of tyranny of a liberty cap and pole or the innocence of a youthful face and flowing hair, the <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00042">Statue of Liberty</a> was more mature, more classical in the folds of her drapery, and more suggestive of wisdom with her torch of enlightenment.  The nineteenth century was a time of mass immigration to America, and the addition of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00078">Emma Lazarus</a>'s lines, "Give me your tired, your poor, /Your huddled masses yearning to breathe free, /The wretched refuse of your teeming shore./Send these, the homeless, tempest-tost to me, / I lift my lamp beside the golden door!" solidified the symbolism of the United States as a refuge and a land of opportunity.
</p> 

<p class="intro">
Saum Song-Bo's dissenting voice, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00036">"A Chinese View of the Statue of Liberty,"</a> reminds us that not all immigrants were equally welcome.  The cartoon showing the Statue lifting her skirt to avoid the dirty masses illustrates the tensions between the ideal of a land of refuge and the reality of American cities feeling the pressure of large numbers of poor immigrants, a tension that still exits today. 
</p>

</div>




<div id="washington"><h2>Washington</h2>

<p class="intro">
<a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">George Washington</a> died December 14, 1799.  He was already a mythic figure in American history, and his idealization grew after his death.  The Commander and Chief of the Revolutionary War was known for his integrity and imposing figure-his height was measured on his deathbed at 6'3.5" inches-, and the larger than life status he had while living became a sacred presence in the iconography after his death.  Irish engraver <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00154">John James Barralet's "Apotheosis of Washington"</a> drew on the tradition in religious painting of the assumption of the Virgin Mary into Heaven.  Numerous other representations of Washington seated him on clouds, or dressed in full military regalia presenting the heroes of the Revolution to the Goddess of Liberty.  Like Benjamin Franklin, <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a> was widely admired in Europe, and both in France and America he became first a symbol of the success of the American Revolution and then the symbol of the stability and influence of the new democratic country.  The extraordinary popularity of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a> as an icon of American success, like that of the <a href="">Statue of Liberty</a> as a symbol of freedom and opportunity, led to many commercialized uses of his image and debasements in the myth.  Stories of his life were sentimentalized into fables of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=washington">Washington</a> as the Father of Our Country who would not lie about chopping down the cherry tree. <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/content.php?id=lby.00072">Chateaubriand</a>'s memoir in 1827 of meeting Washington counters the trivialization,  and his comparison of <a href="http://libr.unl.edu:2000/liberty/explore/themes.php?name=napoleon">Napoleon Bonaparte</a> as a man who stole from a nation its independence and Washington as a man who raised a nation to its independence elevates Washington to the highest realms of historical importance:    "Seek out the unknown forests where the sword of Washington shone, what will you find there?  Tombs?  No, a world!  Washington has left the United States as his trophy on the field of battle."
</p>

</div>


<div id="nations"><h2>Nations</h2>

<p class="intro">
The most important republican experiments of the nineteenth century happened in France, Great Britain, and the United States.  Many of the European nationalities we recognize today had no national unity or freedom-for example, Italy, Germany, Poland, Hungary, and Greece.  Their citizens, however, also yearned to make the experiment with republican liberty or at the very least to throw off imperial chains, and political cartoons and public discourse of other European nations or proto-nations displays the iconography of Liberty.  Switzerland is invoked by progressives, liberals, and Romantics as a model of national liberty, though its liberty was achieved as far back as 1291 and defended resoundingly against the Austrians in 1386.  In the nineteenth century, Germany's states were not unified; Prussia, a German state, was first among equals, and was allied with Austria, ruled by the Hapsburg dynasty.  Eastern Europe was ruled by the Austrian, Russian, and Ottoman empires; when Poland tried at various points during the century to revolt against its Russian overseer, it was brutally suppressed, most thoroughly in 1832 and 1865.  Italian city-states were ruled by kings whose rule was ratified by the 1815 Congress of Vienna, though northern Italy was governed by Austria.  Movements for Italian national independence grew through the century; Austria put down the first major revolt by the Carbonari in 1820.  The cause of Greek independence from the Ottoman empire famously lured Byron to join the armed conflict, though he died of fever in 1824 before he ever took arms against the Turks, who suppressed Greek revolt thoroughly by 1827.  And throughout the century, nationalist movements in Scotland, Ireland, and Wales continued to call for their liberty from England's imperial rule.
</p>

</div>

<div id="spain"><h2>Spain</h2>

</div>

<div id="italy"><h2>Italy</h2>

</div>

<div id="poland"><h2>Poland</h2>

</div>

<div id="russia"><h2>Russia</h2>

</div>

<div id="switzerland"><h2>Switzerland</h2>

</div>

<div id="wales"><h2>Wales</h2>

</div>

</text>