<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00196</field>
      <field name="title">Eugenie Grandet</field>
      <field name="setting">boudoir</field>
      <field name="nationality">french</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene Two:  Eugénie foolishly gives her savings to her cousin"Dear cousin!" whispered Eugenie, throwing down the letter and
         running
         softly back to her room, carrying one of the lighted candles. A thrill
         of pleasure passed over her as she opened the drawer of an old oak
         cabinet, a fine specimen of the period called the Renaissance, on
         which could still be seen, partly effaced, the famous royal
         salamander. She took from the drawer a large purse of red velvet with
         gold tassels, edged with a tarnished fringe of gold wire,—a relic
         inherited from her grandmother. She weighed it proudly in her hand,
         and began with delight to count over the forgotten items of her little
         hoard. First she took out twenty portugaises, still new, struck in
         the reign of John V., 1725, worth by exchange, as her father told her,
         five lisbonnines, or a hundred and sixty-eight francs, sixty-four
         centimes each; their conventional value, however, was a hundred and
         eighty francs apiece, on account of the rarity and beauty of the
         coins, which shone like little suns. Item, five genovines, or five
         hundred-franc pieces of Genoa; another very rare coin worth
         eighty-seven francs on exchange, but a hundred francs to collectors.
         These had formerly belonged to old Monsieur de la Bertelliere. Item,
         three gold quadruples, Spanish, of Philip V., struck in 1729, given
         to her one by one by Madame Gentillet, who never failed to say, using
         the same words, when she made the gift, "This dear little canary, this
         little yellow-boy, is worth ninety-eight francs! Keep it, my pretty
         one, it will be the flower of your treasure." Item (that which her
         father valued most of all, the gold of these coins being twenty-three
         carats and a fraction), a hundred Dutch ducats, made in the year 1756,
         and worth thirteen francs apiece. Item, a great curiosity, a species
         of medal precious to the soul of misers,—three rupees with the sign
         of the Scales, and five rupees with the sign of the Virgin, all in
         pure gold of twenty-four carats; the magnificent money of the Great
         Mogul, each of which was worth by mere weight thirty-seven francs,
         forty centimes, but at least fifty francs to those connoisseurs who
         love to handle gold. Item, the napoleon of forty francs received the
         day before, which she had forgotten to put away in the velvet purse.
         This treasure was all in virgin coins, true works of art, which
         Grandet from time to time inquired after and asked to see, pointing
         out to his daughter their intrinsic merits,—such as the beauty of the
         milled edge, the clearness of the flat surface, the richness of the
         lettering, whose angles were not yet rubbed off.Eugenie gave no thought to these rarities, nor to her father's mania
         for them, nor to the danger she incurred in depriving herself of a
         treasure so dear to him; no, she thought only of her cousin, and soon
         made out, after a few mistakes of calculation, that she possessed
         about five thousand eight hundred francs in actual value, which might
         be sold for their additional value to collectors for nearly six
         thousand. She looked at her wealth and clapped her hands like a happy
         child forced to spend its overflowing joy in artless movements of the
         body. Father and daughter had each counted up their fortune this
         night,—he, to sell his gold; Eugenie to fling hers into the ocean of
         affection. She put the pieces back into the old purse, took it in her
         hand, and ran upstairs without hesitation. The secret misery of her
         cousin made her forget the hour and conventional propriety; she was
         strong in her conscience, in her devotion, in her happiness.As she stood upon the threshold of the door, holding the candle
         in one
         hand and the purse in the other, Charles woke, caught sight of her,
         and remained speechless with surprise. Eugenie came forward, put the
         candle on the table, and said in a quivering voice:"My cousin, I must beg pardon for a wrong I have done you; but God
         will pardon me—if you—will help me to wipe it out.""What is it?" asked Charles, rubbing his eyes."I have read those letters."Charles
         colored."How did it happen?" she continued; "how came I here? Truly, I do not
         know. I am tempted not to regret too much that I have read them; they
         have made me know your heart, your soul, and—""And what?" asked Charles."Your plans, your need of a sum—""My dear cousin—""Hush,
         hush! my cousin, not so loud; we must not wake others. See,"
         she said, opening her purse, "here are the savings of a poor girl who
         wants nothing. Charles, accept them! This morning I was ignorant of
         the value of money; you have taught it to me. It is but a means, after
         all. A cousin is almost a brother; you can surely borrow the purse of
         your sister."Eugénie, as much a woman as a young girl, never dreamed of refusal;
         but her cousin remained silent."Oh! you will not refuse?" cried Eugénie, the beatings of whose heart
         could be heard in the deep silence.Her cousin's hesitation mortified her; but the sore need of his
         position came clearer still to her mind, and she knelt down."I will never rise till you have taken that gold!" she said. "My
         cousin, I implore you, answer me! let me know if you respect me, if
         you are generous, if—"As he heard this cry of noble distress the young man's tears fell upon
         his cousin's hands, which he had caught in his own to keep her from
         kneeling. As the warm tears touched her, Eugénie sprang to the purse
         and poured its contents upon the table."Ah! yes, yes, you consent?" she said, weeping with joy. "Fear
         nothing, my cousin, you will be rich. This gold will bring you
         happiness; some day you shall bring it back to me,—are we not
         partners? I will obey all conditions. But you should not attach such
         value to the gift."Charles was at last able to express his feelings."Yes, Eugénie; my soul would be small indeed if I did
         not accept. And
         yet,—gift for gift, confidence for confidence.""What do you mean?" she said, frightened."Listen, dear cousin; I have here—"
         He interrupted himself to point
         out a square box covered with an outer case of leather which was on
         the drawers. "There," he continued, "is something as precious to me as
         life itself. This box was a present from my mother. All day I have
         been thinking that if she could rise from her grave, she would herself
         sell the gold which her love for me lavished on this dressing-case;
         but were I to do so, the act would seem to me a sacrilege." Eugénie
         pressed his hand as she heard these last words. "No," he added, after
         a slight pause, during which a liquid glance of tenderness passed
         between them, "no, I will neither sell it nor risk its safety on my
         journey. Dear Eugénie, you shall be its guardian. Never did friend
         commit anything more sacred to another. Let me show it to you."He went to the box, took it from its outer coverings, opened
         it, and
         showed his delighted cousin a dressing-case where the rich workmanship
         gave to the gold ornaments a value far above their weight."What you admire there is nothing," he said, pushing a secret spring
         which opened a hidden drawer. "Here is something which to me is worth
         the whole world." He drew out two portraits, masterpieces of Madame
         Mirbel, richly set with pearls."Oh, how beautiful! Is it the lady to whom you wrote that—""No," he said, smiling; "this is
         my mother, and here is my father,
         your aunt and uncle. Eugénie, I beg you on my knees, keep my treasure
         safely. If I die and your little fortune is lost, this gold and these
         pearls will repay you. To you alone could I leave these portraits; you
         are worthy to keep them. But destroy them at last, so that they may
         pass into no other hands." Eugénie was silent. "Ah, yes, say yes! You
         consent?" he added with winning grace.Hearing the very words she had just used to her cousin now addressed
         to herself, she turned upon him a look of love, her first look of
         loving womanhood,—a glance in which there is nearly as much of
         coquetry as of inmost depth. He took her hand and kissed it."Angel of purity! between us two money is nothing, never can be
         anything. Feeling, sentiment, must be all henceforth.""You are like your mother,—was her voice as soft as yours?""Oh! much
         softer—""Yes, for you," she said, dropping her eyelids. "Come, Charles, go to
         bed; I wish it; you must be tired. Good-night." She gently disengaged
         her hand from those of her cousin, who followed her to her room,
         lighting the way. When they were both upon the threshold,—"Ah!" he said, "why am I ruined?""What matter?—my father is rich;
         I think so," she answered."Poor child!" said Charles, making a step into her room and leaning
         his back against the wall, "if that were so, he would never have let
         my father die; he would not let you live in this poor way; he would
         live otherwise himself.""But he owns Froidfond.""What is Froidfond worth?""I don't know; but he has Noyers.""Nothing but a
         poor farm!""He has vineyards and fields.""Mere nothing," said Charles disdainfully. "If your father had only
         twenty-four thousand francs a year do you suppose you would live in
         this cold, barren room?" he added, making a step in advance. "Ah!
         there you will keep my treasures," he said, glancing at the old
         cabinet, as if to hide his thoughts."Go and sleep," she said, hindering his entrance into the disordered
         room.Charles stepped back, and they bid each other good-night with a mutual
         smile.Both fell asleep in the same dream; and from that moment the youth
         began to wear roses with his mourning. The next day, before breakfast,
         Madame Grandet found her daughter in the garden in company with
         Charles. The young man was still sad, as became a poor fellow who,
         plunged in misfortune, measures the depths of the abyss into which he
         has fallen, and sees the terrible burden of his whole future life. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>