<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00031</field>
      <field name="title">Madame Bovary</field>
      <field name="setting">carriage</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="nationality">french</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene Three: 
         Emma and Leon in the Zigzagging CarriageIt was a
         beautiful summer morning. Silver plate sparkled in the jeweller's windows, and
         the light falling obliquely on the cathedral made mirrors of the corners of the
         grey stones; a flock of birds fluttered in the grey sky round the trefoil
         bell-turrets; the square, resounding with cries, was fragrant with the flowers
         that bordered its pavement, roses, jasmines, pinks, narcissi, and tube-roses,
         unevenly spaced out between moist grasses, catmint, and chickweed for the
         birds; the fountains gurgled in the centre, and under large umbrellas, amidst
         melons, piled up in heaps, flower-women, bare-headed, were twisting paper round
         bunches of violets. The young man
         took one. It was the first time that he had bought flowers for a woman, and his
         breast, as he smelt them, swelled with pride, as if this homage that he meant
         for another had recoiled upon himself. But he was
         afraid of being seen; he resolutely entered the church. The beadle, who was
         just then standing on the threshold in the middle of the left doorway, under
         the "Dancing Marianne," with feather cap, and rapier dangling against
         his calves, came in, more majestic than a cardinal, and as shining as a saint
         on a holy pyx. He came towards
         Léon, and, with that smile of wheedling benignity assumed by ecclesiastics
         when they question children— "The
         gentleman, no doubt, does not belong to these parts?  The gentleman would like
         to see the curiosities of the church?" "No!"
         said the other. And he first
         went round the lower aisles. Then he went out to look at the Place. Emma was
         not coming yet. He went up again to the choir. The nave was
         reflected in the full fonts with the beginning of the arches and some portions
         of the glass windows. But the reflections of the paintings, broken by the
         marble rim, were continued farther on upon the flag-stones, like a
         many-coloured carpet. The broad daylight from without streamed into the church
         in three enormous rays from the three opened portals. From time to time at the
         upper end a sacristan passed, making the oblique genuflexion of devout persons
         in a hurry. The crystal lustres hung motionless. In the choir a silver lamp was
         burning, and from the side chapels and dark places of the church sometimes rose
         sounds like sighs, with the clang of a closing grating, its echo reverberating
         under the lofty vault. Léon with solemn steps
         walked along by the walls. Life had never seemed so good to him. She would come
         directly, charming, agitated, looking back at the glances that followed her,
         and with her flounced dress, her gold eyeglass, her thin shoes, with all sorts
         of elegant trifles that he had never enjoyed, and with the ineffable seduction
         of yielding virtue. The church like a huge boudoir spread around her; the
         arches bent down to gather in the shade the confession of her love; the windows
         shone resplendent to illumine her face, and the censers would burn that she
         might appear like an angel amid the fumes of the sweet-smelling odours. But she did not
         come. He sat down on a chair, and his eyes fell upon a blue stained window
         representing boatmen carrying baskets. He looked at it long, attentively, and
         he counted the scales of the fishes and the button-holes of the doublets, while
         his thoughts wandered off towards Emma. The beadle,
         standing aloof, was inwardly angry at this individual who took the liberty of
         admiring the cathedral by himself. He seemed to him to be conducting himself in
         a monstrous fashion, to be robbing him in a sort, and almost committing
         sacrilege. But a rustle of
         silk on the flags, the tip of a bonnet, a lined cloak it was she! Léon rose and ran to meet her. Emma was pale.
         She walked fast. "Read!"
         she said, holding out a paper to him. "Oh, no!" And she
         abruptly withdrew her hand to enter the chapel of the Virgin, where, kneeling
         on a chair, she began to pray. The young man
         was irritated at this bigot fancy; then he nevertheless experienced a certain
         charm in seeing her, in the middle of a rendezvous, thus lost in her devotions,
         like an Andalusian marchioness; then he grew bored, for she seemed never coming
         to an end. Emma prayed, or
         rather strove to pray, hoping that some sudden resolution might descend to her
         from heaven; and to draw down divine aid she filled full her eyes with the
         splendours of the tabernacle. She breathed in the perfumes of the full-blown
         flowers in the large vases, and listened to the stillness of the church, that
         only heightened the tumult of her heart. She rose, and
         they were about to leave, when the beadle came forward, hurriedly saying: "Madame,
         no doubt, does not belong to these parts?  Madame would like to see the
         curiosities of the church?" "Oh,
         no!" cried the clerk. "Why
         not?" said she. For she clung with her expiring virtue to the Virgin, the
         sculptures, the tombs anything. Then, in order
         to proceed "by rule," the beadle conducted them right to the entrance
         near the square, where, pointing out with his cane a large circle of
         block-stones without inscription or carving: "This,"
         he said majestically, "is the circumference of the beautiful bell of
         Ambroise. It weighed forty thousand pounds. There was not its equal in all Europe. The workman who cast it died of the joy—"
         "Let us go
         on," said Léon. The old fellow
         started off again; then, having got back to the chapel of the Virgin, he
         stretched forth his arm with an all-embracing gesture of demonstration, and,
         prouder than a country squire showing you his espaliers, went on: "This
         simple stone covers Pierre de Brézé, lord of Varenne and of Brissac, grand
         marshal of Poitou, and governor of Normandy, who died at the battle of
         Montlhery on the 16th of July, 1465." Léon bit his lips, fuming. "And on
         the right, this gentleman all encased in iron, on the prancing horse, is his
         grandson, Louis de Breze, lord of Breval and of Montchauvet, Count de
         Maulevrier, Baron de Mauny, chamberlain to the king, Knight of the Order, and
         also governor of Normandy; died on the 23rd of July, 1531—a Sunday, as the
         inscription specifies; and below, this figure, about to descend into the tomb,
         portrays the same person. It is not possible, is it, to see a more perfect
         representation of annihilation?" Madame Bovary
         put up her eyeglasses. Léon, motionless, looked at her, no longer even
         attempting to speak a single word, to make a gesture, so discouraged was he at
         this two-fold obstinacy of gossip and indifference. The everlasting
         guide went on: "Near him,
         this kneeling woman who weeps is his spouse, Diane de Poitiers, Countess de
         Brézé, Duchess de Valentinois, born in 1499, died in 1566, and to the left, the
         one with the child is the Holy Virgin. Now turn to this side; here are the
         tombs of the Ambroise. They were both cardinals and archbishops of Rouen. That one was minister under Louis XII. He did a
         great deal for the cathedral. In
         his will he left thirty thousand gold crowns for the poor." And without
         stopping, still talking, he pushed them into a chapel full of balustrades, some
         put away, and disclosed a kind of block that certainly might once have been an
         ill-made statue. "Truly,"
         he said with a groan, "it adorned the tomb of Richard Coeur de Lion, King
         of England and Duke of Normandy. It was the Calvinists, sir, who reduced it to
         this condition. They had buried it for spite in the earth, under the episcopal
         seat of Monsignor. See! this is the door by which Monsignor passes to his
         house. Let us pass on quickly to see the gargoyle windows." But Léon hastily took some silver from his pocket and seized Emma's
         arm. The beadle stood
         dumfounded, not able to understand this untimely munificence when there were
         still so many things for the stranger to see. So calling him back, he cried: "Sir! sir!
         The steeple! the steeple!" "No, thank
         you!" said Léon. "You are
         wrong, sir! It is four hundred and forty feet high, nine less than the great
         pyramid of Egypt. It is all cast; it—" Léon was fleeing, for it
         seemed to him that his love, that for nearly two hours now had become petrified
         in the church like the stones, would vanish like a vapour through that sort of
         truncated funnel, of oblong cage, of open chimney that rises so grotesquely
         from the cathedral like the extravagant attempt of some fantastic brazier. "But where
         are we going?" she said. Making no
         answer, he walked on with a rapid step; and Madame Bovary was already, dipping
         her finger in the holy water when behind them they heard a panting breath
         interrupted by the regular sound of a cane. Léon turned back. "Sir!"
         "What is
         it?" And he
         recognised the beadle, holding under his arms and balancing against his stomach
         some twenty large sewn volumes. They were works "which treated of the
         cathedral." "Idiot!"
         growled Léon, rushing out of the church. A lad was
         playing about the close. "Go and
         get me a cab!" The child
         bounded off like a ball by the Rue Quatre-Vents; then they were alone a few
         minutes, face to face, and a little embarrassed. "Ah! Léon! Really—I don't know—if I ought," she whispered. Then with a more
         serious air,
         "Do you know, it is very improper—" "How
         so?" replied the clerk. "It is done at Paris." And that, as an
         irresistible argument, decided her. Still the cab
         did not come. Léon was afraid she might go back into the church. At last the
         cab appeared. "At all
         events, go out by the north porch," cried the beadle, who was left alone
         on the threshold, "so as to see the Resurrection, the Last Judgment, Paradise, King David, and the Condemned in Hell-flames."
         "Where to,
         sir?" asked the coachman. "Where you
         like," said Léon, forcing Emma into the cab. And the
         lumbering machine set out. It went down the Rue Grand-Pont, crossed the Place
         des Arts, the Quai Napoléon, the Pont Neuf, and stopped short before the statue
         of Pierre Corneille. "Go
         on," cried a voice that came from within. The cab went on
         again, and as soon as it reached the Carrefour Lafayette, set off down-hill,
         and entered the station at a gallop. "No,
         straight on!" cried the same voice. The cab came
         out by the gate, and soon having reached the Cours, trotted quietly beneath the
         elm-trees. The coachman wiped his brow, put his leather hat between his knees,
         and drove his carriage beyond the side alley by the meadow to the margin of the
         waters. It went along
         by the river, along the towing-path paved with sharp pebbles, and for a long
         while in the direction of Oyssel, beyond the isles. But suddenly it
         turned with a dash across Quatremares, Sotteville, La Grande-Chaussée, the Rue
         d'Elbeuf, and made its third halt in front of the Jardin des Plantes. "Get on,
         will you?" cried the voice more furiously. And at once
         resuming its course, it passed by Saint-Sever, by the Quai'des Curandiers, the
         Quai aux Meules, once more over the bridge, by the Place du Champ de Mars, and
         behind the hospital gardens, where old men in black coats were walking in the
         sun along the terrace all green with ivy. It went up the Boulevard Bouvreuil,
         along the Boulevard Cauchoise, then the whole of Mont-Riboudet to the Deville
         hills. It came back;
         and then, without any fixed plan or direction, wandered about at hazard. The
         cab was seen at Saint-Pol, at Lescure, at Mont Gargan, at La Rougue-Marc and
         Place du Gaillardbois; in the Rue Maladrerie, Rue Dinanderie, before
         Saint-Romain, Saint-Vivien, Saint-Maclou, Saint-Nicaise in front of the
         Customs, at the "Vieille Tour," the "Trois Pipes," and the
         Monumental Cemetery. From time to time the coachman, on his box cast despairing
         eyes at the public-houses. He could not understand what furious desire for
         locomotion urged these individuals never to wish to stop. He tried to now and
         then, and at once exclamations of anger burst forth behind him. Then he lashed
         his perspiring jades afresh, but indifferent to their jolting, running up
         against things here and there, not caring if he did, demoralised, and almost
         weeping with thirst, fatigue, and depression. And on the
         harbour, in the midst of the drays and casks, and in the streets, at the
         corners, the good folk opened large wonder-stricken eyes at this sight, so
         extraordinary in the provinces, a cab with blinds drawn, and which appeared
         thus constantly shut more closely than a tomb, and tossing about like a vessel.
         Once in the
         middle of the day, in the open country, just as the sun beat most fiercely
         against the old plated lanterns, a bared hand passed beneath the small blinds
         of yellow canvas, and threw out some scraps of paper that scattered in the wind,
         and farther off lighted like white butterflies on a field of red clover all in
         bloom. At about six
         o'clock the carriage stopped in a back street of the Beauvoisine Quarter, and a
         woman got out, who walked with her veil down, and without turning her head.  
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>