<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00016</field>
      <field name="title">from "The Case of Henry Ward Beecher: Opening Address by Benjamin F. Tracy, of counsel for the Defendant"
         
         
      </field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">history</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">popularpress</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="text">Excerpts from Benjamin Tracy's Opening Arguments for the Defense in the Beecher-Tilton Case WEDNESDAY,
         FEBRUARY 24, 1875.87th
         DAY.Mr. Tracy—May it please the court,
         gentlemen of the jury: The time having
         arrived when the defendant is permitted to be heard in his own behalf, my
         associates have assigned to me the duty of stating his case to this Honorable
         Court and to you. I am sure, gentlemen, when you consider for whom and in whose
         presence I speak, you will believe that it is for me an occasion of great
         personal embarrassment. When I think of the interests involved in this
         trial and the effects which may follow it, when I contemplate the deep and
         painful anxiety which it everywhere excites, I am oppressed by the burden of responsibility
         which the over-kindness of my associates has laid upon me, and would gladly
         surrender it to other and abler hands. Nothing, indeed, prevents me from sinking
         beneath the task I have undertaken, but a clear conviction of the absolute
         innocence of my client, and the assurance of my eminent associates that his
         case is too strong to be injured by my unskillful advocacy. And moreover, I am
         assured by the knowledge that comes to me from every quarter, that, in my
         effort to make his innocence as plain to you and to the world as it has long
         been to his counsel and his people, I have the universal sympathy of mankind.
         The magnitude
         and importance of the questions here involved, cannot be over-estimated, for
         they go down to the very foundations of our social, moral, and religious life.
         If the effect of your decision in this case could be limited to determining
         whether the plaintiff has suffered a wrong at the hands of the defendant, for
         which he is entitled to be compensated in money, this trial would not excite
         the widespread interest which has attached to it from the beginning, and which
         must follow. But, gentlemen, I need not remind you how utterly impossible it is
         to circumscribe the effect of this trial within such narrow limits. Either
         this defendant is to go forth from this courtroom vindicated by your verdict,
         or you and I and all who take part in this day's work are actors in one of the
         greatest moral tragedies which has ever occupied the stage of human life. Look
         at it as we may, it is impossible to separate the defendant from his representative character.
         Not
         that I would endorse the remarkable statement of the plaintiff's counsel in his opening, that "upon the result of your verdict,
         to a
         very large extent, will depend the integrity of the Christian religion."  God
         forbid that the integrity of the Christian religion should depend upon the
         character or the fortunes of any man, however learned, eloquent or devout. The
         Christian religion is founded upon the eternal rock of God's nature and God's
         decree. It is from everlasting to everlasting: and will abide when the remotest
         records of future history shall have faded from the annals of time, and the
         heavens "shall have, been rolled together as a scroll." My
         client expects no other support from the Christian religion than such as may be
         found in its promises. He takes his stand here alone upon his own integrity,
         sustained only by God and the justice of his cause. And yet, gentlemen, I
         repeat, you cannot consider him altogether without reference to that sacred
         faith of which he has been for a long time one of the most honored ministers,
         which would acquire lustre in his vindication, and which could not but be
         deeply wounded in his fall.HENRY
         WARD BEECHERThe son of one of the most eminent
         clergymen of the last generation, a member of a large family of which all the
         men are clergymen and all the women authors of repute—a family, let me say,
         gentlemen, on whose fair fame the shadow of reproach has never rested hitherto—the defendant early devoted himself to the
         self-denying pursuit of a minister
         of the Gospel. For it was no bed of roses in a luxurious abode that he spread
         for himself; he made no use of a dominant family influence to secure the
         refinements and privileges of a wealthy city parish. He struck boldly out
         into the wilds and hardships of the West. He rode the rough circuit
         of a home missionary life. With his own hands he made the fires, swept the
         floors and rang the bell in his forest church; with his own hands, assisted
         only by the faithful wife who stood by him then, and who—to the honor of
         womanhood—stands by him to-day, he ministered to the necessities of his
         forest home. When the thunders of his manly eloquence
         had reached even this distant coast, and the imperative demand of the church had
         summoned him to a wider sphere of action, he left neither his simplicity nor
         his independence behind. He has been the same genuine, true-hearted, unaffected
         man here that he was in the West. In the midst of all the refinements and
         luxuries of city life, his motto has been that of the great apostle he so much
         resembles, "I know how to be abased, and I know how to abound." To
         some who, in the early days, when he was less known than now, undertook to
         control his utterances by threatening loss of place, he made this memorable
         reply: "You may unseat me, but you cannot control me. I came from
         the woods, and I can go back to the woods again."
         This man, so
         introduced to us, has wrought and taught for near thirty years in our midst. He
         is no longer a stranger, and no longer a new acquaintance. Genial and
         unassuming in his manners; inspiring in his speech as new wine; accessible to
         all, from the gravest citizen to the humblest child—the life he has lived
         before us has been as warm and fruitful as God's summer, as open and beneficent
         as His day.No truth
         struggling with error has ever failed to find in him a champion; no phase of
         human sorrow has sought him in vain for sympathy and relief. Nay, as we have
         too much reason to know, the very excess of his sensibility has at times become
         to him an element of weakness, and left him for the moment at the mercy of
         colder and harder men.And, if this is
         a fair picture of his private and domestic life, what shall be said of his life
         and influence as a preacher of the Gospel? Let the immense assemblies that for
         nearly thirty years—without abatement, without fluctuation—have thronged
         his chapel, more numerous and enthusiastic today than ever before, bear
         testimony. To this great congregation, presenting an unusual proportion of
         able and thoughtful men, he has ministered all these years untiringly. That
         his ministrations have been marked by a rare spirituality, and a wonderful
         mastery over the various motives of human character and moods of human
         experience, is universally acknowledged. He has been empathically a preacher
         of the people. Living himself in constant communion with the unseen,
         he has interpreted the mysteries of the soul and given voice to those dim
         intuitions—those immortal yearnings—which spring up in every human breast,
         but which so few ever utter. A clergyman of the Congregational Church, he has
         labored for the aggrandizement of no sect, for the building up of no
         denomination. His creed is as broad as humanity itself; and his deep, warm
         heart, instinctively responding to the feeling of all, has enabled him to
         summon the race to a higher, nobler, and purer life. Though a Protestant, he
         has ever been able to discern the common Christian faith in all churches
         bearing the Christian name. Moral integrity, sincere devotion, and an earnest
         consecration to the common Lord, have always been recognized by him, without
         reference to the question of his own recognition by those to whom his charity
         has extended. Every honest soul that labored for the salvation and elevation of
         mankind, whether minister, priest or monk, or only self-sacrificing layman, has
         been to him a Christian brother, a minister of God. It is then no wonder that,
         besides the power of his personal teaching, the demand for his printed
         sermons should be beyond all precedent. Their weekly issue is read in every
         town and hamlet throughout this broad land; they are met within the cabin of
         the backwoodsman, in the hut of the miner, in the forecastle at sea. Not only
         this, but they have been translated into every European language. In England alone, as I am informed, their circulation is
         thrice as large as that in all this
         country.Thus has he—alone—almost fulfilled the
         divine command, "Go ye into all the world and preach the Gospel to every
         creature." I estimate the full force of my words when I affirm that no man
         ever exerted in his own lifetime so wide-spread and beneficent an influence. The
         far-reaching and abiding power of this Christian minister, has long been a
         marvel to the people of two continents, and theories both friendly and hostile
         have been advanced to explain it. Gentlemen, shall I solve the problem
         for you? The reason of the power of this man's preaching is that behind his
         sermons there is a life—and behind the life, a man. It is because they have
         come from the heart, that they have gone to the heart. It is because his
         preaching is known by those who know him best to be illustrated by his daily
         living, that he is, in this supreme emergency of his life, girded by millions
         of faithful hearts and walled to heaven by the unfaltering love and confidence
         of his people.But if there are those who are not interested
         in the minister of the Gospel, I invite them to contemplate the patriot and philanthropist. Espousing the cause of
         the oppressed, he labored for the emancipation of a race. When the agitation
         resulted in a conflict of arms, imperiling the Union of the States, his clarion
         voice was heard everywhere arousing the nation to the holy strife. When danger
         threatened from abroad, he was prompt to plead the cause of "American
         union on the basis of American liberty" in the face of infuriated
         thousands set on by a foreign aristocracy to revile him and to strike him down.
         Mr. Beecher's hand-to-hand fight with the English masses on English soil, is a
         thrilling page in history, known and read of all men. His courage, his
         devotion, his eloquence, in that memorable contest, won the admiration of all Europe and can never be forgotten by the American
         people. In that struggle, Henry Ward
         Beecher won the nation's gratitude and the nation's love. When the
         fury of the storm had spent its force, when the war was over, and the nation
         was saved—then the voice which had rung like a trumpet in the strife was the
         first to plead for forbearance to the vanquished, for a generous condonation of
         the past, and a permanent peace resting upon universal amnesty. This, gentlemen,
         is a true and unflattered portrait of the defendant in this case—as a husband,
         a father, a citizen, a patriot, a philanthropist, a minister, and a man. If it
         were a statement to be established by testimony, thousands upon thousands of
         witnesses might crowd this court to confirm its truth for the name of Henry Ward
         Beecher has long been the treasure of the nation, as it has been the special pride
         and glory of this city, famous throughout the world as the scene of his life
         and labors.
         One of the most
         striking characteristics of the man I have been describing was a profound and
         ever-active interest in young men. The first work he ever published, a work
         which won him an enviable reputation while he was himself yet a young man, and
         which is still disseminated by thousands in this and other lands, was his
         "Lectures to Young Men."  When, therefore, in his earlier Brooklyn ministry, he encountered a young man of unusual promise,
         it was like him to
         receive the youth into his "heart of heart" and to lavish upon him
         that affection, that expenditure of time, and that wealth of intimate
         intercourse, which not a few men of the highest culture had desired in vain.
         For that privileged intimacy, and for that affectionate devotion, this
         prosecution is the grateful reward. The heart in which that generous sowing
         brought forth only the deadly nightshade of envy and hate was the heart of the
         plaintiff in this suit.THEODORE
         TILTONIt now becomes
         my unpleasant duty to invite you, gentlemen, to consider for a moment who and
         what is Theodore Tilton. The plaintiff in this case presents the most impressive
         instance that has ever come within my observation, of the remorseless power and
         the destructive effect of a single absorbing master passion. An
         all-dominating, selfish egotism is the basis of his character. As a boy,
         he was bright and ambitious, and his quickness of apprehension and felicity of
         statement brought him early recognition and praise. Everybody flattered and
         encouraged him, regarding his self-conceit as something which mature years and
         the hard experience of life would modify into a reasonable self-reliance and an
         honorable pride. Beginning life as a reporter on the public press, he was
         brought into contact with great orators and public men, and he early resolved
         to devote himself to a public career. All his studies turned upon this point—to make himself a graceful and powerful speaker
         and writer. The art of
         appearing well and sounding well was the art he sought—a dangerous pursuit
         for one already strongly predisposed by constitutional vanity to consider life a
         drama and himself its hero. He began, with unbounded confidence and cool,
         calculating pertinacity, to work his way upward.  Possessed of a fine
         address, a lively imagination, fertile fancy and flowing speech, he lacked the
         powers of deep and original thought, and, more than these, sound sense,
         discriminating judgment and the unselfish aims which are the prime elements of
         a noble manhood. Anxious above all things to shine, he seized every opportunity
         and advocated every cause which would give him prominence. He adopted the
         ideas of leading men of the country, Sumner, Phillips, Garrison, and, more than
         any other, of Mr. Beecher, who, as we have seen, was lavish of friendship and
         aid—and reproduced them in sensational editorials and lectures. The extremists
         in politics and religion to whom he joined himself, were ready to reward the facility
         with which he yielded himself to their uses by fostering his conceit;
         representing him as the successful antagonist of Mr. Beecher—the young David
         who had overthrown the great Goliath in debate, and the brilliant occupant of
         the editorial chair of The Independent, who had eclipsed the light of
         his predecessor.He fell in with gay, fascinating people, who
         considered themselves free from the conventional restraints of society; and,
         little by little, he slid into their ways of thinking. His unbalanced vanity
         was not proof against the wine of dangerous theories, when presented by the
         hand of the flatterer. Surrounded only by those who burned incense to his
         vanity, he became inflated with success, and fancied himself a monumental
         genius, a prolific source of wit and wisdom—in a word, the foremost man of
         his time. Conspicuously destitute alike of logical power and the poise of a
         nice moral sense, he embraced the wildest views and rushed forward, believing
         that the world would follow where he led. Some persons of cool heads can
         speculate on social, political, or religious questions without losing their
         balance; but, with Theodore Tilton, to calculate the depths of an abyss was to
         plunge headlong into it. A believer in the Christian faith and a member of an
         orthodox church, he speculated on the origin of matter and the attributes of
         God until he became a deist, denying the divinity of Christ, and rejecting the
         Scriptures as a Divine revelation of God's will to man. The husband of a
         gifted, pure, and loving wife—the father of an interesting family, leaving,
         as he describes it, an "ideal home," he speculated on social
         problems, and was led by the malign influence under which he fell, to denounce
         the marriage relation as a remnant of effete civilization—a clog and hindrance
         to the development of the race. His remedy for the evils of marriage was easy
         divorce, leaving parties as free to dissolve the relation as they were to enter
         into it. He denies that he is a free lover, but Victoria Woodhull, the apostle
         of free love, asks for no greater social freedom than this. A leader of men
         must know how to construct and to preserve, but Theodore Tilton knew only how
         to unsettle and destroy. The moment he assumed a position of such prominence
         that he could be studied and criticised, the glaring defects of his character
         discovered themselves to those who had hitherto been his dupes. Opposition
         sprang up in every quarter, and at last be was forced to realize that the
         foundation which had been reared for him, and on which he had been placed by
         others more than by himself, was crumbling beneath his feet. The end was near.
         Theodore Tilton fell—fell from an eminence seldom attained by men of his age—to the very bottom of the abyss, the depths of
         which he had attempted to sound.From that abyss,
         he beheld afar off the man who had been his early friend and patron, but whom
         he had long regarded as his rival and inferior, standing firm and erect, his
         influence widening and deepening, and his hold on public favor becoming more
         and more permanent and secure. A man fed by inordinate vanity can never awake
         to a sane, reasonable estimate of himself.  Failure and disappointment never
         lead such a man to self-examination, but excite within him only bitterness,
         rage and malice.   With him, it is never his own folly and impotence that have
         impeded his advance, but some malevolent power has interfered. In the blindness
         of his rage, Theodore Tilton persuaded himself that the sole and efficient
         cause of his overthrow was Beecher; that the one man who had prevented him from
         reaching the topmost summit of fame was Beecher. But one resource was left to
         him. If he had not power to rebuild, he still had power to destroy, and Beecher should feel that power. To be eclipsed and
         neglected was gall and wormwood to his
         soul. If he could not be famous, he could at least be infamous; and he
         preferred infamy to oblivion. Mr. Beecher had long been his friend, and the
         intimate friend of his wife. That friendship he could pervert, and make
         himself the author, and at the same time the central figure, of the most famous
         scandal of modern times. If he could not supplant Beecher in the affection of
         the people, he could scandalize him. If he had made it impossible
         for any honorable pen to write his own biography, then was it worth any cost to
         have a line devoted to him in the biography of Henry Ward Beecher. His natural
         bent towards, plots and conspiracies now fully revealed itself, and Beecher was the object of his schemes. His grand genius
         for attitudinizing—for Tilton is
         nothing if not dramatic—began to be displayed. As in a play,
         everything was arranged with a view to effect. Facts were nothing to him,
         except as they could be adroitly used to serve the purpose of his pageant.  Friends, wife, children, and all that other men
         hold sacred and dear, must be
         trampled down and walked over to reach the notice and applause for which he has
         shown himself willing to barter his immortal soul.  Pure women might abhor and
         shun him, but one pure woman at least should go to her grave, bearing witness
         to his power in a blasted life and a broken heart. Here, gentlemen, here
         speaks the "master passion" of this perverted man. At this very
         moment, if he could realize the sad truth that he is morally dead, he would
         still rejoice in this post mortem investigation of his character. The decaying corpse would rather be
         dissected than buried; but we propose, gentlemen, to dissect him first in the
         interest of truth, and to bury him afterwards in the interest of decency.
         Such, gentlemen,
         is the plaintiff in this cause. A staunch new vessel, launched upon an
         honorable voyage, sailing with prosperous winds over unruffled seas, has been
         transformed into a pirate by the wickedness of her commander, and wrecked by
         his folly, and now lies a stranded and battered hulk, the object at once of the
         curiosity and abhorrence of mankind.And now,
         gentlemen, with this imperfect preliminary sketch of the two leading characters
         in what we shall show you is the most remarkable conspiracy of modern times,
         perhaps you will be better prepared to comprehend the "strange
         eventful" history which I proceed to lay before you. In 1841, Mr. Beecher
         removed from Indianapolis and settled in Brooklyn.  His success as a preacher
         was already established, and he immediately took rank among the foremost
         orators of America. His church was at once crowded, and soon came to be the largest
         and one of the wealthiest in the two cities. Removing to Brooklyn in 1851 or
         1852, the plaintiff—then a boy just from school—took his place among the
         young men of Plymouth Church. He was speedily taken into favor by some of the
         leading members and by the pastor.  He was employed to report some of Mr.
         Beecher's sermons, and the two men came into frequent contact and formed a warm
         friendship. The favor in this friendship was all on one side. Mr. Beecher was
         a man of mature years, and, even then, almost at the height of his fame. He had
         multitudes of friends—men of wealth, of learning, of high reputation—and could derive nothing from the mere lad whom he thus
         took into the circle of
         his friends, except the pleasure which a great and generous nature feels in
         imparting knowledge to an opening mind, and in helping forward a struggling
         aspirant. The pastor was led to take additional interest in this young man by
         the fact of his marriage to a young girl whom Mr. Beecher had known and loved
         from her childhood. In the following year, Tilton, through Mr. Beecher's
         friendly interest, was taken upon the editorial staff of The Independent, a paper mainly owned by one of Mr. Beecher's congregation,
         and to which Mr. Beecher was himself a regular and valued contributor. From
         this time the relations of the two grew more and more intimate. Tilton visited
         frequently at Mr. Beecher's house and took an active part in the work of the
         church; and when, in 1861, Mr. Beecher was invited to the editorial chair of The
         Independent, his affection for Mr. Tilton was so well known that one of the
         chief inducements held out to him to accept that position was, that Mr. Tilton
         should be associated with him as assistant editor. It is true that there had
         been some indications of envy and conscious rivalry on the part of young
         Tilton, even at this early day, and some of Mr. Beecher's oldest friends
         suspected and criticised the motives of the young man; but Mr. Beecher himself
         was entirely free from suspicion, and put the most innocent interpretation upon
         every act of his new friend.At this time,
         gentlemen, Mr. Beecher had a summer residence in the country, to which it was
         the habit of his family to repair, about the last of May or the first of June,
         and to return again in October, or sometimes as late as November. But a portion
         of the time, while his family were thus residing in the country, and prior to
         the beginning of his summer vacation, in the city—he spent in working at his
         own house, taking his meals with some of the families of his church during the
         time that he was in the city. This habit was well known to Mr. Tilton, and
         early in 1861 or 1862 he urged Mr. Beecher to make his house also a place of
         frequent resort. He spoke often to his pastor of his wife's great affection for
         him, and requested him to call and make himself at home in the
         family. Mr. Beecher had known Mrs. Tilton prior to his acquaintance
         with Mr. Tilton, but only as a young girl, a member of the church; and the
         acquaintance had practically ceased after her marriage, until it was renewed,
         as I have stated, at the request of Mr. Tilton—ceased, I mean, so far as his
         visits to their house were concerned; for in the early years of their marriage
         they were boarding, and when they began to keep house they commenced in Oxford
         street, so far from the place of Mr. Beecher's residence that it was quite
         impracticable for him to visit the house often. Still, at the earnest
         solicitation of Mr. Tilton, as we have said, he began his visits to the house
         in Oxford street; and it was during these visits—quite infrequent, as the
         plaintiff tells you, and made at his earnest request—that Mr. Beecher first
         became acquainted with Mrs. Tilton in the relations of wife and mother.MRS.
         ELIZABETH R. TILTONAnd now,
         gentlemen, I ask you to consider for a moment that Mrs. Tilton is the true defendant
         in this cause—she whose lips are sealed and whose hands are tied, while the
         battle is waging over her body. She can make no outcry, and strike no blow in
         her own defense. She can only weep and pray, as she has done so often already,
         looking for her deliverance to Almighty God and to the spirit of justice which
         He inspires in the hearts of men.Small in stature,
         and of a childlike disposition, this lady is of a nature deeply reverential and
         filled with an exalted religious enthusiasm. The plaintiff himself declares
         that, had she lived in former days and belonged to the Roman Catholic Church,
         she would have been recognized as one of those illustrious women whose names
         shine with the halo of saintliness. She was devoted to her home, entertained
         views of the sacredness of motherhood almost romantic (if that were possible),
         and gave her own life, under God, absolutely to her husband and children, without
         a murmur as to her own self-sacrifice. Gifted, sensitive, pure,
         self-depreciating, idolizing her home, and worshipping with all the intensity
         of her nature the husband of her early love, her very existence was so blended with his, that their union fulfilled Lord
         Coke's definition of marriage. "Two souls united in one person." From
         the time when Theodore Tilton placed the wedding ring upon the finger of Elizabeth, until that hour when, driven by his persecution,
         she was compelled to tear
         herself from his home and from him forever, there had been but one person who
         in all things dominated that household, and that one was Theodore Tilton. His
         wish was to her a command; whatever he willed, she did. Relieving him from
         every household care incident to the rearing of a young and numerous family,
         she was content to toil and suffer that he might win the distinction he coveted
         so much.
         In a married
         life which would have made most women wretched, for ten long years of absolute
         self-sacrifice, Elizabeth Tilton fancied herself happy. Month by month, she
         watched the gradual unfolding of her husband, under the guidance and
         companionship of his friend and pastor.   She saw him rising step by step to
         that proud eminence which had been the ruling ambition of his life, and she was
         happy. But she at last came to realize that every new success brought to him new
         dangers. She saw with pain the character of the associates with whom, in the
         recklessness of vanity and the intoxication of first success, he surrounded
         himself. And with unspeakable anguish she witnessed the change that, day by
         day, was going on in his religious convictions. Slowly but certainly he was sliding
         away from the views of marriage and of social duty which he once adopted, and
         becoming the advocate of theories which seemed to her to have been propounded
         only by those who were unwilling that the principles they professed should be
         better than the lives they lived. The spell of the flatterer was upon him. To
         rescue him from all that she deemed false in religion and pernicious in morals
         was, as it seemed to her, the one great duty of
         life. To accomplish this, no sacrifice was too great. She would patiently if
         not willingly accept humiliation, reproach, accusation; nay, the most sacred
         feelings of wife and mother might be outraged and trampled upon; and still she
         would hide her sufferings and conceal her wounds, if only the object of her
         solicitude and prayers might be saved.There was but
         one person on earth to whom she could make known her sorrow, and that one was
         their friend and pastor. Boundless was her faith in God and the efficacy of
         prayer, but she was not a mere enthusiast; she believed in a wise and faithful
         application of appropriate means. How natural, then, that she should appeal in
         this emergency to him who had been the friend of her husband's youth, the
         counsellor and guide of his maturer manhood. This pastor sympathized with her
         suffering and promised help. How faithfully and how tenderly he counseled the
         plaintiff we have seen by the beautiful letter, as wise as it is beautiful,
         which the defendant wrote to the plaintiff in 1867.  If Tilton could have
         but heeded that advice how different would have been the scene from what we
         this day witness! There would have been no bleeding heart, no deserted hearthstone,
         no wife with broken heart and blasted life, no children with a blight resting
         upon their young and innocent lives; but a home happy and harmonious, a family
         bound together by the ties of love and respect, a household altar undesecrated,
         as in those early days of simple piety of which he is now so much ashamed.But, blinded by
         his egotism and drunk with the intoxication of flattery, he refused to break
         away from his evil associates. Neither the voice of friendship nor the appeals
         of affection had power to save him. And now, gentlemen, they ask us to believe
         that, at this time, when all of a wife's faith, a woman's devotion and
         a mother's love, was being exerted to save Theodore Tilton from the
         companionship and corrupting influence of those "whose feet take hold in hell"
         —this pure-minded and saintly woman, in her very effort to save her
         husband, fell herself! Fell into the very sins against which, for so many
         anxious years, she had been warning her husband "with strong crying and
         with tears!" Nay, more, that the very religion—the religion which she
         had cherished all her life, and which was confessedly so conspicuous in that
         life, furnished the motives for her fall! Still more, that so infatuated and
         unintelligent was her hold upon that faith that, having sinned, she solemnly
         denied this conscientious crime and invented a tissue of lies to support that
         denial; that, still further moved by an inspiration she believed Divine, she abandoned
         all the responsibilities and loves of life, and clave to a spiritual guide,
         himself all leprous and loathsome with adultery and perjury—and that
         (anticlimax of abominations!) she is "a pure and white-souled woman"
         still! Gentlemen, you are men full grown; you have the wisdom that comes from
         the experience of life, the observation of human nature, the knowledge of
         affairs. Is there one among you that can so discredit all that experience and
         observation as to entertain for a moment a suggestion as unutterably absurd, so
         absolutely monstrous?MR.
         TILTON'S TRIUMPHANT CAREER.
         In June, 1863,
         Mr. Beecher, feeling exhausted by his labors, visited Europe for a few months,
         leaving Mr. Tilton in charge of The Independent during his absence; and,
         on his return, finding from experience that the burden was too great for him,
         he privately relinquished the entire charge of the paper to Mr. Tilton. He consented,
         however, that his own name should remain as ostensible editor for a year
         longer, and, at the end of that time, Mr. Tilton openly assumed the charge of
         the paper. The prize Tilton had so earnestly struggled for was now won; and, at
         the age of thirty years, he found himself the successor of Henry Ward Beecher,
         the occupant of one of the proudest editorial chairs in America. For this position he was indebted to the friendship of Henry
         Ward Beecher.The nature of
         the friendship which I have thus briefly described, and its value to Mr. Tilton
         can be portrayed in no language of mine more effective than that in which he
         has done it himself, in a letter which he wrote under a stress of conscience,
         the very year that he became editor, and a few days after he had, over his
         wine, made direct and wicked insinuations against his loving pastor and best
         friend. In this letter he tells, under an impulse of gratitude which was all
         too brief, something of the obligations which he was under to the man whom he had
         just begun covertly to slander, and whom he now seeks
         to destroy:Midnight, BROOKLYN , Nov. 30,1865.Rev.   Henry Ward Beecher:My Dear friend—Returning home late to-night,
         I cannot go to bed without writing you a letter.Twice I have been forced to appear as your antagonist before the public the
         occasions five years apart.  After the first, I am sure our friendship, instead of being maimed was strengthened. After this
         last, if I may guess your heart by knowing mine.
         I am sure the old love waxes instead of wanes. * * * My friend, from my
         boyhood up, you have been to me what no other man has been — what no other man
         can be. While I was a student, the influence of your mind on mine was greater
         than all books and all teachers. The intimacy with which you honored me for
         twelve years has been (next to my wife and family) the chief affection of my
         life. By you I was baptized — by you married. You are my minister, teacher,
         father, brother, friend, companion. The debt I owe you I can never pay. My
         religious life; my intellectual development; my open door of opportunity for
         labor; my public reputation; all these, my dear friend, I owe in so great a
         degree to your own kindness that my gratitude cannot be written in words, but
         must be expressed in love.Then, what hours
         we have had together? What arm in arm wanderings about the streets! What hunts
         for pictures and books! What mutual revelations and communings! What
         interchangings of mirth, of tears, of prayers!The more I think back upon this friendship, the more am I convinced that not
         your public
         position, not your fame, not your genius, but just your affection, has been the
         secret of the bond between us; for whether you had been high or low, great or
         common, I believe that my heart knowing its mate, would have loved you exactly
         the same!Now, therefore, I want to say that if, either long ago or lately, any word of mine, whether
         spoken or printed, whether public or private has given you pain, I beg you to
         blot it from your memory, and to write forgiveness in its place.Moreover, if I should die, leaving you alive, I ask you to
         love my children for their father's
         sake, who has taught them to reverence you, and to regard you as the man of men. One thing more.
         My religious experiences have never been more refreshing than during the last
         year. Never before have I had such fair and winning thoughts of the other
         life. With these thoughts you stand connected in a strange and beautiful way.
         I believe human friendship outlasts human life. Our friendship is yet of the
         earth, earthy, but it shall one day stand uplifted above mortality, safe, without
         scar or flaw, without a breath to blot or a suspicion to endanger it.
         Meanwhile, O my friend! may our Father in Heaven bless you on the earth, guide
         you, strengthen you, illumine you, and at last crown you with the everlasting
         crown! And now, good
         night, and sweet be your dreams of Your
         unworthy, but eternal friend,Theodore Tilton. THURSDAY,
         FEBRUARY 15, 1875.38th
         DAY.
         GENTLEMEN
         OF THE JURY: 
         We now approach a stage of this case where it is important
         for us to consider the nature of the action, the rules which judicial experience
         has found it necessary to establish in the trial of this class of cases, in
         order that the truth may prevail, and collusion, deceit and falsehood be
         defeated. First, the charge of adultery is to be tried by the rules applicable to crimes. The charge involved here
         is in the nature of a crime; the burden of proof is upon the prosecution, and
         they are bound to make out their case beyond a reasonable doubt. It
         is not for this defendant to prove that he is not guilty of this offense; it is
         for the prosecution to prove that he is. As you perceive, gentlemen,
         from the very nature of the case, it is one where affirmative evidence of innocence
         is impossible, except from the testimony of the party implicated. No man, whoever
         he may be charged with such an offense as this, can introduce affirmative
         evidence upon the witness stand that he is not guilty of the offense, for it is impossible for any witness
         save himself to testify that he did not commit it. Whenever such an accusation
         is made against any man and woman residing in the same city, running over a
         long period of time, you see how utterly impossible it is that any witness
         could come upon the witness stand and say: "Of my own knowledge I know
         that this accusation is untrue." Select the most estimable man within your
         knowledge, gentlemen, and bring a charge against him; let any person however
         worthless, charge him with having visited houses of ill-fame, for instance, in
         the city of New York, during a period of sixteen months. If he has resided in
         the city of New York during that time, what can he do in answer to such a
         charge as that but say it was untrue, and rely upon the insufficiency of the
         evidence to establish his guilt?  It is utterly impossible for him to call witnesses
         who can say that this man did not visit these houses; he cannot do that from
         the very nature of the case.  It is an attempt to prove a negative,
         which it is very difficult under any circumstances to establish. From the very
         nature of this case, therefore, when this defendant is accused of this crime
         committed with a lady who was his acquaintance, whom it is admitted he
         frequently visited at her house, at the solicitation of her husband—all he
         can do is to interpose his word of denial and rest upon his established
         character, which he has made during the last thirty years in your midst. The evidence
         of guilt muse be removed from all suspicion; it must be evidence free from
         doubt; it must be evidence that carries home to your consciences conviction of
         the truth of the offense charged, or you are bound by the oaths you have taken
         to render a verdict for this defendant.
         The
         charge of adultery is not a new one in our courts of justice. It is a matter of
         frequent occurrence and the rules of law which judicial experience has
         established in order to ascertain the truth in this
         class of cases are well defined and well understood. This charge may be
         established, first, by direct evidence of witnesses who saw the act. I need
         not say to you, gentlemen, that there is no such evidence pretended in this
         case. Second, it may be established by circumstantial evidence leading
         irresistibly to the conclusion that the act has been committed. There is no
         evidence worthy of the name which fall, under that head in the case now on
         trial. These parties have been acquainted for twenty years. During all that
         time this lady has been a member of the Church of which this defendant is the
         pastor. During all that time they have been acquaintances and friends.
         During all that time, up to within the last four years at least, the pastor and
         the husband were intimate personal friends; he visited that house at the
         solicitation of the husband; and, beyond that fact, the fact that he came to
         the house of the plaintiff at his request, there is not a fact or
         circumstance worthy of credit here which tends to show in the slightest degree
         improper familiarity between these parties, much less a criminal act.THE
         PLAINTIFF'S EVIDENCE WEIGHED AND DECLARED WANTING.The plaintiff accuses his
         wife now, and seeks to blast her character; but during all these years he is
         unable to lay his hand upon a single well authenticated fact which convicts
         this white-souled woman of the slightest impropriety of conduct in connection
         with her pastor. Will it be said that I forget the evidence? Will it
         be said that I do not remember Kate Carey, the woman  brought from the lazar
         house of New York city, reeking with prostitution and disease, twice its inmate
         within three months, discharged everywhere she has been employed for
         intoxication or some improper conduct, who testifies to the fact that on some
         occasion she saw this plaintiff's wife sitting upon the knee of the defendant?
         Gentlemen, I shall not insult your good sense by supposing that twelve
         honest-minded men would blast a reputation such as Henry Ward Beecher's and
         that of a woman of the character that this plaintiff gives his wife for twenty
         years, upon the word of such a woman as Kate Carey; Carey is the name, I
         believe, or Smith; which is it?Mr. Shearman—Smith; Carey alias Smith. Mr. Beach—She gave her name as Kite Carey
         Smith on the stand.Mr. Tracy—Then, gentlemen, what does that
         circumstance amount to if it is true? What were the facts connected with her
         testimony which shows, the improbability of this story that she tells herself.  Why,
         she says to you, that she came down into the dining-room one day
         for a drink of water, when the doors between the dining-room and the parlor
         were wide open and as she walked in she saw the plaintiff's wife
         sitting upon the knee of the defendant, and she heard him say to her: "Elizabeth,
         how do you feel?" and she said: "Dear father, so so."
         [Laughter.] Well, gentlemen, you only needed that last expression to show that
         this was a matter that was coined from the brain of this simple-minded woman.
         It was natural for her to address her priest by the name of "Father,"
         and therefore when she comes to make this plaintiff's wife address her minister
         she uses the same word that she would have used if she
         had been addressing her own. It is that slight circumstance that is
         enough to show the improbability of the story which this woman tells, upon her
         own showing. But I shall not dwell upon that, gentlemen. It is unworthy,
         I repeat, of the serious consideration of twelve honest men.There is another
         circumstance which I am not permitted to forget, not on account of its
         importance as evidence, gentlemen, in this case, for, as such, it amounts to
         nothing, but on account of the exhibition which was made by the witness who
         came to testify to it. I refer to the brother of this plaintiff's wife, who said
         she was his only sister, and how highly he regarded her, who came into Court in
         company with this plaintiff, knowing and realizing and telling you from the
         stand that he knew nothing of his own knowledge that could affect the
         reputation of these parties, unless he should be permitted to make a speech to you
         from the witness stand and connect with what he saw what he had heard
         from such women as Kate Carey and other people—prostitutes, male and female
         alike. If he could repeat these rumors and these stories that he had heard,
         then perhaps his evidence would have some significance; but he knew perfectly
         well, and realized it, that if he was permitted to testify only to what he had
         seen, it amounted to nothing against his sister. And yet why did he come here? 
         Why? He was under no obligation to come here. If he had told the plaintiff,
         or rather, permit me to say, if he had told the senior counsel of the
         plaintiff that what he had seen would amount to nothing, he would have been
         excused; but if he could come here and be permitted to make a speech against
         his sister, then he might possibly prejudice your minds against her. Now, what
         is the story he told? He says that on one occasion—when, he doesn't know and
         cannot tell—he went into the parlor of his sister one morning, and on opening
         the door saw Mr. Beecher sitting in a chair, and saw his sister moving away from
         his direction—moving rapidly, he says, with
         her face apparently flushed, and that is all he saw! They were in the parlors,
         gentlemen, where a virtuous woman receives an honorable guest. They were in no
         bedroom, and Mr. Beecher was sitting quietly; no movement on his part
         gentlemen, no surprise could this man testify to at all, and he practically
         testified to none against his sister. How long had his sister been in that
         room? He does not know. Where did she come from, and what had she been doing
         before he went in? He does not know. He saw her moving away. How far she was
         from him he does not know.   And is there any evidence of guilt in that,
         gentlemen?  Is that not a thing that is likely to happen to anybody a thousand
         times.Why, let me
         refer you to the evidence of a virtuous woman, given from this witness stand by
         herself, her own confession of an interview that she had with this defendant
         without provoking a suspicion on the part of her husband of impropriety, and
         without a thought of impropriety on her part. I refer to Mrs.
         Moulton. She says that she spent four hours with this defendant in
         a bedroom, left there by her husband. Aye! 
         more. She testifies to a fact that they have not yet fastened on Elizabeth
         Tilton. She tells you that while alone in that bedroom with this defendant she
         kissed him. Now, gentlemen, supposing that they had got a servant who could
         have testified to such facts as that against Mrs. Tilton and 
         Mr. 
         Beecher.
         Supposing they had found him tucked up on a sofa with an Afghan, having an
         interview in a bedroom with this plaintiff's wife and she kissing him, all
         testified to by a servant. That, the counsel of the plaintiff would argue, was
         evidence of guilt. Yet you see that when that fact is testified to by Mrs.
         Moulton herself, against herself, it excites in the mind of no honorable man
         even a suspicion against that woman's virtue. And you see, therefore, what
         familiarities and what liberties virtuous women can take, and properly take,
         with virtuous men, without exciting suspicion. But there is no such fact as
         this against Elizabeth Tilton. I say, and I repeat to you, that this case
         stands entirely destitute of either class of evil once usually relied upon in
         cases of this description to convict this defendant. It is confined entirely to
         the confessions of the defendant, written and oral, mainly oral, for they have
         despaired of convicting him upon his letters, and, therefore, they have
         endeavored to supplement them by oral confessions. The effect of that class of
         evidence I shall have occasion to consider in a moment. But that class of
         evidence, gentlemen, you will bear in mind comes from a single family, if I may
         count Tilton as a member of the family of Moulton, as I think I can safely from
         the evidence of both himself and Mr. Moulton and Mrs. Moulton. It comes from
         two conspirators against this defendant; the plaintiff, his mutual friend, and
         the mutual friend's wife. No other witness appears to testify to oral
         confessions except these three.MR. BEECHER'S ALLEGED ORAL CONFESSIONSNow, gentlemen
         of the jury, I come to another branch of this case; and that is the branch
         which is now mainly relied upon, to wit, the pretended oral confessions which
         this defendant is alleged to have made to Francis D. Moulton and to his wife,
         and to the plaintiff, Theodore Tilton. In the beginning, gentlemen, we shall
         show you that these parties relied expressly upon the writing that they had,
         and upon nothing else. As late as July 10, 1874, after the appointment of the
         Church Committee, and on Mr. Tilton's first appearing before the Committee, we
         shall show you, I apprehend, by evidence which you will not doubt, that Mr.
         Tilton there said that his case against Henry Ward Beecher was in writing. He
         said that he knew that his reputation was impaired in this community, and that
         the guilt or
         innocence of Henry Ward Beecher did not at
         all depend upon his word—he had it in writing. I think that the evidence will
         show you that after Mr. Tilton had repeated that once or twice over, he was
         interrupted by one who thought, at least at that time that he had seen the
         written case against Henry Ward Beecher, who said to him: "Mr. Tilton, if
         your case against Henry Ward Beecher is in writing, then it is wholly a
         question of what these writings prove; that is a fact that other people can judge
         of as well as you can; it is the construction of the papers;" and he was
         told then and there, I think, by one who supposed he had seen these papers and
         studied them carefully, that they did not warrant the insinuations which
         Theodore Tilton was there making, and they would not prove the case that he was
         then insinuating. I think it will transpire before you, gentlemen, that up to
         that time neither Tilton nor Moulton had ever talked about oral confessions of
         Henry Ward Beecher. I think it will transpire that this part of their case has
         arisen since that date. At least I have no doubt that it will appear to you
         that on that occasion Mr. Tilton did not pretend that he had any oral confessions
         from Mr. Beecher tending to establish his case, but that he said distinctly
         that his case against Mr. Beecher was in writing, and was locked in his safe,
         or in Moulton's safe.
         In Moulton's
         statement, published August 21st, some time after this, and after this
         controversy had begun, Mr. Moulton alleged in general language, that Mr.
         Beecher had confessed orally to him; but his language was entirely general; he
         gave no specific words; he made no statement which was legal evidence of that
         fact. His paper was challenged on that recount, and it was said: "Henry
         Ward Beecher ever confessed to you, why haven't you stated the confession, so
         that other people can see whether his language amounted to a confession of
         guilt or not?"  It was not until after he had been thus
         challenged and made his second statement that he undertook to give the words in
         which Mr. Beecher confessed. And finally, on the trial here, gentlemen, he
         clothes Mr. Beecher's confessions in entirely different language from what he
         did in his second statement. But you will not
         forget the remarkable language which he so continuously puts in the mouth of
         Henry Ward Beecher; "sexual relations," "sexual intercourse,"
         " sexual expression," " adultery," not once, gentlemen, I
         beg you to observe, but continuously, at every interview, and he
         never has Mr. Beecher refer to "their relations" without preceding it
         with the word "sexual." Do you believe that, gentlemen of the jury?
         Even assenting that Henry Ward Beecher did intend to convey to Francis D.
         Moulton the idea that he had had criminal relations with the wife of the
         plaintiff do you believe that at every interview that occurred between them
         afterwards Mr. Beecher expressly referred to the confession, and used the precise
         language that he did on the first occasion?  Having used it once, would not a
         mere reference to it afterwards have been sufficient?  Was it necessary for him
         to repeat always the words "sexual relations" to have Mr. Moulton
         understand what he meant?  Why, it is most improbable, I submit. If Mr. Beecher
         had been confessing, he never could have been guilty of such weakness, and displayed
         such love of nasty expressions as to be continually rolling these from his
         lips, as Moulton says he did. It is impossible to believe it; it is
         incredible. They are words that are manufactured and put into the mouth of
         Henry Ward Beecher on occasion after occasion. He never used any such
         expression; he never made any such confession. And you will remember,
         gentlemen, if you recall his (Moulton's) expression upon the witness stand,
         when he has attempted to repeat this phraseology, the remarkable slip he made,
         not once, but twice, when he undertook to say, "Mr. Beecher said his
         relations—his sexual relations." Not once, but twice, he did that in
         repeating it, and that is the precise manner he repeats it in his
         statement. In his published statement he says: "Mr. Beecher said his
         relations with this woman," without adding the word "sexual"; but
         when he comes to
         repeat it from the witness stand he says:  "Mr. Beecher said his relations
         —his sexual relations;" and when he told it again on his
         cross-examination he made the same slip, and, recalling himself, added the word
         "sexual."
         I shall not
         dwell upon those interviews. They are remarkable if they ever occurred, most
         remarkable. It is a most remarkable fact that Henry Ward Beecher, if he had
         been guilty, could have committed the indiscretion of throwing open his heart
         to a friend of a day; for you will bear in mind that Francis D. Moulton was a
         stranger to Henry Ward Beecher on the night of the 30th of December. He tells you
         that he was a stranger to him; that is, he knew him as everybody knew Mr.
         Beecher; he had a speaking acquaintance with him; he had been introduced to him
         before, but there were no relations between them as friends or acquaintances;
         and yet he goes to him on the 30th of December in a hostile attitude as a
         friend of the man who was accusing him, and he comes to him again on the 31st
         of December, the next night, and he says, without word of caution or
         preliminary suggestion, Mr. Beecher opened to him and confessed his adultery
         with this woman. The absurdity of the statement itself is sufficient to
         challenge the closest scrutiny on the part of the jury, and to excite the
         gravest doubts, even if it fell from the lips of an unquestioned witness,
         whether it could be possible that any man in his senses could be guilty of such
         an indiscretion as that.But
         further, gentleman, you will remember the great struggle we had when Mr.
         Moulton was on the witness stand, to get him to testify that the subject of
         these stories which Bowen had circulated against Tilton to Beecher, and Beecher
         had circulated against Tilton to Bowen, were the subjects of conversation
         between Mr. Beecher and Moulton on the night of the 31st of December, or on the
         night of the 1st of January. But we could not get him to do it; we could not
         get him to say that Mr. Beecher agreed to apologize to Bowen, and to
         write a letter to Bowen taking back what he said in regard to Tilton and Mrs.
         Bullard. He would not acknowledge that it was done on either the 31st of
         December or the 1st of January. This was very important for him, and he understood
         the importance of it, because that would give a clue, you see, to the
         contrition and the sorrow and the regret which Beecher was expressing on the
         night of the 1st of January. If his discreditable report concerning Laura Curtis
         Bullard had been the subject of conversation, and he had agreed to take it
         back, and had agreed to write a letter for that purpose — if these stories that
         he had circulated in regard to Tilton, to Bowen, had been the subject of conversation,
         and he had been expressing his regrets concerning them, why, that would have
         furnished some explanation of what his excitement was, what caused it. But they
         keep that all out of view. They ask you to believe, gentlemen, that there was
         nothing talked of on either of these nights except his relation to Mrs. Tilton,
         substantially, and that that was what he was expressing his sorrow and regret
         for; and so they say that this letter to Bowen was not the subject of
         conversation. But it was written so soon after, you see, gentlemen, that they
         could not postpone it very long. It must be the subject of conversation right
         away. If it was not on the night of the 31st of December, or the 1st of
         January it must be immediately following. They saw that necessity, and they
         must meet it. Now, how did they do it? Moulton does it by inventing an
         interview between himself and Mr. Beecher on the 2d of January, where he makes
         these stories the subject of conversation, and this letter to Bowen their
         matter of talk and agreement. I say he invents it, and I shall leave you no
         doubt upon that subject, gentlemen. The 1st of January that year came
         on Sunday. This letter called the "Apology" was written Sunday
         afternoon, in Beecher's house. Moulton tells you that he called the next day
         in the afternoon towards evening, somewhere from 3 to 5 o'clock, I think, that
         evening, and had another long interview with Mr. Beecher, on the 2d of January,
         and he tells you in great detail what occurred. He tells you expressly, in
         answer to a question put to him on cross-examination that he had four separate
         interviews with Mr. Beecher on four successive days. That is the
         question put to him and that is the question he answered. Now, gentlemen, we
         shall show you that Francis D. Moulton had no interview with Henry Ward Beecher
         on the 2d of January. The 2d of January; as the day celebrated as
         New Year's and Mr. Beecher, as was his custom received New Year's calls that
         day, and was engaged all day long in receiving New Year's calls. He had nearly
         800 callers I am informed, at his house on the 2d of January, 1871. Busy all
         day, from 9 o'clock in the morning until late in the evening, he had no opportunity
         for such an interview, and no such interview ever occurred. I say it has been
         invented, and invented for a purpose, in order to enable this witness to carry
         an interview, on very important and vital questions, one day beyond the writing
         of this letter of apology. He tells you further that Mr. Beecher consulted him
         on that day as to whether the pew-renting should go off that year. Why,
         gentlemen, if that interview was on the 2d day of January, the pew-renting was
         to take place the next day, and had been advertised everywhere, and everybody
         knew it was to go
         on. The talk of stopping it from going on
         would have been worse than a printed confession. There was no such talk, no
         such thought. The renting of the pews, I say, had been advertised, and it took
         place the next day, and there was never a suggestion as to whether it should go
         off or not, or be postponed.
          Midnight, BROOKLYN , Nov. 30,1865.Rev.   Henry Ward Beecher:My Dear friend—Returning home late to-night,
         I cannot go to bed without writing you a letter.Twice I have been forced to appear as your antagonist before the public the
         occasions five years apart.  After the first, I am sure our friendship, instead of being maimed was strengthened. After this
         last, if I may guess your heart by knowing mine.
         I am sure the old love waxes instead of wanes. * * * My friend, from my
         boyhood up, you have been to me what no other man has been — what no other man
         can be. While I was a student, the influence of your mind on mine was greater
         than all books and all teachers. The intimacy with which you honored me for
         twelve years has been (next to my wife and family) the chief affection of my
         life. By you I was baptized — by you married. You are my minister, teacher,
         father, brother, friend, companion. The debt I owe you I can never pay. My
         religious life; my intellectual development; my open door of opportunity for
         labor; my public reputation; all these, my dear friend, I owe in so great a
         degree to your own kindness that my gratitude cannot be written in words, but
         must be expressed in love.Then, what hours
         we have had together? What arm in arm wanderings about the streets! What hunts
         for pictures and books! What mutual revelations and communings! What
         interchangings of mirth, of tears, of prayers!The more I think back upon this friendship, the more am I convinced that not
         your public
         position, not your fame, not your genius, but just your affection, has been the
         secret of the bond between us; for whether you had been high or low, great or
         common, I believe that my heart knowing its mate, would have loved you exactly
         the same!Now, therefore, I want to say that if, either long ago or lately, any word of mine, whether
         spoken or printed, whether public or private has given you pain, I beg you to
         blot it from your memory, and to write forgiveness in its place.Moreover, if I should die, leaving you alive, I ask you to
         love my children for their father's
         sake, who has taught them to reverence you, and to regard you as the man of men. One thing more.
         My religious experiences have never been more refreshing than during the last
         year. Never before have I had such fair and winning thoughts of the other
         life. With these thoughts you stand connected in a strange and beautiful way.
         I believe human friendship outlasts human life. Our friendship is yet of the
         earth, earthy, but it shall one day stand uplifted above mortality, safe, without
         scar or flaw, without a breath to blot or a suspicion to endanger it.
         Meanwhile, O my friend! may our Father in Heaven bless you on the earth, guide
         you, strengthen you, illumine you, and at last crown you with the everlasting
         crown! And now, good
         night, and sweet be your dreams of Your
         unworthy, but eternal friend,Theodore Tilton.  
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>