<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00093</field>
      <field name="title">Sex, Politics and Society: The Regulation of Sexuality Since 1800.</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">divorce</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="theme">prostitution</field>
      <field name="text">1. 
         "From the end of the eighteenth century with the
         debate on over-population and the hyperbreeding of the poor, sexuality pervades
         the social consciousness: from the widespread discussions of the birthrate,
         deathrate, life expectancy and fertility in the statistical forays of the
         century to the urgent controversies over public health, housing, birth control
         and prostitution. . . .The reports of the great Parliamentary Commissions, which
         in the 1830s and 1840s investigated working conditions in factories and mines,
         were saturated with an obsessive concern with the sexuality of the working
         class, the social other, displacing in the end the acute social crisis from the
         area of exploitation and class conflict, where it could not be coped with, into
         the framework of a more amenable and discussable area of 'morality'. From the
         1850s sexuality, particularly in the wide area of venereal disease and
         prostitution (allied to feats that Britain would follow Rome into imperial
         decline) enters the heart of Parliamentary debate. The controversy over the
         Contagious Diseases Acts, passed in the 1860s to impose compulsory medical
         examination and registration on working-class women suspected of being
         prostitutes in designated garrison and naval towns, generated an avalanche of
         controversy and publications. The Acts were the subject of repeated
         Parliamentary enquiries, while the repeal organizations alone published at
         least 520 books and pamphlets on venereal disease and prostitution. Between
         1870 and 1885, 17,367 petitions against the Acts, with 2,606,429 signatures
         were presented to the House of Commons, and over 900 public meetings were held
         by supporters of repeal.Other legislative changes produced their own
         effects. The divorce act of 1857 evinced a flurry of interest in the next
         decade in stories of bigamy and adultery: a special paper, The Divorce News
         and Police Reporter, was founded to cater for specialized tastes, but other
         Victorian papers, like their more familiar twentieth-century offspring, were
         full of divorce cases and other sexual scandals" (19-20).2. 
         "The popular morality of the vast majority was no
         less strict for being loosely Christian in a formal sense. As G.R. Quaife has
         put it, 'God does not loom large as a damper on lower-class sexual activity.' 
         This should not be taken to imply that there was in any sense an unrestrained
         licence for peasant sexuality; there was no 'amorality' in a fundamental
         sense. There was, on the contrary, an often strict morality, enforced through
         various informal and traditional methods such as those of public shaming, the
         charivari and skimmington rides. But it was a social morality, in which
         the potential economic burden to the community of bastards mattered more than
         the 'immorality' of premarital sex.' 
         What seems to be happening in the nineteenth
         century, in response to major social changes (rapid industrialization and
         urbanization, the disruption of old class patterns and the rise of capitalist
         social relations, the development of new and sharp class conflicts with their related
         social and intellectual manifestations) is a continuous battle over the
         definition of acceptable sexual behaviour within the context of changing class
         and power relations. And there are different rhythms in this process. There
         was no blanket imposition of 'repression.' Not until the 1880s did 'social
         purity' have any major legislative purchase; and it is significant that it is
         from this period that the earliest critiques of 'Victorianism' stem" (22-23).3. 
         "The new marriage laws (especially those after
         1836, which granted the right to marry to nonconformist chapels as well as
         civil registrars) had the effect of making the betrothal less binding and of
         sharply differentiating the married from the unmarried, hence making the
         difference between licit and illicit sex more important. Earlier traditions
         survived in rural areas and amongst the unorganized and disrupted working
         class, but marriage became increasingly the gateway to respectability and
         stability. It was buttressed by an increasing idealization of domesticity, a
         growing specification and rationalization in the censure of extra-marital sex
         (partly articulated by what one sex reformer called 'the continued extension of
         criminal law') and by the difficulty of divorce. The 1857 Matrimonial Causes
         Act, which set up secular courts and procedures, established no new principle
         not involved in the old form of divorces by petitions in Acts of Parliament.
         The only principle abandoned in 1857 was the propriety of making legal remedies
         for marriage difficulties available for the aristocracy while withholding them
         from the growing upper middle class. Change was slow: divorce rose from an
         annual average of 148 in the decade after 1851 to 582 in the decade before
         1900; and divorce remained a strong social stigma. Even innocent parties were
         excluded from court until 1887. In the working class, though the stigma might
         be less, the difficulties were even greater and divorce was quite out of the
         question for most" (24-25).4. 
         "The life style of the bourgeois lady was
         purchased at the expense of a large class of servants, often prone to sexual
         depredations, and an equally vulnerable group of prostitutes. The ideological
         division of women into two classes, the virtuous and the fallen, was already
         well developed by the mid-eighteenth century: its reality was to have a vivid
         impact on the Victorian imagination. Nor did it go unchallenged. The
         evangelical and puritan strands vigorously opposed the double standard, and by
         the last decades of the century were able to pose a significant challenge to
         its easy acceptance. Nonetheless, it is inescapably true that familial
         ideology was accompanied by, and often relied on, a vast underbelly of
         prostitution, which fed on the double standard and an authoritarian moral code"
         (30) 5. 
         "Sexuality thus had an extremely complex and vital symbolic role in what became the dominant ideology in the nineteenth century.
         First and foremost, sexual respectability expressed the aspirations and lives of the middle class.  Only secondarily was it
         for export to other classes.  It is here that theorizations which see the nuclear family as a means for controlling the working
         class in the 'interests of capitalism' can be seen to be inadequate. . . . 
         [D]espite . . . earnest evangelical endeavors it is probably true to say that many bourgeois groups had little direct interest
         in working-class morality, as long as work relationships were secured.  In the debate over the great Commissions of Inquiry
         of the 1830s and the 1840s, divisions amongst the bourgeoisie were quite clear.  Neither the interpretations nor the prognostications
         of men such as Lord Ashley were universally acceptable and the 'colonizing' efforts were largely unsuccessful. By the 1890s
         the seats of sexual respectablity were seen by reformers such as Grant Allen to rest in the lower middle class and the upper
         working class, but in the latter there was no simple acceptance of middle-class norms.  What was taking place was much more
         complex, and the working-class patterns of family and sexual life that were brought to the twentieth century were as much
         the product of working-class adaptation to rapid change in the context of a ruling set of ideas as a successful colonization.
         nevertheless, the existence of this vast and strange symbolic other served to confirm the rightness, indeed righteousness,
         of the moral code.  It is in this context that we can appreciate the truth of Foucault's dictum that 'sexuality' was originally
         and fundamentally bourgeois in origins.  It was in the great middle classes that sexuality, albeit in a morally and sharply
         defined form, first became of major ideological significance" (32-33).  
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>