<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00063</field>
      <field name="title">Reverend Beecher and Mrs. Tilton:  Sex and Class in Victorian Americafrom Chapter One, "The Brooklyn Scandal"1982</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">popularpress</field>
      <field name="text">Theodore
         Tilton and Henry Ward Beecher had first become friends when they worked
         together on the popular religious journal, the 
         Independent. The minister, along with others in Plymouth Church, had been instrumental in obtaining a position for Tilton
         on the paper, later promoting
         him to editor. Tilton, twenty-two years younger than Beecher, regarded the
         minister as a father figure. Anxious that Beecher's friendship include his wife
         and children, he repeatedly urged the preacher to visit his home. These
         invitations were ignored until 1866 when Tilton began a series of lecture tours
         that kept him away from Brooklyn three or four months every year.During
         these absences, Beecher began calling upon Mrs. Tilton every week—indeed, he
         became almost a part of the household, reading the children stories and putting
         them to bed. Elizabeth Tilton, flattered by attention from this
         "great man," described these visits in letters to her husband.
         Despite her openness, however, Tilton's suspicions were aroused. He vacillated,
         however, between feeling flattered and, increasingly, jealous. Significantly,
         Tilton was not alone in his suspicions, for many Plymouth Church parishioners,
         who were neighbors of the Tiltons, had noticed the frequent visits. Beecher had a reputation as a nonvisiting minister; he
         made no secret of his aversion to
         this particular pastoral duty. Mrs. Tilton was a notable exception.Whatever rumors
         may have circulated, nothing was said openly for four years after the visits
         began. From 1866 on, however, it was clear
         that the Tiltons experienced marital difficulties, while the discord between
         Henry Ward Beecher and his wife Eunice was common knowledge. Rumors surfaced
         that Beecher had sought sympathy and sexual solace from other female members of
         his congregation. Despite the gossip, however, the Tiltons continued their
         friendship with the minister. Elizabeth Tilton even suggested to her husband
         that the two of them—with "pure" friendship—might cure Beecher of some of the "delusions" he had about himself. Apparently,
         the Tiltons were more deluded than Beecher, for on October 10, 1868, the pastor probably succeeded in seducing Elizabeth.
         She told her husband later that she had "surrendered" only after
         "long moral resistance... and ... repeated assaults... upon her mind with
         overmastering arguments." She had weakened only because of her
         "tender state of mind" and her need of consolation following the
         death of her infant child. Beecher's arguments that "pure affection and a
         high religious love" justified their sexual union were indeed "overmastering."
         They convinced Elizabeth that, despite the affair, she remained "spotless
         and chaste." But her contention that "pure" love should be
         honest and open, and that she should therefore inform her husband of their
         relationship, was vehemently resisted by Beecher. He insisted, she said, that
         the vulgar world would not understand such purity; they must practice
         "nest-hiding." Keeping their love a secret was necessary to preserve
         its integrity.On
         July 3, 1870, Elizabeth
         finally did confess to her husband. Clearly, however, she intended the
         revelation only for Theodore—it was not a public statement. At the time of
         her confession, Theodore offered to keep her secret and help heal her
         "wounded spirit." Despite intentions of secrecy, however, the scandal
         almost became public the following December when Tilton quarreled with his
         employer and fellow Plymouth Church member, Henry C. Bowen. Bowen as publisher
         and Tilton as editor of the 
         Brooklyn Union had come to disagree on the paper's editorial policy
         toward Plymouth Church. In the heat of the dispute, Tilton revealed to Bowen
         his wife's adultery with Beecher. The impact of this information on Bowen was
         startling. He already harbored numerous grievances against the minister, one — possibly
         —for the seduction of his own wife Lucy eight years before. Bowen himself had
         been the source of the earlier rumors about Beecher. This evidence of another Beecher adultery offered Bowen the opportunity
         for revenge. He urged Tilton to demand the
         minister's resignation. Caught off guard by this turn of events, Tilton wrote
         such a letter but then confided to his long-time friend Frank Moulton what had
         occurred. Moulton, suspicious of Bowen's motives, urged Tilton to destroy the
         letter, but it was too late; it had been delivered by Bowen himself. Beecher as
         well as Tilton, badly shaken by the possibility of public exposure, now
         welcomed Moulton's offer to "manage" the affair. Thus began a
         four-year attempt to cover up the scandal. The "mutual friend," as
         Moulton later became known, planned the cover-up strategy—suddenly becoming an
         important figure in the lives of both men.Moulton, in
         fact, accompanied the preacher as he confronted Elizabeth Tilton. It was the
         first time they had seen each other since Beecher's discovery of her
         confession. During that encounter, the minister persuaded Elizabeth—who was
         recovering from a miscarriage—to write a retraction of the confession; he
         even dictated its contents. Tilton, upon discovering this maneuver on Beecher's part, insisted that his wife write yet another
         letter, this time denying her
         retraction and indicating that Beecher had dictated it. She abjectly agreed.The next day, in
         one of the more dramatic episodes of the case, Moulton called on Beecher, took a pistol from his coat, and chided the minister
         for obtaining from Mrs.
         Tilton a letter which he "knew to be a lie." Some accounts claim that
         it was common for those who had business along Brooklyn's waterfront to carry
         pistols, although others insisted that Moulton was deliberately threatening Beecher. Significantly, the preacher surrendered
         the retraction to Moulton amidst
         "great sorrow and weeping" and protestations that the "sexual
         expression" of his love for Elizabeth Tilton was as natural as its
         "verbal expression."For
         a time, Moulton was extremely effective in concealing the scandal and
         persuading Tilton and Beecher to resume their friendship. Because Henry Bowen
         had fired Tilton, Moulton and his business partners, with financial help from Beecher, backed a new weekly paper, the Golden
         Age, with Tilton as editor. Moulton
         also sent off to boarding school a young girl who had been living with the
         Tiltons and who knew of Beecher's affair with Mrs. Tilton. He even persuaded Beecher to pay the girl's expenses.Moulton might
         have
         congratulated himself on his astute handling of the scandal
         if Woodhull, through her connections with Susan Anthony and Elizabeth Cady
         Stanton, had not heard rumors of the affair. In the spring of 1871 came the
         first hints that she knew of the scandal—causing Moulton, Beecher, and Tilton
         to begin frantically, and somewhat comically, conspiring to keep her quiet. The
         three conceived a plan whereby Tilton would placate Woodhull by putting her
         under "social obligation" to them. He accomplished this by flattering
         her and offering to compose an admiring biography. (Woodhull later claimed that
         he had also become her lover for more than six months.) The appeasement policy
         succeeded for a year, until 1872, when Woodhull, angered by the attacks upon
         her by Beecher's sisters, Catherine and Harriet, published her story.This
         time, despite Moulton's frantic schemes to avoid it, the scandal erupted. One
         after another of the incriminating letters and documents was published in the
         papers—but it was still a full year and a half before any formal action was
         taken. Curiously, it was Tilton who was first attacked for his part in
         the scandal. In 1873, Plymouth Church dismissed him from membership, citing his
         "slander" of the minister and association with Woodhull. Even then,
         however, Tilton's commitment to silence was unshaken. Had it not been for a
         Brooklyn Congregational Council's demands for an investigation, the affair
         might once again have faded from public notice. The council had no real power,
         but it inspired a series of articles in the Independent by a Yale
         divinity professor—a friend of Beecher's—who referred to Tilton as a
         "knave" and a "dog." Tilton could not stand this
         public degradation; in June 1874, he responded with a long reply, which he sent
         to the major New York and Brooklyn newspapers, stating his version of the case
         and voicing his refusal "to sacrifice my good name for the sake of his."By
         July 1874, public outcry was so great that Beecher abandoned the policy of
         silence. Taking the offensive, he appointed a Church Investigating Committee
         (which consisted of six of his closest friends) to hear the charges. During
         August the committee took testimony which the newspapers published verbatim. A
         fascinated public hung on every word. Elizabeth Tilton, determined to defend Beecher, appeared the day after leaving her husband,
         revealing with touching pathos a sad
         tale of "domestic unhappiness," but denying the adultery. Tilton, now
         joined by Moulton in an effort to expose Beecher, presented a mass of
         documentation—including Beecher's own letters—which constituted almost
         irrefutable evidence. But, not surprisingly, the committee issued a report
         completely exonerating Beecher. "The evidence," stated the
         Investigating Committee, established "to the perfect satisfaction of his
         church" Beecher's "entire innocence and absolute personal
         integrity." Because of their pastor's "unmerited sufferings,"
         the committee members reiterated that they now felt a "sympathy more
         tender and a trust more unbounded" than ever before. When Moulton
         protested the report at a full church meeting, he was threatened with violence
         and the police were called to "escort" him from the hall. Tilton,
         angered by Beecher's private system of justice and smarting under the sharp
         insulting rebuke of the committee, filed criminal charges against the minister.
         The ensuing trial was the greatest national spectacle of the 1870s. For six
         months—from January to June 1875—the most renowned lawyers in the country
         dedicated their talents to the case. Opening and closing statements alone took
         two months; opera glasses were sold in the courtroom and bouquets of flowers
         were showered on Beecher and Tilton. The trial became known as the "flower
         war." In the end, the jury could not agree and Beecher was acquitted. His
         congregation staged a huge celebration, voting to raise his salary by $100,000
         in order to pay the lawyers. It was all a magnificent vote of confidence which
         demonstrated the overwhelming devotion of Beecher's congregation.Because
         the result of the trial was equivocal, Plymouth Church sought to make the
         verdict conclusive by calling a second church council in 1876. In that council,
         Henry C. Bowen, for the first time, came forward, testifying that he knew Beecher to be a "libertine and a seducer." Nevertheless,
         the council—which
         consisted of churches carefully chosen because of their sympathy with Beecher—followed the lead of Plymouth in completely
         exonerating Beecher. Bowen, Emma
         Moulton, and others who had testified against the minister were promptly excommunicated.
         The purge was completed in the spring of 1878 when Elizabeth Tilton, in a
         startling reversal of the stand she had taken all through the trial, made a
         public confession of the adultery and was also excommunicated.The
         members of Plymouth Church were both numerous and powerful in Brooklyn and New York and their revenge against the Tiltons
         was complete. Ostracized by Plymouth Church, Elizabeth Tilton died in 1897, lonely and blind, at the home of her daughter
         in Brooklyn. The influence of Beecher's wealthy parishioners in journalistic
         circles prevented Theodore Tilton from earning a livelihood and he fled to Paris where he lived in poverty, writing poetry,
         and playing chess.Beecher,
         despite his continued popularity in Plymouth Church and as a lecturer, did
         suffer from the scandal. The religious newspaper he edited, the Christian
         Union, lost a significant number of subscribers and the publishing firm
         that depended for most of its profit on the sale of Beecher's books went
         bankrupt. Though respected and popular until his death in 1887, Beecher never again enjoyed the same universal reverence of
         the prescandal days. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>