<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00092</field>
      <field name="title">from Women and Marriage in Nineteenth-Century England</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="text">1. "The English upper classes were sexually
         permissive throughout the nineteenth century, not (as is often suggested) only
         in the Regency period; and women generally expected the same sexual freedom as
         men after they were married. What changed during the century was that they
         became much more discreet about it. The Regency aristocracy did as they
         liked: as Dorothy Marshall wrote, 'Indifference to the pain of others and
         sexual laxity were accompanied by a verbal coarseness and frank acceptance of
         bodily functions which the middle class of the time, and late generations,
         found deeply shocking (Marshall, Industrial England, 1776-1851 (1973))'"(89).2. "The most widely read of all foreign authors
         in
         England (except perhaps Goethe) was the French writer George Sand, though the
         middle class was afraid of her neutral presentation of free, in the sense of
         illicit, love. By the 1840s free love in England was associated in the public
         mind with Bohemian circles. Bohemians, originally meaning gypsies, had come to
         mean 'those of Society who lived outside society'. There were rumours and much
         speculation about the 'Phalanstery' at Royal Hill House, Queen's road,
         Bayswater, where in the 1840s George Henry Lewes and his wife Agnes were said
         to have lived in a co-operative household run on Fourieresque principles with
         the Thornton Hunts, the Gliddons, and the Samuel Laurences. The writer Eliza
         Lynn Linton was introduced to the Phalanstery when she came to London in 1840, but she did not describe the arrangements in
         detail. She wrote, 
         
         At the time I first knew these
         people they were living in a kind of family communion that was very remarkable.
         Sisters and cousins and brother — some of the women married, and with
         yearly increasing families to which they devoted themselves; others single and of
         general domestic utility all round — clubbed together their individuality and
         their resources and made a kind of family.
         
         The lack of convincing evidence about sexual relations
         between the members of the commune makes it difficult to know whether free love
         was practiced or not" (215). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>