<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00001</field>
      <field name="title">from "Love in the Garden: Maud, Great
         Expectations, and W.S. Gilbert's  Sweethearts" 
      </field>
      <field name="setting">garden</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="text">1."The garden is a central and sacred space in Christian mythology. Of the three
         crucial events of human history, two—the birth of the race into innocence
         and the fall of the race into sin—are located in the garden; only the final
         redemption, which returns humankind to the very bosom of God, is reserved for a realm
         beyond Nature" (761).2.". . . Walter E. Houghton observes in The Victorian Frame of
         Mind, 'When the religious emotions of worship were denied a divine object,
         they could readily turn to a human one, to a hero or a heroine; and romantic love,
         called on to fill the vacuum, could take on a new fervor and importance.' But, while
         the fervor may have been new, spawned by a desperation that now drove the search for
         salvation, romantic love had long been endowed with a particular importance when
         placed within the confines of the garden. As Terry Comito asserts in The Idea of the Garden in the Renaissance: 'what is shared
         by
         monks, poets, philosophers, lovers—even...constructors of artificial
         perspective—is a nostalgia for Paradise. Gardens set aside for poetry or
         contemplation or love all participate in a glamour appropriate to sacred places; and
         conversely, activities so apparently distinct as poetry or contemplation or love take
         on, through their association with gardens, the aspect of a single quest, a turning
         outward to the world, a search for an equilibrium in which mind and thing constitute
         one another in a creative blossoming like that of the first Garden.' Yet, like
         religion, such ceremonies of innocence were bound to be drowned in the scientific
         deluge of the mid-nineteenth century. Romantic love, in a garden setting, is featured
         prominently in three works of the period: Alfred, Lord Tennyson's Maud, completed in 1855, Charles Dickens's Great
         Expectations, serialized in 1860 to 1861; and W.S. Gilbert's play Sweethearts, produced in 1874. And, by the end of the brief
         nineteen years that separate the first from the last of these, neither love nor the
         garden is assigned the same spiritual significance as it was before" (765-66).3. [In Maud], "the speaker's attempted entry
         into the garden is
         the climax of his story. He has previously seen and spoken of Maud in this garden but
         has never tried to cross its boundaries. However, on the night of the ball hosted by
         her brother, he intends to change this:For I am not invited,But, with the Sultan's pardon,I am all as well delighted,For I
         know her own rose-garden,And mean to linger in itTill the dancing will be over;And then, Oh, then, come out to meFor a minute,
         but for a minute,Come out to your own true lover,That your true lover may seeYour glory also, and renderAll homage to his
         own darling,Queen Maud in all her splendour.He has actually entered the forbidden precincts by the time that he rhapsodizes
         his
         way through the serenade that is the poem's best-known section—'Come into
         the garden, Maud.' In the context of his own myth, the speaker's audacious actions
         are equivalent to nothing less than an attempt by postlapsarian man to storm the
         guarded gates of the earthly paradise and there embrace his own
         salvation—personified for this speaker by Maud—in the here and
         now of this world. But this trespass into 'Eden' ironically evokes that great enemy
         of salvation, Milton's Satan. It is thus not surprising that the result of the
         speaker's action proves not to be redemption but another fall, for it is now that he
         does the Cain-like deed of killing Maud's brother" (769-70). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>