<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00027</field>
      <field name="title">The Farmer of Inglewood Forest</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="setting">boudoir</field>
      <field name="setting">garden</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene Two: Villain repeats rape attempt and commits suicide when victim is rescuedFitzmorris rose earlier than usual,
         his head aching from the last night's debauch.  In order to reduce
         his spirits to some degree of calmness, he walked out into his garden, and was
         apparently lost in thought when Anna, leaning on Julia, crossing the path
         before him, and for a time banished his reverie:— "Abroad so
         early!" said he; "I am fortunate this morning!" at the same
         time offering to place her arm under his. "May I flatter myself you will
         breakfast with me?""I came merely to try my
         strength, Sir," returned Anna, withdrawing her hand, "as I propose
         going to town to see Mrs. Fitzmorris to-day.""You jest surely!"
         answered he; "you cannot think of putting your health to so dangerous a
         hazard, or that I am so little sensible of the value of my charge as to permit
         so improper a step!""I was intrusted, Sir,"
         replied Anna, "to Mrs. Fitzmorris's care; I am not afraid of
         fevers, and as Miss Editha is not here —""I will, on my honour, fetch
         her in two days," interrupted he; "but favour me, charming Anna, by
         dismissing  your servant; I have something to communicate which requires
         your private ear.""I hear no subject,
         Sir," replied Anna, "that needs concealment, and for myself would
         only entreat that you will permit one of your domestics to fetch me a chaise
         from Hounslow.""And will you favour me with
         no answer to what I requested yesterday," said he, angrily, "since
         I must speak before this black devil?""You call devil black massa?"  interrupted Julia. "Negro call devil white; me believe
         no colour,
         only bad heart make devil—wicked conscience hell.""Damn you," exclaimed
         Fitzmorris, losing his temper; "I merit this for permitting you to
         torment me after what passed in Jamaica.""Ah! much pass dere, massa; if you forget, your memory no so good as Julia's."Fitzmorris
         raised his hand, and was
         only prevented from striking her by the presence of Anna.— "I
         see," said he, "I have nothing to expect, and shall act
         accordingly; yet let me inform you, Madam, that to Mrs. Palmer only will I
         resign you, she, perhaps, may be more sensible of my attention than you
         are."With these words he turned away in
         a rage, and soon regained the house, leaving Anna astonished at his brutality,
         and shocked to find herself in the power of so bad a man.Fitzmorris saw Anna in the
         afternoon in her own apartment; he attempted as before to send away Julia, but
         in vain, liberty had made her bold, and she now openly despised the tyrant,
         whose frown had heretofore made her tremble.From Anna he was convinced he had
         no favour to expect; he saw he was detested, and anger, as much as love,
         stimulated him to revenge the affront. He had been particularly favoured by the
         ladies, and was enraged to find her blind to those attractions that had subdued
         so many, never considering that her heart might be pre-engaged, or that he was
         no longer so young, or possessed of so attractive a person as formerly, though,
         to confess the truth, his dissipated life, more than age, had caused the
         alteration."I have no time to
         lose," said he to his colleague in vice; "and it is but labour lost
         to try gentle means; force and fear can alone conquer so obstinate a spirit;
         she shall find I am not to be trifled with:  'Sdeath have I lived
         until now to be vanquished by a girl! beside, should I let her escape, she
         would but relate what has passed, and make me ridiculous. By Heaven I will bear
         her to France, and there, wife or mistress, her choice shall determine.  I
         have nothing to fear in this case but the tongue of her mother, and that, until
         I can make all secure, I will keep at a distance. She has no heroic brothers,
         but if she had I care not; my arm never yet failed me, nor do I fear it
         now.""I must confess,"
         replied the valet, "I am not quite so sanguine in this business as I have
         been in some, here I have had the honour to serve you. Mrs. Palmer is rich, and
         will doubtless spare no pains or expense to discover her daughter.""True, nor no expense to heal
         her reputation; for who will believe she was not consenting to the elopement? 
         Besides, the young vixen herself will soon be glad to salve so desperate a case
         with the old remedy, matrimony. But enough of this; prepare me post-horses
         to-morrow night by nine o'clock; I shall settle all my business in the
         day.  You must ride forward and obtain relays, and give out in case of
         question that I am conveying an imprudent daughter to France. We shall reach Dover early in the morning, and will go directly
         on shipboard to prevent all
         alarm.""But what, Sir, do you mean
         to do with Julia?""Damn her, if it was not for
         her infernal yells on the road I would take her too, if it was only for the
         pleasure of putting her overboard into the sea.  As it is, we will lock
         her up, and leave her under the charge of your sister, whom you must command as
         she values her place, not to release her until the next day.""But Miss Editha, Sir, and
         your son?""Pish, if my sister gets
         well, the girl will naturally return to her, and I may make a merit hereafter
         of sending for her abroad.  As for the boy he cannot be better than at
         school, therefore no more questions, but prepare to obey me.""After so many proofs of my
         attachment, Sir," replied the man, "I shall not now forfeit your
         friendship.""After so many proofs of my
         gratitude, I hope you will not," answered the master.With these words the worthy pair
         separated for the night.In the morning all was preparation
         for the intended expedition. Fitzmorris wrote to his sister who was yet in a
         very precarious state of health, that immediate business demanded his presence
         in a distant part of the kingdom, and entreated that, when it should be
         convenient, she would again take the care of Editha. To his son's preceptor
         he like sent, signifying his intention that he should remain at school until
         they heard farther from him.  He also settled his domestic economy for the
         country with his housekeeper, who was the valet's sister, and remitted an
         order to his attorney to discharge his house in town, together with the
         domestics. Thus all was prepared, and Fitzmorris looked on his success as
         certain.Julia, whose eyes and ears were
         attentive to all that passed, was not unmindful of the more than usual business
         that seemed in agitation, but which, perhaps, had made no material impression,
         had she not heard the valet and housekeeper in close conversation, the former
         with a bitter imprecation cursing the new folly that actuated his master,
         declaring it was the last he would be engaged in, concluding with saying,
         "The pitcher goes often to the well, but at last comes home broken. Never
         had man such devilish warnings and hair-breadth escapes; but it is all in vain,
         they only, I think, make him more daring, and for this attempt on Miss Palmer
         —"His eye at that instant met the
         figure of Julia, who was standing in the doorway; but uncertain whether she had
         heard, and concluding that if she had, she could make nothing of it, he turned
         the discourse to common occurrences until her departure.Julia had but just related to Anna
         what she had heard when Fitzmorris sent his compliments, and desired to be
         admitted. It was now afternoon, and he had been endeavouring to drown thought
         in wine, he therefore behaved with less caution than formerly, urging his suit
         with much vehemence, until at length seeing the trembling Anna terrified, and
         almost ready to faint, he desisted, and left her alone with Julia."Oh, my God, protect
         me!" cried Anna, "What can I do?  Surely, if you love me, you will
         not deny my request. The attempt you heard them mention, and his behaviour, all
         conspire to show I have no time to lose; let us then this very night privately
         leave the house; I am strong, and can walk a great way; neither am I without
         money; Heaven will, I am sure, protect us, and we shall reach home in
         safety,""Wid all my heart,"
         replied Julia.  "Ah! me hope some friend come before now.""It is impossible they could
         reach here, had they even come post, before to-morrow or the next day; and oh!
         Julia, what may not happen in that interval!  No, I will brave the worst,
         sooner than remain longer under this hated roof."They then determined, as soon as
         the house should be settled for the night, to endeavour to escape, and reach
         Hounslow on foot: — "From whence," said Anna, "we will, my
         faithful Julia, procure a chaise, and travel all the way post; by morning we
         shall be safe from pursuit, should we even be followed, but that I think
         improbable, as Fitzmorris will be uncertain of our route."This resolution supported the
         spirits of Anna during the evening, in the course of which Julia made up a
         little bundle of necessary apparel, which she proposed to take with them.At length the clock struck nine,
         and an instant after a chaise drove into the court. Anna scarcely breathed,
         though she thought it impossible it should bring any one from Inglewood; but
         all her hopes vanished, when a moment after Fitzmorris desired to be admitted.
         "I am sorry, charming Anna," said he,  "to be the
         messenger of bad tidings; but Mrs. Palmer is taken ill at Derby, and has sent
         to require your immediate attendance.""Preserve her, merciful
         Heaven!" exclaimed Anna, "I will fly to her; the fatigue she has
         undergone has killed her, and I shall be deprived of my dearest friend.""I received the intelligence
         near an hour since," returned Fitzmorris, but could not assume courage to
         declare it to you: I, however, immediately ordered a chaise for your
         conveyance, and, with your permission, will accompany and deliver you safe to
         her.""Julia will be
         sufficient," replied she, recoiling at his offer; "I have no fear
         but for my beloved mamma.""Excuse me, I will not trust
         you alone to the dangers of the night, for I presume you will depart
         immediately. Julia can follow in the morning by the stage. Come, you lose time,
         all is prepared," concluded he, presenting his hand.Anna drew back, and paused for a
         moment, while Julia replied — "No leave Missey, me run after coach
         sooner den be leave here behind.""Has my dear mamma sent no
         letter, nor yet her servant to accompany me," demanded Anna, fixing her
         soft but inquiring eyes on Fitzmorris."No," replied he; "a
         horseman brought the message, and departed immediately for London.""It is strange,"
         answered Anna, pausing, "I should have thought that — but come,
         Julia, we will go, and I can but thank Mr. Fitzmorris for all his
         kindness.""On my life,"
         interrupted he, impatiently, "you shall not go unprotected.""Heaven will protect
         me" replied Anna, raising her eyes: "No action of my past life has,
         I trust, made me forfeit that blessing.""Doubtless not,"
         answered Fitzmorris, with a sneer; "but in this case it delegates its
         power to me. Come—come—on my honour I will guide you in
         safety.""Slender barrier!"
         said Anna, aside. The discourse which Julia had overheard recurring fresh to
         her memory; then turning to Fitzmorris, with as much firmness as she could
         assume, she added:  "Pardon me, Sir, for declining your offer; but,
         indeed, I will not go without Julia.""By my soul but you
         shall," returned he, losing his patience, and stamping with rage:
         "I wished to woo you to love and happiness, but will not be trifled with;
         and therefore now throw off the mask, and boldly tell you, that I am
         determined, all resistance is vain, you must, and shall accompany me.""Oh, God! protect me!"
         cried Anna, trembling; "then, perhaps, my dear—dear friend is not
         ill.""I neither know nor
         care," exclaimed he, rudely seizing her hand: "She is an old woman,
         and fit only for worms meat, while you glowing with youth and beauty....""Unhand me, monster!"
         screamed Anna, at the same time releasing herself and flying to Julia, who
         clenched her fists, and grinning horribly, placed herself before her, bearing
         no indifferent resemblance of a fury defending an angel."No, go widout like,"
         sputtered Julia, almost inarticulate with passion: "Bad white man—wicked
         Christian....me die before let take away Missey.""Die then and be
         d—d," exclaimed he, at the same time with unmanly brutality
         striking her over the face (which was instantly covered with blood) with such
         force as caused her to recoil several paces, and but for the timely succor of
         Anna she must have fallen to the ground."Monster! 
         Villain!" screamed Anna, rending the air with her cries: "Murder us
         together for we will never separate.""I have business for you
         living!" replied he, tauntingly; "resistance is
         useless."  With these words, like a fell kite seizing a dove, he
         snatched up his prey, and in spite of her cries and resistance, bore her down
         the flight of stairs into the hall, covered as she was with the blood of Julia,
         who, from the blow, lay senseless on the ground."For Heaven's Sake,
         Sir!" exclaimed the valet, who was waiting in the hall, —
         "cover her with a cloak, it will not delay a moment. See, she has
         fainted." —And, indeed, Anna, exhausted with the exertion she had
         made, had suddenly became inanimate, and now lay motionless in
         Fitzmorris's arms.The door of the hall had been
         opened in readiness, as Fitzmorris descended the staircase.  At that
         instant William Godwin and Reuben arrived, and rushed in, having heard the
         screams as they alighted from their horses at the gate, there being no one to oppose
         their passage, the postillion alone being on the outside. The first object that
         presented was Anna covered with blood, and apparently dead in
         Fitzmorris's arms. Reuben, his eyes sparkling with rage, flew to him, and
         in a moment, with the vigorous arm of undebauched youth, snatched, in spite of
         resistance, the senseless Anna from his grasp, while his father seconded his
         efforts by knocking down the valet and seizing another villain, who came to the
         assistance of their infamous master.Fitzmorris, whose fury knew no
         bounds, finding himself deprived of Anna, hastily drew a pistol from his
         pocket, and levelled it at William.  At that instant their eyes
         met—they became fixed as statues, the guilty Fitzmorris recoiling a few
         steps, and dropping the pistol from his enervated hand."Is it possible," at
         length exclaimed William, "that my eyes do not deceive me?  Doth the earth
         yet shudder with thy impious weight?  Degenerate monster! guilty of every crime
         that disgraces human nature! The death of thy own daughter was alone wanting to
         complete the number! Oh, murdered, child of the sweet Agnes! I here devote
         myself to revenge; the ties of blood I tear from my heart, and even here on
         earth shall thy detested father pay the dues of offended justice."Daring as Fitzmorris, or rather
         Edwin, was in vice, he appeared petrified with horror, rolling his haggard eyes
         around, and, gnashing his teeth with anguish."She is not dead, my father!
         she breathes, and will yet live to bless us," exclaimed Reuben, in a
         transport."For that Heaven be
         praised!  But say," demanded William, turning indignantly towards
         his brother, "what does this mean?  You cannot surely have been so
         abandoned of God as to have injured this innocent!""She at least has not been
         abandoned of God," replied Edwin; "her person is as uncontaminated
         as it is beautiful. But speak, for I have but little time to lose:  Did
         not you say she was the child of Agnes?" "I did," returned
         William. "In the horror of the moment prudence was lost, and I now will
         conceal the truth no longer; she is your own daughter, but build not upon that,
         for no human power shall snatch her from my protection; therefore attempt it
         not, I warn you, it will be in vain.  As soon as she recovers we will be
         gone. You have my pity, and Heaven forgive you. Oh! will no warning move that
         obdurate heart?  Surely, the meeting with Emma would have deterred any other but
         yourself from vice for ever, and made them penitent as she was."            "Well
         — well — well — you know that too; but enough.  Answer
         me a few questions; and I will swear never to attempt removing the child of my
         Agnes from you."            "I
         ask no oath," replied William; "but propose your questions, Anna
         recovers, and I am in haste."            "And
         so am I," returned Edwin, frantically.  "If Anna is the child
         of Agnes, whose infant did I see dead on her bosom?"            "Mine,"
         answered his brother, "an unhappy innocent, who even in the womb fell a
         sacrifice to your offences by the anguish they caused its mother."            "Enough!"
         cried he, striking his forehead.  "One more question, and then
         farewell for ever — Who is Mrs. Palmer?  Oh! that subterfuge
         destroyed me!"            "The
         present owner of the estate upon the Forest, and a more than parent to Anna,
         whom she received from her dying mother."            "The
         mystery of the ring is then explained," said Edwin, without regarding his
         brother.  "No warning, could, indeed awaken me!"  Then
         turning towards Anna, who was almost recovered, but in silent terror clasping
         Reuben's neck, he viewed her with attention for some minutes; then, with
         a look of despair, rushed out of the room. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>