<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00064</field>
      <field name="title">This Brief Tragedy: Unraveling the Todd-Dickinson Affair</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="text">The plain evidence of
         her own extensive and meticulous records shows that Mabel Todd was never quite,
         or was never only, the enthusiastic young innocent whose charm and talent
         impressed so many in Amherst. Her true outlook on people and affairs was much
         more calculated, and it had in addition a strangely skewed or unbalanced
         quality. In her journals, diaries, and letters she is shown to have
         been—stating the fact in its mildest, nontechnical form — a thoroughly
         self-absorbed, or better, self-contemplating, personality. Her simplest actions
         and opinions, and her ability, apparently unfailing, to captivate all whom she
         met, women as well as men, singly and in groups, were topics of which she never
         tired. Narcissism is the term that inevitably leaps to the mind of anyone who
         becomes at all familiar with the personality of Mabel Todd. Excerpts from
         Mabel's journals have appeared before this, but the selections made, their
         brevity, and indeed their context and framing have tended to obscure, and on
         occasion distort, their true import. There are some documents — those tied to a
         rigid chronology, and of a certain length — that can be rightly judged only
         when scanned in full, or nearly so, and in proper sequence and setting, and this is
         emphatically the case with Mabel's journals. In particular, her revealing
         memory of her first year's involvement with the Dickinson circle no descriptive
         summary or partial quotation can adequately reflect. What follows is the bulk
         of her various journal entries between January 1882 (six months after she first
         reached Amherst) and September 1883 (eight months after the first clash with
         Susan), a total of fifteen passages. Enough commentary is supplied to set each
         entry retrospectively in the flow of the narrative unfolded in the previous
         chapter, and to clarify offhand references.As will become
         evident, the story told by these particular passages, when studied in sequence
         and in detail, is very different from anything that has so far appeared in
         print. So much may be stated at the outset.It
         was at the home of her parents in Washington, D. C., that Mabel made her first relevant journal entry, on January 20, 1882.
         While it does not concern the Dickinsons directly, it is essential to an understanding of all that would develop in Amherst.
         On this day as Mabel lifts her pen she is twenty-five years old and has been
         married for three years. She has one child, a daughter named Millicent, whose
         care up to now has been shared with her mother and grandmother in Washington. That morning her husband David has just left
         for Amherst to resume his teaching
         duties at the college, a fact Mabel notes in opening the entry. She goes on:Everybody has been, as it were,
         "running after me"; and I have felt not the dawning, but the growth,
         intensely, of a wonderful social power. I cannot explain it, but I feel
         strength and attractive power, &amp; magnetism enough to fascinate a room full
         of people—which I have done, actually.On New Year's day I was almost
         intoxicated with this power—which so overflowed and filled me, that our hundred
         callers seemed too small a company for it to be exercised upon.... I
         have flirted outrageously with every man I have seen—but in a way which David
         likes to have me, too. I have simply felt as if I could attract any man to any
         amount. If the power is wholly bottled up I get restless and feverish like a
         caged eagle, but if I exercise it in the innocent ways I
         do, I am satisfied — only that I sigh for more worlds to conquer.
         . . .I have found such a dear friend. It is
         very romantic, and I cannot tell exactly how I came to find it yet; but Mr.
         Elliot, who was introduced to me by Madame Buel before my marriage, has always
         been very kind and complimentary to me. He has always paid me very pleasant
         attentions, and has, I know, admired me much. Lately he has seemed to avoid me
         a little, but the few times I have been with him, he has said very beautiful
         things to me, and I have found out that he is trying to outlive a strong love for
         me! ... He is very lonely and says no man could reach his
         age—thirty-two—without having wished very much for love and tenderness.... When
         I thanked him for something he did for my comfort he said, "I would do
         anything for you," in a tone wherein a suppressed intensity of feeling
         [was] so strong that it was pitiful.... Heaven forbid that I should desire to
         exercise my power upon him. Although love and adulation and admiration are
         agreeable to me, and it will be a great trial to act simply, when I know I could
         keep him by using my attractiveness.There followed
         an interruption of five weeks before her next entry, a long one, which was made
         after her return to Amherst. Dated March 2, 1882, it concerns almost entirely
         the first of her Amherst conquests, the susceptible Ned Dickinson, then a
         sophomore at the college. By now Mabel has become a regular at the Evergreens,
         and she and Ned have
         been well acquainted for five months. To what extent her extreme portrayal of
         Ned as a badly moonstruck admirer is accurate for the moment may be left open.
         That he was strongly attracted to her at this time is true, but whether she
         knew so early that he was an epileptic cannot be said:I have been at Mrs.
         Dickinson's a great deal since my return, &amp; she admires me extravagantly,
         &amp; praises me to Ned and Mattie all the time, as a sort of model for them.
         She appreciates me completely, and I love and admire her equally. She is a rare
         woman, &amp; her home is my haven of pleasure in Amherst. Also, Ned and Mattie
         have run in to see me every day since my return. Then, too, I had not danced at
         all since my marriage, until this winter here, &amp; I found that my waltz step
         did not go very well with the present fashion of waltzing so Ned undertook to
         teach me to get it better. Whenever I went to see Mrs. Dickinson there was a
         waltz in the hall with Ned, while Mattie played.... I never dreamed that Ned
         was more than ordinarily fond of me, or that I could be doing him any harm by
         allowing him to be my Knight Errant whenever David could not attend me....I have known now, for a
         few days, that he [Ned] worships the very ground I walk on. He does not care
         now for general society, and only wants to sit near me and watch me. He is only
         a boy—only twenty—but he is the most graceful host in his own house that I have
         ever seen. And he is so very manly. . . .He told me the other day
         that until now his mother had more than filled every want in his life, but that
         he had come to think so much of me that it is his only thought ... he knows he
         is restless and inattentive to his studies &amp; thinking of me every
         moment.... One day he burst out with—"Oh! Mrs. Todd, I'm afraid I love
         you, &amp; what shall I do?" I consoled him as well as I could by saying
         that he would get over it very soon.... He says he would do anything for me — that
         I could twist him around my little finger—that he would go off and kill
         somebody if I bade him.I told him that I was
         very fond of him and would always use what he called my "unlimited
         influence" over him for his good. "Ah!" he said, "What you
         are kind enough to call your affection for me is nothing for you to give; but I
         love you as you love your husband!" . . .What can I do? He had
         plunged in irrevocably before I suspected it, and every time he sees me gay or
         brilliant in society, or sweet and tender to his mother, or tired after
         dancing, or kind to him, or in fact whenever and however he sees me, it adds to
         his love for me, &amp; I cannot help it. He is perfectly innocent &amp; pure
         about it, and has not an idea that he ought to root it out ... he cannot see
         that it is wrong, &amp; I certainly shall not open the knowledge of good and
         evil to him....Poor boy, poor boy! It
         is all an amazement to him.  He is absolutely perfect in his habits,
         &amp; is really a very strong and manly fellow, &amp; remarkable in many ways.
         But that Heaven should bless me with the virgin love of a young man who hardly
         knows what has come to him, is very remarkable.... His mother does not know of
         it all, of course, and she thinks it is such a fine thing for her young son to
         have a "brilliant and accomplished married lady for his friend," and
         likes to have him pay me attention. She worships Ned, &amp; I don't know what
         she would do if she knew just how far he appreciates having me for his friend.
         What is there in me 
         which so attracts men to
         me, young and old? I am deeply grateful for the power, and I hope I may use it
         for the good of those who succumb to it; but I really do believe in my heart
         that it will be many years before Ned gets entirely over it; and I am vain and
         selfish enough to be glad.Three
         weeks later, as Mabel prepared for another Washington trip, she expanded on the
         situation with Ned and also gave the first
         definite sign that her husband acquiesced in her flirtations. The passage
         offers no slightest indication that as Ned's ardor grew, Mabel did anything to
         discourage him. Blandly she accepted his daily morning visits, remaining
         unconcerned that his college studies were suffering. During these weeks, as is
         made clear later in the journal, at Ned's request and while they are in the
         house together, she sometimes wears his Alpha Delta Phi pin:
         He grows tremendously fonder of me every
         day. Every morning, regularly, after my first hour of [piano] practice is over
         he comes in, &amp; he says the whole day goes off exhilaratingly &amp; joyfully
         after that few moments of talking with me, &amp; perchance touching my hand ...
         he says his thoughts are so constantly with me that he cannot think of his
         recitations, nor in fact of anything else. He takes me to drive regularly
         twice a week, and would like to every day. . . . It is almost fearful to see
         his love for me growing so from day to day. I think it is well that I am going
         away so soon. But I am really very fond of him &amp; I shall miss him very
         much— &amp; he does not yet begin to realize how much he will miss me. It would
         be mean and underhanded to write down the tender and loving things he says to me—for they are only for me,&amp; no one else ought
         to hear them. Of course I tell David in general about it, but my darling husband has perfect trust &amp;
         confidence in me and tells me to act my own pleasure about these things.Mabel may have
         told her husband "in general" about her dalliance with the young son
         of their good friends, and David may have shown himself up-to-date and
         open-minded about "these things." But those few words deserve to be
         highlighted, for they mark the Todds' first steps in what was to prove a
         steady, at times frightening process of moral disintegration. It would end,
         years later, with David lamenting that "adultery ruined my life," and
         adding, in what seems a curious puzzlement, that it was all "like a
         ghastly dream" (curious, because David's own course as an adulterer was to
         keep steady pace with his wife's). At the time he made those remarks, in
         conversation with his own daughter, he was in New York, an inmate of the Bloomingdale
         Insane Asylum.Early
         in April 1882, after having been back in Amherst briefly, Mabel again departed
         for Washington. Ned also left Amherst that day for a visit to Boston (perhaps
         only a pretext), and he arranged to accompany Mabel on the train as far as the
         Palmer Depot interchange. A brief journal entry, made at her parents' home a
         few days later, shows that during the train ride Mabel had rather enjoyed
         exercising her "power" over Ned. She had even, it seems, toyed with
         the idea of an actual indiscretion:The dear boy felt more badly about my
         leaving with every mile. He to all appearances was talking in a lively mood to
         me on the train, but I could see that he felt dreadfully. I never had a more
         intense lover, and I don't know what to do about it.... Of course I am a woman,
         and I am older than he, and I know more of life than he, and I can help him
         somewhat against himself, and I will try. But that is all I can do. Of course,
         I do care for him—the wonderfully chivalrous devotion he showed me could not
         fail to affect me—but I love David so wholly that I am not afraid to trust
         myself entirely to him.... I told him that I did care for him, and he said it
         ought to be enough to make him happy forever.In Washington the persistent Mr. Elliot resumed his attentions, calling on Mabel
         regularly. In
         a journal entry dated May 5 she notes with obvious satisfaction that her friend
         "walked in the woods with a party of us the other day, &amp; I know
         that he cares more than ever for me. He longs inexpressibly for love and
         tenderness, &amp; I am just as sorry for him as I can be."Expected
         to attend the Amherst College commencement in early June, as were all the
         faculty wives, Mabel made a hasty return, planning to stay only a week. She
         took it for granted that whenever her husband was not available she would be
         escorted and amused by the adoring Ned. But for once he failed her, and even in
         the controlled phrasing of the journal her anger at his defection shows
         plainly:I am just now somewhat provoked with
         Ned, because after telling me that Commencement was nothing to him without me,
         &amp; that the moment he came in the house he had to find me, &amp; that he was
         not easy one moment when I was out of his sight, he went off to Pittsfield with
         a lot of young people just for fun, for a day or two. Of course I do not regard
         him as my property &amp; bound to entertain me all the time, but it was
         thoughtless of him to rush off so when I was just leaving his mother for a
         return to a prosaic boardinghouse, and would be a little blue anyway. But he
         shall not know I cared in the least, &amp; I don't, except that I should have
         liked a drive or a horseback ride to cheer me up a little today. He asked me if
         he should go when the matter was suggested, &amp; I said "by all
         means," very heartily. . . . I do miss him very much, truly, but I said
         goodbye radiantly.After
         commencement she went back immediately to her parents' Washington home, staying
         until early August. Except for a brief passage of general remarks on June 30, she
         did not write in her journal all summer. When next she opened its pages, on
         September 15, a month after her return to Amherst, the result was another revealing entry, but one in which the interest has
         suddenly
         and dramatically shifted: it is no longer young Ned who interests her but his
         father.Some rather delicate
         maneuvering was involved in this deft transfer of attention, and its surface
         manifestations, at least, may be glimpsed in the many briefer entries Mabel
         made in her daily diary for those weeks in which she was neglecting her journal.
         A brief look at the shadowy tale told by the diary, as the summer of 1882 waned
         in Amherst, will serve as an instructive prelude to the journal entry of
         mid-September.Attending
         lawn teas and musical evenings at the Evergreens, taking part in several
         outings, Mabel was with the Dickinsons nearly every day from mid-August to
         early September. The day of her arrival back in Amherst, August 6, she was
         greeted by Susan, as she noted, "with a most whole-souled 'Welcome home,
         Toddy,' which was lovely." After an evening of fun at the Evergreens on
         the thirteenth, Austin walked her home, and he did the same thing again a week
         later, when Mabel noted in her diary, "I like him immensely."
         September 6 proved for her quite a busy, not to say demanding, day: she was at
         the Dickinson house early in the morning and was back again late at night
         giving, as it seems, equal time to father and son:This morning I had a long horseback ride
         with Ned. We went up on the Leverett road, and after about six miles we stopped
         under the trees while he smoked. We sat on the fallen leaves &amp; had a
         pleasant rest. Then we started on again, making at least a ten miles' circuit
         in all.... I went to the Dickinsons' in the evening, &amp; sat alone on the
         veranda with My Dickinson senior about an hour, discussing religion, thought,
         &amp; so forth. I admire him.Next evening she played
         whist at the Evergreens, with Ned and Mattie. Then on the two following days,
         September 8 and 9, she once more divided herself between father and son, and it
         is here that Ned starts to fade from the picture.Twice
         on the eighth she was in Ned's company, first in the morning in town, then in
         the afternoon for a row on the Mill River. She took supper with the Dickinsons that evening, and when her husband, after working
         late, came down to escort her
         home he found himself superfluous: "Mr. Dickinson walked home with me,
         &amp; Ned with David." Next morning everyone went off in a crowd to spend
         the day in the country, and it was while on this outing that Austin—obviously
         responding to a signal from Mabel—made his first overt, if tentative, move in
         her direction:Mr. Dickinson took Grandma &amp; David
         &amp; Millicent &amp; Gilbert in the carriage to Sugar Loaf. I came later with
         Ned and Mrs. Dickinson &amp; Mattie. Near the foot of the mountain we all
         alighted except Grandma &amp; Millicent. I walked up with Mr. Dickinson. He
         cares a great deal for me. Ned followed leading one of the horses.It was the next day,
         September to,
         that Austin took Mabel to pay her well-known
         first visit to the other house. "I sang there, and the rare,
         mysterious Emily listened in the quiet darkness outside," she wrote later
         in her diary (it is more probable that the mysterious Emily was upstairs at the
         bedside of her invalid mother, while both listened to the music). After the
         visit to the Mansion the two returned to the Evergreens for the evening, and
         that night both Ned and his father again walked her home.
         Mabel's plans
         for another sojourn in Washington called for her to leave Amherst on September 12, so
         on the day before she left there was a farewell party at the Dickinsons',
         Austin picking her up at the boardinghouse. The two walked down the hill
         together, and as they reached the gate of the Evergreens, Austin made his
         second move. Before going in to join the others, he suggested, they might take
         a short stroll, just the two of them. As is made abundantly clear from other
         records, during that stroll Austin in some way admitted to feeling a very
         personal and not at all neighborly attraction for his companion. Mabel's
         response, again according to later records, was prompt and open encouragement
         of this new suitor, demonstrating not the least concern that he was the husband
         of her good friend and the father of two youngsters in whose home she
         frequently found amusement. Next day, even as the Todds prepared to leave, Austin was on hand—in the afternoon he took Mabel
         off for a carriage ride, and a few hours
         later saw her to the station.With
         so much as background, the journal entry of September 15, made in Washington, will come as less of a
         surprise:
         Everything
         is so joyous, &amp; my circumstances are so pleasant. And dear Mr.
         Dickinson—Ned's father—is so very fond of me. It was one of the proudest
         moments of my life when he told me that I had more ideas which were congenial
         to him than any other person he ever met. For I most extravagantly admire him.
         He is in almost every particular my ideal man. He is true—so true that one look
         into his blue eyes when I first met him caused me to think involuntarily—"He
         could be forever trusted. "I did not really know until lately that he is
         a very sensitive man, for he has a very strong, almost bluff way with his
         business relations. But he says he has suffered more than he can ever tell from
         sensitiveness....He
         and I are the fastest friends. To think that out of all the splendid and noble
         women he has known, he should pick me out—only half his age—as the most truly
         congenial friend that he had! ...The affection I
         had for Ned is as nothing compared to the strength of interest and admiration I
         have for his father. Indeed, Ned &amp; I have tacitly abandoned our little
         affair, for Ned said it was getting to be with him so strong as to be rapidly
         getting beyond his control ... that if he should let go his fierce hold of
         himself he could not answer for anything.... It was a dreadful thing to start
         up such a fellow as he is, for he has a very strong nature. But as I said
         everything pales in connection with him beside the glorious character of his
         father, &amp; his wonderful interest in &amp; affection for me.A
         disappointment overtook Mabel in Amherst, in early November, when she was
         refused permission to accompany her husband on a government astronomical
         expedition, an exciting event eagerly anticipated. The journal of November 10
         shows that when her husband was about taking his departure, she consoled
         herself with the thought that Austin had given his promise to look after her: "Ned
         has been very devoted — more so than ever. But my only real joy in staying is
         because Mr. Dickinson is here, &amp; looks out for me, &amp; has me on his
         mind.... He is delicate beyond expression, and tender &amp; watchful &amp;
         caretaking." The subject of Austin's tender caretaking she expanded on
         four days later. Almost incidentally she also records the fact that, at last,
         the sensitive father had wholly supplanted the callow son:I am
         not alone very much, for everyone is very kind to me, especially the
         Dickinsons, &amp; of them especially Mr. Dickinson. Mattie &amp; Ned are very
         bright and brilliant, but being so very young are much on the surface.... To be
         sure Ned was very much in love with me once, and would say and do all sorts of
         things to &amp; for me now, if I were a particle responsive.... I really did
         care for him a great deal, in one way, some time ago, but I have not a particle
         of that romantic interest in him left. The point where, if he had known it, he
         could have made me have a very permanent and deep affection for him is passed
         long by, and I am delighted to see how entirely he has passed out of my
         life.... It was in the middle of last summer that I decided to give Ned nothing
         more in the way of my regard, so I put him out. About that time, or, no,
         somewhat later, his father and I began to discover that we had a great many
         ideas in common, and from that began a friendship which is the most true and
         satisfying that I ever had. He thoroughly appreciates and understands me, and
         nothing is too subtle and delicate for him to see. The way in which he cares
         for me &amp; looks out for my comfort &amp; happiness is beyond expression.Telling its own curious
         tale, of course, is the afterthought in that passage ("or, no, somewhat
         later"). With that disingenuous phrase Mabel actually tries to make it
         appear that before settling her affections on the father, she had completely
         finished with the son. But the attempt, of course, is belied by her own
         previous journal entries. Here, strangely, she has told a barefaced lie to
         herself.As the year 1882
         ran out, the friendship with Austin had become "my chief joy," and
         Austin himself "the most true and satisfying friend I ever had. I respect
         and admire him boundlessly. I wish I could write of it but it is beyond
         writing." Even as she exults (yet again) in her happy and accomplished and
         "brilliant" life, she indulges in a curious, and sadly prophetic, linkage
         of Austin and her husband: "David has had exceptional success &amp; is
         coming to me within a few days—and my admirable, noble, strong, true Mr.
         Dickinson is entirely devoted to me."Before she could
         make another journal entry, the January 1883 trouble with the jealous Sue
         erupted. While that initial unpleasantness was fairly soon calmed by the
         "frank" talk between the two women, bad feeling broke out again
         several weeks later. The following journal passage was written by Mabel on
         February 3, within days after the second outbreak. It is a crucial entry and
         requires careful reading, for Mabel, far from setting down objective truth, is
         seeking to excuse her own conduct. Whatever it was exactly that the idealistic
         Ned chanced to see going on between his father and Mabel—certainly more than
         walks and rides—it was enough to disgust as well as thoroughly disillusion him:I am
         not very happy just at present ... the root of all my trouble is that I allowed
         that affair with Ned to progress too much. I got over all especial
         feeling for him in the summer, and supposed he did for me.... But he is of a
         very jealous disposition, &amp; began to think I must care more for his father
         than himself. So he got angry and went to his mother with some very mean
         things—among other things telling her that I was an awful flirt, &amp; having
         allowed him to fall in love with me, I was now tired of him &amp; was trying
         the same thing with his father. Of course this troubled her very much, &amp;
         she began to look about....Ned is excessively polite to
         me, but I am angry enough for anything with him—and I am so sorry for it all.
         As for his father he is as staunch &amp; true as still [sic] to me — but I do
         not see him except very rarely. It is better not, I suppose. But I like him
         just as much as ever, &amp; he does me. Of that I am absolutely sure.When she made her next
         entry, dated April 10,
         1883, Mabel was again in Washington, and David had once more left home on
         business. Emily and Vinnie had both by now entered the fray on their brother's
         behalf—Emily with her two notes, Vinnie in person — hoping to placate the angry
         Susan and restore family harmony. The information Mabel now set down about the
         marriage of Austin and Susan was supposedly told her in the preceding two
         months by Austin himself. Her daily diary does show that the two were together
         on a dozen occasions during that period, including five times when they walked
         or rode alone, allowing ample opportunity for the sort of intimate talk
         reflected in the journal. But, again, the charges Mabel makes here must be read
         with caution—or better, must be read in a mood of high skepticism. Consciously
         or otherwise, she has certainly both exaggerated and distorted whatever it was
         that Austin told her. Austin himself in such a situation scarcely provides
         disinterested testimony.David
         started this morning. I felt terribly to leave him. We have been so much to
         each other since our separation last fall, while he was in California, that it
         seemed to me I could not let him go. We have been together constantly, &amp;
         the companionship is inexpressibly sweet.Mr.
         Dickinson has told me a great many things since I last wrote, and he is more
         absorbed in me than I can write. It seems he &amp; his wife have not been in
         the least happy together, although for the sake of appearances, &amp; for the
         children, they have continued to live together. Notwithstanding the utter lack
         of love between them, the fact that he is so interested in me has stirred her
         beyond the power of words to express. And she makes it pretty dreadful for him
         at home. I have seen some developments in her character which are very
         startling. But I do admire her in most respects very much. We have courteous
         relations, but that is all. This whole thing has weighed my spirits down
         dreadfully—it is the cause of my languor and weakness &amp; lack of enthusiasm.
         There are aspects of it which hurt me terribly. Aside from that, everything is
         joyous—except my darling David going away today. I have nearly wept my eyes out
         over that.Mr.
         Dickinson's life has been very barren, &amp; I understand him thoroughly. He is
         the rarest nature I have ever met. Honor &amp; purity &amp; pathos &amp;
         strength. And it has come to mean all the world to him—his feeling for me. That Austin did in some manner complain to Mabel
         about one or another aspect of his home life,
         whether or not justified, is probable. That he used such phrases as "not
         in the least happy" and "utter lack of love," or that he claimed
         he had stayed with Susan for the children's sake, are things quite improbable.
         Such a serious estrangement—given what is known of the Dickinsons' twenty-five
         years together before Mabel's arrival on the scene—simply lacks all support.
         Further, the unnamed but ominous-sounding "developments" in Sue's
         character, considering the manner in which her wayward husband was behaving,
         could not have been so startling as all that. It would have been much more
         startling—and infinitely more revealing—had Susan failed to show some fire.With
         David out of town, Mabel and Austin now went a step further as they proceeded
         to make plans for a rendezvous out from under the knowing eyes of Amherst. It was to take place in Boston in the summer, she
         coming down from her vacation
         resort in New Hampshire, supposedly for a day of shopping, he going up from Amherst. Their meeting place was the horsecar
         stop on Winter Street, the date June 30. As
         arranged, the tryst came off smoothly, the two not parting until late evening,
         when Mabel, as she wrote in her journal, "went back to Winchester on wings
         as it were." Less than two weeks later Austin wrote his first private note
         to Mabel of definite date, and it shows that Susan had not been fooled by her
         husband's Boston excursion. It also shows that Austin, like the good lawyer he
         was, had his defense prepared—a straightforward claim, of the Sam Bowles variety,
         that he had nothing to hide in arranging to meet a friend in another town, even
         if that friend happened to be an attractive young married woman. The session
         with Sue he describes took place the day after his arrival back home from Boston:At
         breakfast next morning the question came square—after leading up
         properly—"Did you see Mrs. Todd?" I had anticipated it and said at
         once, "Certainly, that was what I went to Boston for." This
         unhesitating frankness was somewhat stunning and the rally wasn't prompt. When
         it came it was, "She told me she was to spend a few days in Boston before going to Hampton and I concluded you would see her."
         I replied yes I
         said I did. This ended it. There has been no allusion to it, or you, since. I
         don't know whether on the whole I am supposed to have lied about it or not, but
         you know I spoke the truth. Surprisingly, Austin's bold tactic worked, to an extent at least, and by the date of this letter,
         July 12, 1883,
         matters at the Evergreens had more or less settled down again. For the
         remaining days of July it was decided that Austin would join his family,
         evenings after work, at a holiday spot in nearby Shutesbury, returning to town
         each morning. With that, Vinnie and Emily, watching anxiously from next door,
         must have concluded with relief and no little satisfaction that peace had at
         last been restored or was on its way. In the minds of all concerned the summer
         months of 1883 began to drift by at their old, serene pace. But
         once again the aura of peace was woefully deceptive. An unusually long, frank,
         and introspective journal entry Mabel made in mid-September at Hampton, her first in more than four months, warns only of
         a rapidly gathering storm. Its
         opening paragraph introduces still another Washington admirer, one who briefly
         rivaled the romantic Mr. Elliot:I
         remained in Washington until about the middle of May, having a very brilliant
         time, as I always do there. Dr. Eaton was especially devoted to me. But I have
         had all the experience I ever want with jealous wives, so I did not let it
         progress very much....[In
         Amherst in June] Mrs. Dickinson was still very chaotic and not sweet. Another
         unfortunate incident occurred which irritated her. So beyond a call or two
         exchanged, where everything was courteous, we had no relations. Mr. D. kept me
         perfectly informed of every aspect of her mind, and everything she said, and
         was himself marvelously thoughtful and tender to me. Fifty little
         kindnesses &amp; more he poured upon me. He is the truest and most loyally
         affectionate of men. But he has had a wretched life at home, in spite of the
         perfect house &amp; grounds, the carriages &amp; horses, the pictures &amp;
         luxuries generally. He is equally lovely to David, and the sweet and trusting
         relationship between us three is one of the most beautiful things that ever
         came into my life—to say nothing of the rest of it....[David]
         has been so tender &amp; thoughtful of me through my sadness owing to Mrs.
         Dickinson and Ned, and has constantly devised so many little diversions and
         pleasures, that I should be indeed most ungrateful if I did not respond &amp;
         show forth my shining blue sky again. And I do—my happiness has come back
         again. With two such rare men to do for me, &amp; to hold my happiness above
         everything in their lives, how could I be sad! ...Mrs.
         D. is so well understood there that the fact of her breaking with us [the
         previous spring] cannot redound to her credit. I have never spoken about it to
         anyone, but a lady said to me that it was a matter of wonder with my friends
         that there had been no break before. It was Mrs. D's way to have some
         "fuss" on hand most of the time. Notwithstanding all that I hear
         about her, I do admire her mind. And she stimulates me intellectually. And I
         cannot blame her for her frantic efforts to regain the respect &amp; love of
         her husband — which she has not had for more than twenty years. She has
         tried in every way, and she cannot move him — coldness, hauteur, affectionateness,
         commanding, indignation—nothing succeeds. And now she sees that he is
         immovable, that his affection for David and myself is permanent, and she can do
         nothing more. So she yields gracefully &amp; takes us in partially again. But
         she will not wish him to see much of me.Mr.
         D. says she fears me—the first woman who has really crossed her path—fears me
         because she knows I have stirred him as no other woman has 
         ever 
         stirred
         him. Though she has gone her own way all these years, and has never tried to
         keep him, doing all the time things morally certain to do more than alienate
         him from her—yet now when she sees that he has turned to me, &amp; finds peace
         &amp; content &amp; congeniality in being with me, she chafes &amp; raves &amp;
         cannot endure it. The greatest joy in life lay beside her for years, &amp; she
         never moved to retain it, even pushed it from her. Now it has left her
         irrevocably, &amp; she sees the awful loss &amp; void. She has the husk from
         which the soul is departed. And I cannot blame her, nor do other than deeply
         pity her.But
         when I see the holy joy rise in his eyes when he sees me, and the youthful
         beauty glow over his face, and contrast it with the apathetic, careless
         indifference which was his leading characteristic for months after we first
         knew him, I cannot but rejoice for the happiness I have brought him. For the
         first time in his life he lives, he says. And I admire him &amp; respect him
         &amp; love him. So David does also....Yes, oh! yes, life is full
         of joy &amp; sweetness. The sun shines, the dear crickets chirp, the red leaves
         flutter down, the sparkling sea sings to me. People love me—books, music, painting
         minister to me, and I love it all so deeply!Crying out for
         prompt comment is that admiring compliment to herself that Mabel puts into Austin's mouth, the statement that "for the first
         time in his life he lives." If Austin really did say that, or anything like it, and said it in full awareness, then he
         stands convicted not only of insincerity but of the classic
         male ploy in such affairs. The many fervent letters he wrote to Susan during
         their courtship thirty years before, all of them at that moment reposing in the
         attic of the Evergreens, pour out his romantic feelings in precisely the same
         hurried, overblown style as anything he was to pen later to Mabel. The only
         difference detectable between earlier and later love letters is of the sort to
         be expected from the span of years, and from the fact that the youthful ones
         were written with marriage in mind.While a few
         select portions of this outspoken entry have been quoted and commented on
         before, its deeper implications have managed to elude notice. There is, to
         start with, the rather chilling self-indulgence of Mabel's pleasure in having
         "two such rare men to do for me, &amp; to hold my happiness above
         everything in their lives." Here she proclaims that in her own eyes at
         any rate, her conquest of Austin is more or less complete, nor does she give
         any thought to the harm her victory may do others, notably the three Dickinson
         children. Equally disturbing is her remark about Sue being "well
         understood" in Amherst society. The real thrust of this statement, in its
         own subtle way not a little shocking, does much to fix the truth of Mabel's
         underlying character. Here she expresses a confident hope that Sue's prior
         reputation in town for personal embroilment will now happily prove useful to
         her, supplying a cover for her own budding affair with Austin. Any disturbance
         that might be created by the wronged wife, in other words, will be put down
         among townspeople to Mrs. Dickinson's supposed prickly temper, her liking for a
         fuss, leaving Mabel unscathed and unsuspected.The other charges
         leveled at Sue in that passage—principally blaming her for a supposed two-decade
         crumbling of her marriage—on the available evidence may, again, be dismissed.
         No doubt over the years the marriage had known its share of rough times, and
         perhaps by the eighties affection on one side or the other had worn thin,
         waxing and waning, like most. But it was not any noticeable strain in his
         homelife that had produced Austin's "apathetic" air. The real cause
         was something even sadder, that same oppressive burden that so often weighs
         down a certain kind of man as he reaches his mid-fifties, an awful sense of
         having fallen short. When Mabel came to know him, the talented, ambitious Austin had already begun to feel an almost panic
         sense of failure, a conviction that the
         grand promise of his youth would not be realized. More than any temporary
         disappointments as husband and father, what finally made him want to stray from
         his marriage vows was bitter regret over all his broken dreams of success, as
         he put it, among "men of the world and affairs" in the larger sphere
         beyond Amherst.That is a
         dangerous mood to lay hold of any man. All too often his resentment, smoldering
         beneath the indifference, prepares him to fall a ready victim to circumstance.
         At that moment, in the early fall of 1883, fate had in store for Austin, and
         for all the Dickinson clan, one last, truly devastating circumstance, the death
         of little Gilbert. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>