<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00086</field>
      <field name="title">Bedside Seductions:  Nursing and the Victorian Imagination, 1830-1860</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="setting">publicspace</field>
      <field name="text">1. "....the nineteenth-century nursing reform movement focused a great deal of attention on the supposed promiscuity of youthful
         pauper nurses
         who were seen as either seducing or being seduced by patients, doctors, and
         medical students. There was an anxiety about the ongoing sexual corruption of
         the old-style nurse that seemed to assume a young, sexually active, and
         seductive, or sexually vulnerable worker. For example, in a rare defense of
         old-style nurses, an anonymous London physician writes to the London Times
         in 1857 that English hospital nurses are 'insulted, if old and ill-favoured;
         talked flippantly to, if middle-aged and good humoured; tempted and seduced, if
         young and well-looking'....The Victorian nursing reform movement consistently expressed the desire to replace old-style nurses
         with either morally groomed pauper girls or 'naturally' asexual, indigent gentlewomen.  For example, in a typical description
         of the morally purifying new-style nurse, E.J.R. Landale writes in 1896 that they should 'be chosen not only for their excellence
         in ward work, but for that higher moral force and excellence which will fit them to rule and influence their subordinates
         wisely, and for their highest good.'  In her Subsidiary Notes, [Florence] Nightengale asserts that:  'none but women of unblemished
         character should be suffered to enter the work, and any departure from chastity should be visited with instant final dismission.'
         This focus on the nurses' sexuality sets the nineteenth-century nursing reform movement apart from traditional British anxieties
         concerning working-class nurses" (36-37). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>