<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00033</field>
      <field name="title">from Trials of Intimacy: Love and Loss in the Beecher-Tilton Scandal</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">popularpress</field>
      <field name="category">history</field>
      <field name="text">Mrs.
         Tilton was the most articulate of them all about this deliverance, perhaps
         because her voyage of self-discovery was the longest, and the most treacherous.
         She testified at great length to the Plymouth Church
         Investigating
         Committee on July 31 — after she and Theodore had spoken privately to the
         Committee (she on July 8 and he on July 10), after she had finally separated
         from him (on July 11), after his published attack on Henry and her as adulterers
         (on July 21), and after Henry's and her initial responses to that attack (on
         July 22 and 23, respectively). Her oral remarks on July 31
         contain an eloquent testament to the power of friendship to reawaken selfhood.
         She called that power "love" and "friendship"
         interchangeably, as she did in her public "card" of July 23, which
         spoke of "my love to my friend and pastor."
         The
         immediate context for her reflections about Henry was the Committee's concern
         about the 
         "Griffith Gaunt" 
         letter
         she had written her husband from Schoharie, New York, in 1871, in which she confessed
         that she had sinned in her knowing of Beecher. It was a potential bombshell
         because unlike the other most incriminating letters, this one was written with
         no coaching or coercion from Theodore. The letter was now a public item, since
         Theodore had reproduced it in his statement of July 21. It was
         "perfidy," "sacrilege," to try "to make my own words
         condemn me," Elizabeth had said publicly two days later of his publishing
         excerpts from eleven of her letters to him. She had seen nothing yet: in August
         he would publish an entire treasury of two hundred of their love letters in the
         
         Chicago Tribune. 
         The 
         "Griffith Gaunt" 
         letter began as follows:Today, through the
         ministry of Catharine Gaunt, a character of fiction, my eyes have been opened
         for the first time in my experience, so that I see clearly my sin. It was when
         I knew that I was loved, to suffer it to grow to a passion. A virtuous woman
         should check instantly an absorbing love. But it appeared to me in such false
         light. That the love I felt and received could harm no one, not even you, I
         have believed unfalteringly until four o'clock this afternoon, when the
         heavenly vision dawned upon me."Had
         you at that time any reference to adultery, or thought of it?" queried a
         committeeman. "No, sir," Elizabeth said. "What did you refer
         to?" "I will try to answer that question." She answered with a
         side-stepping reflection. "The one absorbing feeling of my whole life has
         been Theodore Tilton; neither Mr. Beecher, I assure you, nor any human being,
         has ever taken away from that one fact, my love for turn." It was
         essential groundwork for the emerging legal case (and for her own well-being)
         to establish that her love for Henry had never rivaled her love for her
         husband. It was also important for her to go on record as having had many other
         "friends," male and female. "I felt very great helpfulness in my
         own soul front having had the friendship of Mr. Beecher, and also of other
         people, as many women as men." These opening remarks were not just about
         laying legal foundations. If the Committee wished to understand her tie to
         Henry or anyone else, they had to reckon with the complex love she felt for and
         shared with her husband.The
         gentlemen steered her back to the question at hand. "In your Schoharie
         letter you spoke of your 'sin.' What did you mean by that?"
         "Theodore's nature being a proud one," she said, "I felt, on
         reading that book (Griffith Gaunt, 
         )that
         I had done him wrong, that I had harmed him in taking anyone else in any way,
         although, on looking it over, I do not think but that I should do it again,
         because it has been so much to my soul." Her roundabout response was
         bewildering to the Committee, which kept trying to get a direct answer.
         "Taking any one else in what respect?" wondered a committeeman.
         "I do not think if I had known as much as I do now of [ Mr.] Tilton that I
         should ever have encouraged Mr. Beecher's acquaintance: I think I did wrong in
         doing it, inasmuch as it hurt Theodore." The committeeman must have
         scratched his head, musing on the wandering female or mystical mind. But Elizabeth was only warming up for her hymn to friendship
         with Henry — who was not just one
         friend among many, after all:I do not know as I can make myself
         understood; but do you know what I mean when I say that I was aroused in myself
         — that I had a self assertion which I never knew before with Theodore; there
         was always a damper between me and Theodore, but there never was between me and
         Mr. Beecher; with Mr. Beecher I had a sort of consciousness of being more: he
         appreciated me as Theodore did not: I felt myself another woman; I felt that he
         respected me; I think Theodore never saw in me what Mr. Beecher did.Liking
         what he heard, a committeeman gave her a supportive prompt: "Do you mean
         to say that Theodore put down self-respect in you while Mr. Beecher lifted it
         up?" "Yes," she replied, "I never felt a bit of embarrassment
         with Mr. Beecher, but to this day I never could sit down with Theodore without
         being self-conscious and feeling his sense of my inequality with him."The
         Committee tried again for a pithy answer: "Will you state, in a few words,
         what was that sin which you spoke of in that letter?" Again she gave them
         a both-and response. "I do not think that I felt that it was anything more
         than giving to another what was due to my husband — that which he did not bring
         out, however." Another committeeman: "Do you mean that you thought
         you let your affections, or your regard, or your respect, go out for Mr.
         Beecher unduly, and so censured yourself?" "No, sir," she
         answered. "I do not think I ever felt that, because I did not think I
         harmed Theodore in that; I harmed him in his pride by allowing any one else to
         enter into my life at all; I think that was sin." Her sin, she thought,
         lay not in 
         undue 
         affection — not in some excess of
         passion or attachment but in the initial reception, the first opening of—the gate to her heart. That act of welcome had disrupted
         the surrender of her
         self to Theodore, a surrender required not by law or custom or morality, in her
         view, but by his "pride."In
         her testimony Elizabeth refused to limit herself to the narrow issue of sex, or
         to the narrow logic of either-or, sin or not-sin. Perhaps she was simply-—confused. Perhaps she was thrown by the fact that
         she had indeed had sex with Beecher and couldn't speak of it. Perhaps she was blocked by the knowledge that she and
         Henry had done something physical together that wasn't quite sex but wasn't
         quite not-sex either. Perhaps she had an insight into the tragic tangle of love
         and friendship in which she or her husband — or both — had been destined to
         suffer. What she voiced was clear enough, but it was a paradox: her sin resided
         in her assertion of self in the first place, and yet this assertion of self
         might not be a sin at all. It depended on how one held her action up to the
         light. If it were a sin, she believed she would quite likely sin all over
         again, how ever much she might wish not to hurt her husband.The Committee's
         abortive quest for a straight answer provoked Mrs. Tilton to make another claim
         about herself and her husband, one that helps us see the full sweep of her
         attachment to Henry. "When you speak of your sin," a committeeman
         asked, "you do not mean to be understood as going further than that ['than
         allowing any one else to enter into my life at all']?" "No," she
         replied. "Let me tell you a little more.""Theodore, up to that time,
         in his accusations, would often talk to me by the hour to show me the effect
         that he said he knew I carried about my personal presence with gentlemen, and I
         would become nearly crazy in my conscience; he would say that he knew there was
         no one who carried such an influence as I did; I would say, `Theodore, I do not
         think that is a fact; if I did, I would never speak to another man in all my
         life.'""Did he define that
         influence?" wondered a member of the Committee. "He said I had a
         sensual influence," she answered. "I used to become impregnated with
         this idea of his myself while under his influence, and I wondered if it was so,
         and would think it over and over; he would often talk to me in that way by the
         hour, and try to persuade me that it was true; and then, when I used to get out
         from under his influence, I was perfectly sure that no man ever felt that way
         toward me." Theodore's own fears about her person — that her vivacity was
         a come-on to other men — sent her reeling into self-doubt. That spinning state
         made the deliverance announced by friendship with Beecher all the more urgently
         attractive. He could free her, she imagined, from the ordeal of
         "influence" altogether — from her husband's constraining power and
         from the spectre of her own sensual allure. She would be free of arbitrary
         human controls, subject to God's scrutiny alone.A final set-up
         question by the Committee: "Was there in the sin which you referred to
         anything that was unjust, or that was giving to Mr. Beecher any affection that
         belonged to your husband?" "No, sir; I think that the wifely feeling
         which I gave to my husband was [as] pure as anything that I could give him; there
         was nothing more than confidence and respect which I gave to Mr. Beecher, and I
         teach my daughters that if they give to their husbands what I have given to
         mine they will do enough." The committeemen must have squirmed, for it did
         Beecher's cause no good for her to imply that she had given Theodore only
         some grudging minimum of devotion. They let her continue, and their patience
         was rewarded as she returned to Theodore's fears and their crushing impact upon
         her."I
         would like to have you, gentlemen, realize how very severe that was to me,
         because it has been day after day and week after week — the hearing that that
         was the effect of my presence upon persons; it made me sick and caused me to
         distress myself; it kept me in embarrassment; it was a hard thing to live
         under." Theodore's criticism of her sensual presence extended to her body
         itself. When they were entertaining at home, or out together at public events,
         "I was so insignificant that he was ashamed of me; and I remember
         perfectly in two or three instances of going to hotels, where my being short of
         stature was a dreadful trial to him.... I would have cut off my right arm to
         have been five inches taller; he seemed to be unwilling that I should be as the
         Lord made me." Elizabeth's love for Theodore, by her 1874 account, was interwoven with a longing to
         escape his judgment and the "impregnating" of that judgment within
         her. She had been turning against herself, making his viewpoint her own,
         forcing her very real love for him into the warped channel of assuaging him,
         and protecting them both from what she considered the sinful assertion of her
         self. After Henry took an interest in her, friendship with him promised release
         from the downward spiral of self-vilification and love-as-appeasement. With an
         assist from Henry, she thought, self-creation could replace the self-erasure
         with which she placated Theodore. Henry had the power to make her believe that
         her sin was no sin at all. If Elizabeth was making an accurate assessment of
         the psychic forces at play, Theodore would have taken Henry as a mortal threat.
         For Henry would have been doing much more than "alienating
         affections." He would have been tampering with an intricate system of love
         and loathing, in which Elizabeth loved Theodore and loathed herself.Mrs.
         Tilton was a double-edged sword for the Investigating Committee and its creator
         Henry Ward Beecher. They had to use her to slice up her husband, but they had
         to shield Henry from accidental slashing. Elizabeth alone could destroy
         Theodore's credibility. Yet she was a confessed liar: under his
         "mesmeric" influence, she claimed, she would say or write anything.
         How could the Committee guard against the quite logical deduction that under Beecher's influence or the Committee's she might
         also be lying.  First, by drawing her out
         on the horrible evil (and absolute uniqueness) of Theodore's mind-control over
         her, and second, by encouraging her to get away from him. If Theodore had had
         hypnotic power over her, as she alleged — and as the Committee's "medical
         testimony" attested was "not infrequent" and "consistent
         with an honest mind"—then her testimony, given two weeks after she
         escaped his irresistible authority, could be trusted. On the same day (July 11)
         that Beecher had announced the creation of the
         Investigating Committee, Elizabeth had awakened Theodore to tell him she was
         moving out. "I rose quietly," she wrote in her public card of July
         23, "and having dressed, roused him only to say: 'Theodore, I will never
         take another step by your side. The end has indeed come!'" She went to stay
         with Maria and Edward Ovington, Plymouth Church stalwarts, and never lived with
         Theodore again.In
         the fall the Boston Journal reported that Mrs. Tilton had become a
         recluse. Even before leaving her husband in July she had abandoned her weekly
         Sunday afternoon song-leading at the "Christian Association rooms"
         and given up her "general Christian work." She was still at 143 Hicks Street, the Ovingtons' home, and her children were staying
         in New Jersey with her
         mother. Hicks Street was six substantial blocks west, toward the East River, from the Tiltons' Livingston Street home. She
         was now in the heart of Brooklyn Heights, with its brick Greek Revival homes from the 1820s
         and 1830s, and its quiet gaslit streets. Yet even there she was pursued and
         "greatly annoyed by the curious who crowded on her privacy. She went from
         place to place, and was even called by another name to escape attention. But
         all in vain." The press joined the gawkers in invading her privacy.
         Rebuffed in their attempts to get an interview, the papers focused on locating
         a picture. "The greatest effort has been made to get a correct likeness of
         Mrs. Tilton. One house offered $1,000 for a photograph. There are but two known
         ones in existence. One of these Mr. Tilton has, and keeps on his parlor mantel.
         When anyone speaks of his wife, he takes it down and shows it. The other is
         held by a distinguished New York photographer. He has resisted the glittering
         offer for the picture. He regards the disposal of it as a breach of faith that
         would hurt his business."But
         what does she look like, Boston Journal readers still wished to
         know. "Nothing that has appeared gives the slightest idea of this now
         famous woman," wrote the reporter. "She is a small, fragile woman,
         dark complexion, low in stature, girlish in look, her hair parted in the centre
         and falling in ringlets behind — looking more like a school-girl of 18 than a
         matron of 40." Beecher made an identical assessment in his testimony to
         the Investigating Committee, but he saw character reflected in physique.
         "Childish in appearance, she was childlike in nature." Her spiritual
         purity emanated from this youthful innocence. He should be forgiven, he
         thought, for failing to notice the gradual transformation of her interest in
         him from "due" to "undue" attachment. "I would as soon
         have misconceived the confidence of her little girls as the unstudied affection
         she showed me." For Beecher there was nothing wrong with the original
         attachment that had suddenly struck Elizabeth, on the afternoon of June 29,
         1871, as sinful. Her complex and still evolving story concerned a sin that
         paradoxically bestowed new life. Guilt and innocence, remorse and renewal, were
         mysteriously but undeniably entwined. His simpler story
         was about a spontaneous affection that she allowed, gradually and tragically, to
         spin out of control. Like Theodore's, Henry's 1874 story about himself was a
         tale of faultlessness. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>