<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00087</field>
      <field name="title">The Flirt's Tragedy:  Desire Without End in Victorian and Edwardian Fiction</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="text">1. "Desire, particularly as opposed to romantic love,
         has been the subject of intense, widespread critical scrutiny in the last
         twenty years in the works of postmodern Continental theorists and those writing
         in an Anglo-American context. Roland Barthes's strict distinction between
         desire as opposed to romantic love has been extremely influential. Thus Robert
         Polhemus, implicitly expanding on Barthes's distinction, has used the term
         'erotic faith' to describe romantic love, noting that throughout European
         culture narratives of love have served to imagine 'forms of faith that would
         augment or substitute for orthodox religious visions.' Critics addressing the
         strictly formal dimensions of literary texts, as well as theorists seeking a
         more politically pronounced emphasis on how fiction operates in a matrix of
         cultural determinants, have turned to desire as a crucial locus of meaning.
         Rene Girard's exploration of 'triangular desire'; Barthes's intensely personal
         endorsement of 'bliss' and 'pleasure'; the hymeneal 'dissemination' evoked by
         Jacques Derrida; Julia Kristeva's semiotic, signifying stress on process; Leo
         Bersani's focus on the fluid fragmented staging of desublimated carnality;
         Judith Butler's elaboration of sexuality as sheer 'performance'; Tim Dean's
         Lacanian exploration of desire as fundamentally impersonal—have all accentuated
         an eroticism that is mutable and unstable, in which functional desire emerges
         as a historical aberration. For many postmodern critics, that aberration is a
         scandalously successful nineteenth-century literary invention that has come to
         legitimize patriarchally and heterosexually structured social scenarios" (2-3)2. "....In a male-dominated order, in which
         marriage was
         prized as a satisfying resolution, flirting represents a reckless adventurism
         that violates—and sometimes succeeds in undermining—the smooth functioning of
         middle-class interests and aspirations. Within the context of
         nineteenth-century fiction, that violation often emerges as a subtly intimated,
         dissident gesture at the center of a larger, apparently well-settled narrative of
         connubial bliss" (4). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>