<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00199</field>
      <field name="title">La Regenta</field>
      <field name="setting">dance</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="nationality">spanish</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One:  Flirtations and coquetry at a dinner partyThe guests sat down.  The only earmarked places were those on either
         side of the marchioness and the marquis.  On the right of Doña Rufina sat Ripamilán, and on her left the canon theologian;
         on the right of the marquis sat Doña Petronila Rianzares, and on his left Don Victor Quintanar.  All the other guests sat
         wherever they liked, or wherever they could.  Paco sat between Edelmira and Visitación, the judge's wife between 
         Ripamilán and Don Alvaro, Obdulia between the canon theologian and Joaquín Orgaz, Don Saturnino Bermudez between Doña Petronila
         and the Vegallanas' chaplain.  On Don Victor's left was Don Robustiano Somoza, the dashing doctor to the aristocracy, who
         tied his napkin around his neck with an elegant knot.Before the others had their soup the marquis helped himself to a great
         plateful of fried pilchards while he talked to Doña Petronila Rianzares about the demolition of St. Peter's Church, an idea
         which she considered to be ignominious.  Meanwhile, the guests made themselves busy with the choice, varied, delicious hors-d'oeuvres.
         It was an informal meal, they all knew that, and customs of which they were all aware were to be respected.  Vegallana always
         started with his pilchards; he would devour a few dozen and then rise from the table and discreetly disappear from the room.
         Following long-established usage, everyone pretended not to notice the marquis's absence, and meanwhile the soup arrived and
         was served.  When the master of the house returned to his place he was a little pale, and perspiring.'All right?' muttered
         the marchioness, formulating the question more with her look than with her lips.Her husband replied with a nod which meant:
         'Perfectly!'  And helped himself to a generous bowlful of turtle soup.  The pilchards were no longer inside him.Another mystery,
         like Balmes on the ceiling.The marchioness liked to concoct her own singular hodgepodges, to which, again, nobody any longer
         paid attention.  She ate lettuce with almost every dish and sprinkled vinegar or spread mustard over everything.  Her neighbours
         at table knew about her whims and looked after her solicitously, showing their long experience in the preparation of her vinegary
         mixtures.  While Ripamilán, who was on his feet and jerking his head to and from as if it were mounted on a spring, held a
         heated argument with his dear friend Don Victor, he mixed the marchioness's third salad with all the dexterity of a smooth-running
         machine; and the lady let the diminutive canon proceed with a task, trusting him yet not taking her eyes off his hands, though
         certain of his complete success.'My dear sir!' cried Ripamilán as he dissolved salt in oil and vinegar on Doña Rufina's plate
         by beating it all with the point of a knife.  'My dear sir, it's my belief that Señor Carraspique had every right to do so,
         and I don't know where you pick up these subversive ideas, ideas I have never heard from your lips in all these forty years
         we have known each other.''Pray listen to me, you rogue-priest!' exclaimed Quintanar, who was in excellent spirits and beginning
         to feel rejuvenated.  'I am perfectly certain of what I am saying, and neither you nor any other eighty-year-old ladies' man
         like you can give me lessons in morality.  But, as a liberal...'"Twiddle-Twaddle!''More of a liberal today than yesterday,
         and tomorrow more than today.''Bravo! Bravo!' shouted Paco and Edelmira, who were also feeling youthful, and they made Don
         Victor clink glasses with them.It was all in jest.  Neither was Don Victor more of a liberal today than yesterday nor did
         he use formal words like 'pray' when talking to Ripamilán or consider him to be a ladies' man.  It was just his way of expressing
         the cheerfulness imparted to everyone by the clear wine gleaming in a fine glass, glinting gold, shining with the mysterious
         iridescence of a magic grotto—the amaranth and deep violet hues of the claret in which the most venturesome rays of the sun
         bathed after filtering through the green foliage which curtained the windows on the courtyard side.  Why not be merry?  Why
         not laugh and play the water and trees swaying in the wind, and the frenzied singing of garrulous birds; from the courtyard
         windows came perfumes carried by the breeze, which had set all the leaves jingling.  The fountains were an orchestra accompanying
         the boisterous banquet.  Pepa and Rosa—one blonde and the other as dark as a mulatto, both wearing brightly coloured but well-cut,
         close-fitting dresses, cheerful, jaunty, as clean as an ermine, and sinuous and rustling as they walked—waited at table with
         grace, speed, good humour and skill, showing the men teeth like pearls and bending over with the dishes with coquettish humility.
         According to Ripamilán, such a luncheon served in such a way was pure milk and honey.All the people sitting around the table
         responded to the cheerfulness in the air.  They laughed, shouted, lavished attention on each other, complimented each other
         by means of discreet antiphrastic gibes.  They all knew that an insolent attack meant its very opposite:  it was shameless
         flattery.The gaiety in the dining-room was echoed in the kitchen.  When Pepa and Rosa returned there with the dirty plates
         they were still smiling at the scene which they had just left.  In the whole house there was but one completely serious personage:
         Pedro the cook.  His turn to enjoy himself would come later, but for now he thought only about his responsibility.  He was
         coming and going, directing operations as if in a battle, and from time to time he looked in to the dining-room door and corrected
         minor mistakes in the service with magnetic looks which Pepa and Rosa obeyed like automata, well-disciplined like old soldiers
         in the midst of all the expansiveness and hubbub.After Pedro, the least boisterous people in the house were the judge's wife
         and the canon theologian.  From time to time they looked and smiled at each other.  De Pas said a word to Anita now and again,
         leaning over behind the marchioness so that Anita could hear him, and at such moments Don Alvaro would observe them, silent,
         frowning, unaware that Viitación, seated by his side, was watching him.  With a discreet touch of her foot the bank clerk's
         wife brought him out of his reverie.'Things are getting hot, eh?' said Visita.'What, what?' asked the marchioness, who was
         eating without a pause, happy in the midst of the racket.  'What's hot?''The peppers, my lady.'Don Alvaro was grateful to
         Visitación for her warning and immersed himself once more in the general chit-chat, hiding as best he could his boredom, which
         he described in his own mind as 'sovereign.''What a strange thing!  He was touching the dress and at times even feeling one
         of the knees of the judge's wife, the woman he desired—and when would another opportunity like this present itself?—yet he
         was bored.  He believed he was wasting his time and he was certain that the luncheon would not further his plans and that
         the judge's wife was not a woman who became merry on such occasions.  At least not yet.''It would be most imprudent to make
         any more moves.  Were I to take advantage of the state of excitement induced by the meal, I should be in her bad books for
         ages.  I am sure that she's feeling a little worked up, too, that she's thinking about my knees and elbows, as I am about
         hers; but the time is not yet ripe to turn such physiological advantage to account.  This opportunity is no opportunity at
         all.  We'll wait and see what happens at El Vivero, but here there's nothing to be done—however strong the urge.'  And his
         behaviour towards Ana became more courteous; he applied his attentions to her in the distinguished style which he could assume
         when it suited him, but he went no further than that.  Visitación could not believe her eyes.  'What was happening?'  When
         nobody was looking, she stared at Mesía in astonishment, opening her eyes wide and puffing out her cheeks, a gesture which
         meant:  'You milksop—I'm flabbergasted to see you acting like a little mouse after I sat next to her with the best of intentions.'Mesía's
         sole answer was to move closer to the bank clerk's wife and press his foot on hers, but she received him with kicks, giving
         him to understand that 'she was an old soldier' and was standing by the principle implicit in the slap she had administered
         the previous afternoon.Paco did not dare press his latest cousin's foot, but he had her under his spell with the jokes he
         was telling her, the jokes of a well-bred young gentleman who had lived, and indeed lived it up, in Madrid.  What was more,
         he smelt so nice, smelt of such fresh things, such elegant, refined things, too!  In her village Edelmira had thought a great
         deal about the Young Marquis, whom she had seen two or three times when she was still a little girl and he was an adolescent.
         Now it was a different Paco she was seeing, and he far surpassed everything she had dreamed and imagined; for he was better-looking,
         roseir-faced, more cheerful, fleshier.  That afternoon the Young Marquis was wearing a suit of fine alpaca, the colour of
         pease-pudding, a piqué waistcoat of the same colour, and a pair of summer slippers which Edelmira considered to be the height
         of elegance, although they would have suited Turkish feet better.  Her cousin's trinkets, his coloured shirt, his necktie,
         his magnificent showy rings, his hands, which looked like the hands of a young lady—they all captivated Edelmira, who was,
         like Paco, very fond of everything clean and healthy.Little by little Paco had been bringing one of his knees closer to the
         girl's skirt, until he finally felt something solid yet yielding; he was about to withdraw but the girl remained so calm that
         he left his leg there as if he had forgotten it.  In her innocence Edelmira was so hard to shock that Paco could have gone
         so far as to press his foot upon hers and she would not have complained unless it hurt.  'Besides,' thought the girl, 'it's
         the custom here.'  Tradition recounted much greater marvels about the house of her uncle and auntie.Obdulia, sitting opposite,
         directed occasional languid looks at the lively couple.  She remembered the winter sun of the previous afternoon.  Paco had
         already forgotten it!  He only had thoughts for that fresh young beauty, smelling of grass and rosemary, brought from her
         village to gratify his senses.  But after devoting a moment of wistful reflection to her follies of the previous day, the
         widow turned back, provocative and suggestive, to the canon theologian.  She was trying to turn his head with her perfumes,
         with her drop-curtain glances and, indeed, with all those resources at her disposal which could be employed against such a
         man and in such circumstances.  De Pas responded to Obdulia's coquetry with ill-concealed indifference and did not even feel
         grateful for the burnt offering which she was making, for his sake, of Joaquín Orgaz's attentions, received by her with obvious
         disdain.Joaquinito was seething with indignation.  'That woman is a...' and he thought of a Flamenco word.  'Well she's making
         passes at the vice-general, isn't she?'  The other guests either did not notice or pretended not to notice these goings-on,
         but Joaquinito, who had a deep personal interest, paid them his closest attention.  He did not surrender, however, and persisted
         in flirting with the widow and turning a blind eye to what was happening between her and the canon.  Usually Obdulia and Joaquinito
         got along well together.  'Lord! he'd even had a date with her in a coal-hole once!  True, he couldn't boast of having taken
         that stronghold, that dismantled stronghold.  He hadn't enjoyed her supreme favours—yet, but still, advances, pledges, or
         whatever you liked to call them—he'd had those all right.  Ah! if he achieved complete victory, as he expected to, he'd make
         her pay for all her flighty disdain, her changes of mood, the humiliation of being put in second place behind a Holy Joe!"The
         man bereft of all hope, overwhelmed by disillusionment and dying of sorrow, was Don Saturnino Bermudez.  After the events
         in the cathedral, where he had thought that he had taken such long strides forward (at the great expense of his conscience),
         he had not seen Obdulia again until that morning.  But when he had approached her to tell her how great had been his sufferings
         in her absence (without mentioning, however, the constipation which had obsessed him and kept him in bed), when he had made
         to recite into her ear the short speech which had prepared—in the style of a novel written by Feuillet in a sacristy—she had
         turned her back on him not once but three or four times, making it clear that non erat his locus, that he would only be tolerated
         in church.'Such was Woman!  Such, in particular, was this woman!  Wherefore love women?  Wherefore pursue the ideal of love?
         Or rather, wherefore love real women, women of flesh and blood?  Better far to dream—to continue dreaming.'  Thus thought
         the melancholy Bermudez, a man always sad in his cups, while he replied in a cold absent manner to Doña Petronila Rianzares,
         who was busy delivering a whispered panegyric on her idol the canon theologian.  From time to time Bermudez gazed at the judge's
         wife, whom he had loved in secret, and from time to time he gazed at Visitaciñn, whom he had also loved, as an adolescent,
         during the period when she was rumoured to have climbed from a balcony together with a gentleman-friend.  Not even Visitaciñn
         had ever heeded him in the slightest; not once had she screwed up her small eyes at him in the way which, she believed, captivated
         men.  It was not that the ladies of Vetusta scorned Bermudez, it was just that they saw him as a sage and a saint, but not
         a man.  Obdulia had discovered the man in him but had immediately disparaged her discovery. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>