<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00091</field>
      <field name="title">from "Lost and Found: Once More the Fallen Woman"</field>
      <field name="setting">piano</field>
      <field name="setting">garden</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="text">1.
         "Yet perhaps no work is more closely intertwined with
         Rossetti's Found and his very conception of the fallen woman than Holman
         Hunt's Awakening Conscience, signed and dated 1853, exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1854. Despite their striking differences
         of interpretation and structure,
         or perhaps because of them, one can see these works as pendants, opposing
         visions of a single moral issue: rising versus falling, salvation versus
         damnation, Christian optimism versus Christian or crypto-Christian despair, the
         larger oppositions in both cases growing out of intimate personal experience,
         probably involving Annie Miller [model and sometime mistress of Hunt], and couched in the pictorial language of
         realism. Like Rossetti, Hunt reinforces the credibility of his painstaking
         visual realism with an equally painstaking scaffolding of symbolic incident: 
         at the crucial instant of conscience awakening, a cat releases a bird beneath
         the table, and light—reflected in the mirror in the background—quite
         literally dawns in the unspoiled garden outside the St. John's Wood sitting
         room. That parlor's unsavoriness is attested by such elements as the print of Christ
         and the Woman Taken in Adultery on the wall, the dozing cupids on the
         clock, the birds stealing grapes in the wall design, as well as by what Ruskin
         admiringly described as the "fatal newness" of the furniture. The volume of
         Noel Humphrey's Origin and Progress of the Art of Writing on the table
         may be a covert reference to Hunt's educational program for his 'fiancée,'
         Annie Miller, the original model for the painting. Certainly it is no accident
         that the young woman experiencing moral epiphany has rings on every finger but
         the third finger of her left hand" (143,145) 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>