<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00004</field>
      <field name="title">Little Women</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One: Parody of a typical Southworth seduction scene"I don't mean to act any more after this time. I'm getting
         too old for such things," observed Meg, who was as much a child
         as ever about 'dressing-up' frolics."You won't stop, I know, as long as you can trail round in a
         white gown with your hair down, and wear gold-paper jewelry.
         You are the best actress we've got, and there'll be an end
         of everything if you quit the boards," said Jo. "We ought
         to rehearse tonight. Come here, Amy, and do the fainting scene,
         for you are as stiff as a poker in that.""I can't help it. I never saw anyone faint, and I don't choose
         to make myself all black and blue, tumbling flat as you do. If I
         can go down easily, I'll drop. If I can't, I shall fall into a
         chair and be graceful. I don't care if Hugo does come at me with
         a pistol," returned Amy, who was not gifted with dramatic power,
         but was chosen because she was small enough to be borne out shrieking
         by the villain of the piece."Do it this way. Clasp your hands so, and stagger across the
         room, crying frantically, 'Roderigo! Save me! Save me!'" and away
         went Jo, with a melodramatic scream which was truly thrilling.Amy followed, but she poked her hands out stiffly before her,
         and jerked herself along as if she went by machinery, and her "Ow!"
         was more suggestive of pins being run into her than of fear and
         anguish. Jo gave a despairing groan, and Meg laughed outright,
         while Beth let her bread burn as she watched the fun with interest."It's no use! Do the best you can when the time comes,
         and if
         the audience laughs, don't blame me. Come on, Meg."Then things went smoothly, for Don Pedro defied the world in
         a speech of two pages without a single break. Hagar, the witch,
         chanted an awful incantation over her kettleful of simmering toads,
         with weird effect. Roderigo rent his chains asunder manfully, and
         Hugo died in agonies of remorse and arsenic, with a wild, "Ha! Ha!""It's the best we've had yet," said Meg, as the dead villain
         sat up and rubbed his elbows."I don't see how you can write and act such splendid things,
         Jo. You're a regular Shakespeare!" exclaimed Beth, who firmly
         believed that her sisters were gifted with wonderful genius in all
         things."Not quite," replied Jo modestly. "I do think 'The Witch's Curse,
         an Operatic Tragedy,' is rather a nice thing, but I'd like to try
         'Macbeth,' if we only had a trapdoor for Banquo. I always wanted to
         do the killing part. 'Is that a dagger that I see before me?'"
         muttered Jo, rolling her eyes and clutching at the air, as she had
         seen a famous tragedian do."No, it's the toasting fork, with Mother's shoe on it instead
         of the bread. Beth's stage-struck!" cried Meg, and the rehearsal
         ended in a general burst of laughter."Glad to find you so merry, my girls," said a cheery voice at
         the door, and actors and audience turned to welcome a tall, motherly
         lady with a 'can I help you' look about her which was truly delightful.
         She was not elegantly dressed, but a noble-looking woman, and the
         girls thought the gray cloak and unfashionable bonnet covered the most
         splendid mother in the world. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>