<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00048</field>
      <field name="title">"Passion's Perils"
         
         
      </field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">arrangedmarriage</field>
      <field name="theme">popularpress</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">history</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="text">PASSION'S PERILSA Heartless Seduction Case in which the Son of a Proud Boston Millionaire FiguredIN NO ENVIABLE LIGHTHe Basely
         Betrays a Beautiful and Confiding Girl, but is Forced to Unwilling ReparationAT THE DEATH-BED OF HIS VICTIMBoston, Mass.,
         June 1.—One night,
         not more than a week ago, there died in a cheap boarding and lodging house on
         Warrenton street, in this city, a young lady who had but recently become a mother.
         She has the peaceful gratification, also, of taking her departure for the
         unknown land as a wife, although that event transpired subsequent to the other.
         Hidden in that hovel were the secrets of two proud families in Boston society and the shame and disgrace of one. It is the
         old story, with the added interest
         that the parties to the indiscreet amour were the son and daughter of two of Boston's most respected merchants, the one a
         millionaire. I have the story from one of the
         physicians who attended the unfortunate young mother before she became a wife
         and who succeeded by his cool and deliberate action in making the nameless
         little waif an heir to a large estate.He tells his story thus: I was called upon rather suddenly
         one night to attend a sick woman on a neighboring street. Upon entering the
         room where the patient lay I at once saw by the number of persons who were crowded
         around the bed that a sufferer reclined thereon, and pushing my way through the
         crowd I approached the bedside of the unfortunate. There were present in the
         room three women and one man, and at the moment of my entry they were engaged
         in making frantic efforts to arrest and prevent the violent and spasmodic
         contortions of a fair young woman, the suffering object of my visit. The
         surroundings of the place and the scene itself did not please me. It occurred
         to me to inquire within myself, Why were those people here? Why were they? 
         And how came this girl, so fair, youthful and respectable-looking, to be found
         in such quarters? I first examined the condition of the young woman and found
         that she was suffering from mania.  In endeavoring to ascertain her real condition,
         requirements, &amp;c , I found to my horror that she had bitten off almost half
         her tongue. Her mouth was filled with blood commingled with froth, and the
         pupils of her eyes were terribly dilated. Her features, beautiful in health,
         had become emaciated in suffering. Her condition at once appealed to my
         better nature, and fearing that some great wrong had been committed, resolved
         to sift the matter to the very bottom. I first administered an opiate of
         sufficient strength and quantity as to cause her to cease her gyrations and
         succumb to the more soothing influence of sleep. As soon as I found that she
         had become subdued and quieted I demanded of those present that they inform me
         as to whether or not the young lady had any friends or relatives present.A middle aged lady, whom I had
         overlooked in making my inspection of those present, and who had attracted my
         attention only by her half-subdued sobs, replied that she was a relative in
         fact, the mother of the poor girl martyr. Beckoning her to one side I
         requested her to accompany me into the adjoining room—a request that she at
         once complied with. I told her that before I went any further in the matter I
         must know the whole story, as I was convinced that great wrong had been done.  After some hesitation she consented and stated
         that herself
         and daughter came into Boston about three weeks ago from their home, in a town
         about ten miles out, and, under assumed names, took the lodgings. Her husband,
         she said, was a rich and prosperous merchant in Boston.Last summer my daughter commenced
         keeping company with a young gentleman in our place, the son of a near
         neighbor. We always believed that the young man contemplated marrying our
         child, and in fact we regarded him as an accepted suitor for her hand, and he
         was treated as a member of the family. He visited our home almost daily, and,
         possessing the most complete confidence in his honor and integrity of purpose,
         my husband and myself never subjected him to any surveillance. About two months
         ago (and at this point the poor woman sobbed aloud, evincing thereby her
         extreme grief) my daughter informed me of her unfortunate condition. I at once
         realized the fact that if the public were made aware of her fall from womanly
         grace that my family would be disgraced, and accordingly I determined to conceal her shame.My daughter and myself came to
         Boston, and under assumed
         names we engaged these apartments. Of course they are not what we have been
         accustomed to, but I thought that we would be less susceptible of detection if
         we hid ourselves away from the world. Previous to coming here, however, I
         endeavored by my pleading to induce the father of my daughter's betrayer to
         permit his son to marry my daughter, and thereby satisfy and sanctify the issue.
         But it was of no avail; he heartlessly refused to admit of such a procedure,
         claiming that his son was too young to marry. Five days after we took up our
         residence in this place my daughter gave birth to the child that you saw in the
         cradle. Child and mother were apparently doing well until the third day after
         the birth of her offspring, when the poor little thing began to cry. I saw at
         once that my daughter, for the first time, had realized the disgrace of her
         situation. She was very much affected, and upon hearing the child repeat its
         piteous wail she became pallid and motionless. Her eyes almost started from
         her head, her lips quivered and assumed a purple hue, and she became livid with grief and shame.She became completely crazed,
         and
         in her ravings leaped out of bed and in piteous tones, mingled with the
         bitterness of rage, exclaimed, "My God! My God! My poor darling! Oh, why did I
         bring you into this world to live in the disgrace of having no father's name!" She
         wished herself dead, and in the convulsions which immediately came upon her and
         which have continued ever since she attempted to bite off her tongue, and you
         see she nearly accomplished it. From that time up to the present my daughter has
         been out of her mind. I am almost crazed myself. You have no idea, Doctor, what
         an ordeal I have had to go through to see my only child enduring such terrible
         agony.  The Doctor continued his narrative
         by stating that he called in another physician, and after a consultation and
         four days careful attention to the patient they found her reviving and
         possessed of a strong desire to see the father of her child.        After consultation we decided it
         advisable to find the young man and bring him to the bedside of the apparently
         dying woman. Nothing short of a miracle could save her life, and we grasped at
         this circumstance as an opportunity for the enactment of a miracle.  I sought out the father of the young man and presented
         my
         view of the case to him. I informed him that I came neither as a moralist nor
         as a minister of the Gospel, but as a simple physician, whose duty it is to
         remove the cause that produces evil effect upon a patient. Miss— has been
         delivered of offspring and your son is the father of that child. She has
         realized the fact that her child is illegitimate and the issue without the
         sanction of law. The fact of her becoming a mother under such circumstances
         has produced acute mania and it may result in death. I therefore want your son
         to marry the young woman. The father, who by the way, is a haughty millionaire,
         at first refused to sanction such a union. He could not permit himself to allow
         his son to marry any such woman. The sacrifice was too great.I immediately informed him that no
         sacrifice that his son would make could ever atone for the wrong that he had
         committed, or for the sacrifice of her life, that this poor woman was about to
         suffer. I also told him that if he did not at once agree to the solemnization
         of the marriage rite between his son and my patient that I would acquaint the
         world with the true state of affairs, and that then he would find himself and
         family not only disgraced but scorned by all respectable people as a man unfit
         to be even tolerated in the community.  Finally he consented.I then called in an eminent divine of this city to officiate.
         The moment that she caught the sight of and was permitted to converse with the father
         of her child we discovered at once a perceptible change in her demeanor, looks
         and language. Placing the child in the bed with the mother we all prepared for
         the act that would legalize the child and redeem the mother. At the time there
         were present the father and mother of the girl, the mother of the young man and
         the two attendant physicians, who served as witnesses to the ceremony, and the
         form of making them man and wife according to the rules of the Episcopal church
         was gone through with. The ceremony had hardly ended before the poor girl,
         overcome with a mother's joy to think that her child had been saved, fell back
         upon the pillow and swooned away. The sequel to the sad story is the most
         painful chapter of the entire narrative. Two days after the fulfillment of the marriage
         contract our patient died. The child, however, was saved, and is an heir to $1,000,000
         and is now being cared for in the mansion of its wayward father. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>