<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00073</field>
      <field name="title">The Way We Live Now</field>
      <field name="setting">wild</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="theme">premaritalsex</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene Two: American vamp attempts a parlour seduction of Paul, the novel's hero'How are they changed?  I am two years older,
         if you mean that.' As she
         said this she looked round at the glass, as though to see whether she
         was become so haggard with age as to be unfit to become this man's
         wife. She was very lovely, with a kind of beauty which we seldom see
         now. In these days men regard the form and outward lines of a woman's
         face and figure more than either the colour or the expression, and
         women fit themselves to men's eyes. With padding and false hair
         without limit a figure may be constructed of almost any dimensions.
         The sculptors who construct them, male and female, hairdressers and
         milliners, are very skilful, and figures are constructed of noble
         dimensions, sometimes with voluptuous expansion, sometimes with
         classic reticence, sometimes with dishevelled negligence which becomes
         very dishevelled indeed when long out of the sculptor's hands. Colours
         indeed are added, but not the colours which we used to love. The taste
         for flesh and blood has for the day given place to an appetite for
         horsehair and pearl powder. But Mrs Hurtle was not a beauty after the
         present fashion. She was very dark,—a dark brunette,—with large round
         blue eyes, that could indeed be soft, but could also be very severe.
         Her silken hair, almost black, hung in a thousand curls all round her
         head and neck. Her cheeks and lips and neck were full, and the blood
         would come and go, giving a varying expression to her face with almost
         every word she spoke. Her nose also was full, and had something of the
         pug. But nevertheless it was a nose which any man who loved her would
         swear to be perfect. Her mouth was large, and she rarely showed her
         teeth. Her chin was full, marked by a large dimple, and as it ran down
         to her neck was beginning to form a second. Her bust was full and
         beautifully shaped; but she invariably dressed as though she were
         oblivious, or at any rate neglectful, of her own charms. Her dress, as
         Montague had seen her, was always black,—not a sad weeping widow's
         garment, but silk or woollen or cotton as the case might be, always
         new, always nice, always well-fitting, and most especially always
         simple. She was certainly a most beautiful woman, and she knew it. She
         looked as though she knew it,—but only after that fashion in which a
         woman ought to know it. Of her age she had never spoken to Montague.
         She was in truth over thirty,—perhaps almost as near thirty-five as
         thirty. But she was one of those whom years hardly seem to touch.'You are beautiful as ever you were,' he said.'Psha! Do not
         tell me of that. I care nothing for my beauty unless it
         can bind me to your love. Sit down there and tell me what it means.'
         Then she let go his hand, and seated herself opposite to the chair
         which she gave him.'I told you in my letter.''You told me nothing in your letter,—except that it was to be—off. Why
         is it to be—off?  Do you not love me?' Then she threw herself upon her
         knees, and leaned upon his, and looked up in his face. 'Paul,' she
         said, 'I have come across the Atlantic on purpose to see you,—after so
         many months,—and will you not give me one kiss?  Even though you should
         leave me for ever, give me one kiss.' Of course he kissed her, not
         once, but with a long, warm embrace. How could it have been otherwise?
         With all his heart he wished that she would have remained away, but
         while she knelt there at his feet what could he do but embrace her?
         'Now tell me everything,' she said, seating herself on a footstool at
         his feet. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>