<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00036</field>
      <field name="title">The Mill on the Floss</field>
      <field name="setting">piano</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One: Maggie Catches Stephen's erotic attention in the music room"Oh yes, pray bring him," said Lucy. "And you will like
         Maggie, sha'n't
         you?" she added, in a beseeching tone. "Isn't she a dear,
         noble-looking creature?""Too tall," said Stephen, smiling down upon her, "and a little too fiery. She is not my type of woman,
         you know."Gentlemen, you are aware,
         are apt to impart these imprudent confidences to ladies concerning their
         unfavorable opinion of sister fair ones. That is why so many women have the
         advantage of knowing that they are secretly repulsive to men who have
         self-denyingly made ardent love to them. And hardly anything could be more
         distinctively characteristic of Lucy than that she both implicitly believed
         what Stephen said, and was determined that Maggie should not know it. But you,
         who have a higher logic than the verbal to guide you, have already foreseen, as
         the direct sequence to that unfavorable opinion of Stephen's, that he walked
         down to the boathouse calculating, by the aid of a vivid imagination, that
         Maggie must give him her hand at least twice in consequence of this pleasant
         boating plan, and that a gentleman who wishes ladies to look at him is
         advantageously situated when he is rowing them in a boat. What then?  Had he
         fallen in love with this surprising daughter of Mrs. Tulliver at first sight?
         Certainly not. Such passions are never heard of in real life. Besides, he was
         in love already, and half-engaged to the dearest little creature in the world;
         and he was not a man to make a fool of himself in any way. But when one is
         five-and-twenty, one has not chalk-stones at one's finger-ends that the touch
         of a handsome girl should be entirely indifferent. It was perfectly natural and
         safe to admire beauty and enjoy looking at it,—at least under such
         circumstances as the present. And there was really something very interesting
         about this girl, with her poverty and troubles; it was gratifying to see the
         friendship between the two cousins. Generally, Stephen admitted, he was not
         fond of women who had any peculiarity of character, but here the peculiarity
         seemed really of a superior kind, and provided one is not obliged to marry such
         women, why, they certainly make a variety in social intercourse. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>