<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00197</field>
      <field name="title">Eugenie Grandet</field>
      <field name="setting">garden</field>
      <field name="theme">courtship</field>
      <field name="nationality">french</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene Three:  Charles tells Eugénie of his impending departure in the gardenWhen the two lovers were alone in the garden,
         Charles said to Eugénie,
         drawing her down on the old bench beneath the walnut-tree,—"I did right to trust Alphonse; he has done famously. He has managed
         my affairs with prudence and good faith. I now owe nothing in Paris.
         All my things have been sold; and he tells me that he has taken the
         advice of an old sea-captain and spent three thousand francs on a
         commercial outfit of European curiosities which will be sure to be in
         demand in the Indies. He has sent my trunks to Nantes, where a ship is
         loading for San Domingo. In five days, Eugénie, we must bid each other
         farewell—perhaps forever, at least for years. My outfit and ten
         thousand francs, which two of my friends send me, are a very small
         beginning. I cannot look to return for many years. My dear cousin, do
         not weight your life in the scales with mine; I may perish; some good
         marriage may be offered to you—""Do you love me?" she said."Oh, yes! indeed, yes!" he answered, with a depth of tone that
         revealed an equal depth of feeling."I shall wait, Charles—Good heavens! there is my father at his
         window," she said, repulsing her cousin, who leaned forward to kiss
         her.She ran quickly under the archway. Charles followed her. When she saw
         him, she retreated to the foot of the staircase and opened the
         swing-door; then, scarcely knowing where she was going, Eugénie reached
         the corner near Nanon's den, in the darkest end of the passage. There
         Charles caught her hand and drew her to his heart. Passing his arm
         about her waist, he made her lean gently upon him. Eugénie no longer
         resisted; she received and gave the purest, the sweetest, and yet,
         withal, the most unreserved of kisses."Dear Eugénie, a cousin is better than a brother, for he can marry
         you," said Charles."So be it!" cried Nanon, opening the door of her lair.The two lovers, alarmed, fled into the hall, where
         Eugénie took up her
         work and Charles began to read the litanies of the Virgin in Madame
         Grandet's prayer-book. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>