<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00084</field>
      <field name="title">Rereading Sex: Battles Over Sexual Knowledge and Suppression in Nineteenth-Century America</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">popularpress</field>
      <field name="text">1. "Some northerners dreamed that a disciplined and
         chastened America would emerge from the fires of the Civil War. But those
         venturing to New York City saw the opposite: a seeming explosion of
         sensationalism and sexual display. Caught up in this changing world, readers sought
         help in understanding sexuality and their own sexual natures. New books on
         phrenology and physiological reform aimed to instruct them. These were now
         more various and included works that articulated the fourth framework, which
         placed sex at the core of life, introduced through utopian movements,
         Spiritualism, and free love. Yet even as readers sought new information,
         forces of suppression threatened to curtail it. The obscenity conviction of
         Simon Landis for selling a book of reform physiology was a harbinger of changes
         to come: changes in law and the courts that would abridge Americans' freedom
         to publish — and therefore read — works offering sexual knowledge" (319).2. "In the late 1860s and early 1870s, weekly
         publications emanating from the city highlighted the racy features of New York
         sporting life and broadcast them to the broader society. By then George W.
         Matsell was the editor of the National Police Gazette...Under his
         direction, the National Police Gazette took on a more dramatic look. The
         technology and style of illustrations meant more exciting visuals emphasizing
         moments of violence, often linked with sexual crimes from across the
         nation...Ministerial misdeeds from many sections of the country formed a clear
         subgroup of articles, and readers learned about men of the cloth who taught
         masturbation to the young or murdered their wives" (322-23).3. "By the late 1860s, the National Police Gazette
         had a competitor in Frank Leslie's weekly, Days' Doings. Leslie had
         several publications appealing to children, Budget of Fun, Chimney Corner, and
         Boys' &amp; Girls'. The subtitle of the Days' Doings suggests
         its different emphasis: "Illustrating Current Events of Romance, Police
         Reports, Important Trials, and Sporting News." Although covering some of the
         ground of the National Police Gazette, the Days' Doings primarily
         promised and delivered salacious gossip about the theatrical world" (323). 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>