<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00193</field>
      <field name="title">Mary Barton</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="nationality">british</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="theme">courtship</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One:  Jem proposes to Mary and is refusedIt so happened that Jem, after much anxious thought, had determined that day
         to "put his fortune to the touch, to win or lose all."  He was in a condition to maintain a wife in comfort.  It was true
         his mother and aunt must form part of the household:  but such is not an uncommon case among the poor, and if there were the
         advantages of previous friendship between the parties, it was not, he though, an obstacle to matrimony.  Both mother and aunt,
         he believed, would welcome Mary.  And, oh! what a certainty of happiness the idea of that welcome implied.He had been absent
         and abstracted all day long with the thought of the coming event of the evening.  He almost smiled at himself for his care
         in washing and dressing in preparation for his visit to Mary; as if one waistcoat or another could decide his fate in so passionately
         a momentous thing.  He believed he only delayed before his little looking-glass for cowardice, for absolute fear of a girl.
         He would try not to think so much about the affair, and he thought the more.Poor Jem! it is not an auspicious moment for thee!"Come
         in," said Mary, as some one knocked at the door, while she sat sadly at her sewing, trying to earn a few pence by working
         over hours at some mourning.Jem entered, looking more awkward and abashed than he had ever done before.  Yet here was Mary
         all alone, just as he had hoped to find her.  She did not ask him to take a chair, but after standing a minute or two he sat
         down near her."Is your father ar home, Mary?" said he, by way of making an opening, for she seemed determined to keep silence,
         and went on stitching away."No, he's gone to his Union, I suppose."  Another silence.  It was no use waiting, thought Jem.
         The subject would never be led to by any talk he could think of in his anxious, fluttered state.  He had better begin at once."Mary!"
         said he, and the unusual tone of his voice made her look up for an instant, but in that time she understood from his countenance
         what was coming, and her heart beat so suddenly and violently she could hardly sit still.  Yet one thing she was sure of;
         nothing he could say should make her have him.  She would show them all who would be glad to have her.  She was not yet calm
         after her father's irritating speeches.  Yet her eyes fell veiled before that passionate look fixed upon her."Dear mary! (for
         how dear you are, I cannot rightly tell you in words.)  It's no new story I'm going to speak about.  You must ha' seen and
         known it long; for since we were boy and girl I ha' loved you above father and mother and all; and all I've thought on by
         day and dreamt on by night has been something in which you've had a share.  I'd no way of keeping you for long, and I scorned
         to try and tie you down; and I lived in terror lest some one else should take you to himself.  But now, Mary, I'm foreman
         in th' works, and, dear Mary! listen," as she, in her unbearable agitation, stood up and turned away from him.  He rose too,
         and came nearer, trying to take hold of her hand; but this she would not allow.  She was bracing herself up to refuse him,
         for once and for all."And now, Mary, I've a home to offer you, and a heart as true as ever man had to love you and cherish
         you; we shall never be rich folk, I dare say; but if a loving heart and a strong right arm can shield you from sorrow, or
         from want, mine shall do it.  I cannot speak as I would like; my love won't let itself be put in words.  But, oh! darling,
         say you'll believe me, and that you'll be mine."She could not speak at once; her words would not come."Mary, they say silence
         gives consent; is it so?" he whispered.Now or never the effort must be made."No! it does not with me."  Her voice was calm,
         although she trembled from head to foot.  "I will always be your friend, Jem, but I can never be your wife.""Not my wife?
         said he mournfully.  "O Mary, think awhile! you cannot be my friend if you will not be my wife.  At least, I can never be
         content to be only your friend.  Do think awhile!  If you say No, you will make me hopeless, desperate.  It's no love of yesterday.
         It has made the very groundwork of all that people call good in me.  I don't know what I shall be if you won't have me.  And,
         Mary, think how glad your father would be!  It may sound vain, but he's told me more than once how much he should like to
         see us two married."Jem intended this for a powerful argument, but in Mary's present mood it told against him more than anything;
         for it suggested the false and foolish idea that her father, in his evident anxiety to promote her marriage with Jem, had
         been speaking to him on the subject with some degree of solicitation."I tell you, Jem, it cannot be.  Once for all, I will
         never marry you.""And is this the end of all my hopes and fears? the end of my life, I may say, for it is the end of all worth
         living for!"  His agitation rose and carried him into passion.  "Mary, you'll hear, maybe, of me as a drunkard , and maybe
         as a thief, and maybe as a murderer.  Remember! when all are speaking ill of me, you will have no right to blame me, for it's
         your cruelty that will have made me what I feel I shall become.  You won't even say you'll try and like me; will you, Mary?"
         said he, suddenly changing his tone from threatening despair to fond, passionate entreaty, as he took her hand and held it
         forcibly between both of his, while he tried to catch a glimpse of her averted face.  She was silent, but it was from deep
         and violent emotion.  He could not bear to wait; he would not hope, to be dashed away again; he rather in his bitterness of
         heart chose the certainty of despair, and before she could resolve what to answer, he flung away her hand and rushed out of
         the house.Jem! Jem!" cried she, with faint and choking voice.  It was too late; he left street after street behind him with
         his almost winged speed, as he sought the fields, where he might give way unobserved to all the deep despair he felt. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>