<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00045</field>
      <field name="title">The Blithedale Romance</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="theme">seduction</field>
      <field name="nationality">american</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One: The male view of the exotic and alluring womanZenobia was truly a magnificent woman. The homely simplicity of her
         dress could not conceal, nor scarcely diminish, the queenliness of
         her presence. The image of her form and face should have been
         multiplied all over the earth. It was wronging the rest of mankind
         to retain her as the spectacle of only a few. The stage would have
         been her proper sphere. She should have made it a point of duty,
         moreover, to sit endlessly to painters and sculptors, and preferably
         to the latter; because the cold decorum of the marble would consist
         with the utmost scantiness of drapery, so that the eye might chastely
         be gladdened with her material perfection in its entireness. I know
         not well how to express that the native glow of coloring in her
         cheeks, and even the flesh-warmth over her round arms, and what was
         visible of her full bust,—in a word, her womanliness incarnated,
         compelled me sometimes to close my eyes, as if it were not quite
         the privilege of modesty to gaze at her. Illness and exhaustion, no
         doubt, had made me morbidly sensitive.I noticed—and wondered how Zenobia contrived it—that she had always
         a new flower in her hair. And still it was a hot-house flower,—an
         outlandish flower,—a flower of the tropics, such as appeared to have
         sprung passionately out of a soil the very weeds of which would be
         fervid and spicy. Unlike as was the flower of each successive day to
         the preceding one, it yet so assimilated its richness to the rich
         beauty of the woman, that I thought it the only flower fit to be worn;
         so fit, indeed, that Nature had evidently created this floral gem,
         in a happy exuberance, for the one purpose of worthily adorning
         Zenobia's head. It might be that my feverish fantasies clustered
         themselves about this peculiarity, and caused it to look more
         gorgeous and wonderful than if beheld with temperate eyes. In the
         height of my illness, as I well recollect, I went so far as to
         pronounce it preternatural."Zenobia is an enchantress!" whispered I once to Hollingsworth. "She
         is a sister of the Veiled Lady. That flower in her hair is a
         talisman. If you were to snatch it away, she would vanish, or be
         transformed into something else.""What does he say?" asked Zenobia."Nothing that has an atom of sense in it," answered Hollingsworth.
         "He is a little beside himself, I believe, and talks about your being
         a witch, and of some magical property in the flower that you wear in
         your hair.""It is an idea worthy of a feverish poet," said she, laughing rather
         compassionately, and taking out the flower. "I scorn to owe anything
         to magic. Here, Mr. Hollingsworth, you may keep the spell while it
         has any virtue in it; but I cannot promise you not to appear with a
         new one to-morrow. It is the one relic of my more brilliant, my
         happier days!"The most curious part of the matter was that, long after my slight
         delirium had passed away,—as long, indeed, as I continued to know
         this remarkable woman,—her daily flower affected my imagination,
         though more slightly, yet in very much the same way. The reason must
         have been that, whether intentionally on her part or not, this
         favorite ornament was actually a subtile expression of Zenobia's
         character.One subject, about which—very impertinently, moreover—I perplexed
         myself with a great many conjectures, was, whether Zenobia had ever
         been married. The idea, it must be understood, was unauthorized by
         any circumstance or suggestion that had made its way to my ears. So
         young as I beheld her, and the freshest and rosiest woman of a
         thousand, there was certainly no need of imputing to her a destiny
         already accomplished; the probability was far greater that her coming
         years had all life's richest gifts to bring. If the great event of a
         woman's existence had been consummated, the world knew nothing of it,
         although the world seemed to know Zenobia well. It was a ridiculous
         piece of romance, undoubtedly, to imagine that this beautiful
         personage, wealthy as she was, and holding a position that might
         fairly enough be called distinguished, could have given herself away
         so privately, but that some whisper and suspicion, and by degrees a
         full understanding of the fact, would eventually be blown abroad.
         But then, as I failed not to consider, her original home was at a
         distance of many hundred miles. Rumors might fill the social
         atmosphere, or might once have filled it, there, which would travel
         but slowly, against the wind, towards our Northeastern metropolis,
         and perhaps melt into thin air before reaching it.There was not—and I distinctly repeat it—the slightest foundation
         in my knowledge for any surmise of the kind. But there is a species
         of intuition,—either a spiritual lie or the subtile recognition of a
         fact,—which comes to us in a reduced state of the corporeal system.
         The soul gets the better of the body, after wasting illness, or when
         a vegetable diet may have mingled too much ether in the blood.
         Vapors then rise up to the brain, and take shapes that often image
         falsehood, but sometimes truth. The spheres of our companions have,
         at such periods, a vastly greater influence upon our own than when
         robust health gives us a repellent and self-defensive energy.
         Zenobia's sphere, I imagine, impressed itself powerfully on mine, and
         transformed me, during this period of my weakness, into something
         like a mesmerical clairvoyant.Then, also, as anybody could observe, the freedom of her deportment
         (though, to some tastes, it might commend itself as the utmost
         perfection of manner in a youthful widow or a blooming matron) was
         not exactly maiden-like. What girl had ever laughed as Zenobia did?
         What girl had ever spoken in her mellow tones? Her unconstrained and
         inevitable manifestation, I said often to myself, was that of a woman
         to whom wedlock had thrown wide the gates of mystery. Yet sometimes
         I strove to be ashamed of these conjectures. I acknowledged it as a
         masculine grossness— a sin of wicked interpretation, of which man is
         often guilty towards the other sex—thus to mistake the sweet,
         liberal, but womanly frankness of a noble and generous disposition.
         Still, it was of no avail to reason with myself nor to upbraid myself.
         Pertinaciously the thought, "Zenobia is a wife; Zenobia has lived
         and loved! There is no folded petal, no latent dewdrop, in this
         perfectly developed rose!"—irresistibly that thought drove out all
         other conclusions, as often as my mind reverted to the subject. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>