<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00052</field>
      <field name="title">Carmen</field>
      <field name="setting">urbanwalk</field>
      <field name="theme">class</field>
      <field name="theme">prostitution</field>
      <field name="nationality">french</field>
      <field name="category">fiction</field>
      <field name="text">Scene One: The narrator's nighttime flirtations with Carmen by the RiverOne evening, when it was too dark to see anything,
         I was leaning against the parapet of the quay, smoking, when a woman ascended the steps leading to the river and seated herself
         by my side.  She had in her hair a large bouqet of jasmine, the flowers which exhale an intoxicating odour at night.  She
         was simply, perhaps poorly clad, all in black, like most grisettes in the evening.  Women of fashion wear black only in the
         morning; in the evening they dress ÿ la francesca.  When she reached my side, my bather allowed the mantilla which coverd
         her head to fall over her shoulders, and I saw, "by the dim light that falleth from the stars," that she was young, small,
         well built, and that she had very large eyes.  I threw my cigar away at once.  She appreciated that distinctively French attention,
         and made haste to say that she was very fond of the smell of tobacco; in fact, that she sometimes smoked herself, when she
         could obtain a very mild papelito.  Luckily, I happened to have some of that description in my case, and I lost no time in
         offering them to her.  She deigned to take one and lighted it at a piece of burning string which a child brought us in consideration
         of a small coin.  Mingling our smoke, we talked so long, the fair bather and myself, that we were finally left alone on the
         quay.  I thought that I might safely venture to invite her to take an ice at the neveria [café].  After hesitating modestly,
         she accepted; but before concluding to do so, she wished to know what time it was.  I caused my repeater to strike, and that
         striking seemed to surprise her greatly."What wonderful things you foreigners invent!  From what country are you, señor? 
         An Englishman, no doubt?""A Frenchman, and your humble servant.  And you, señorita, or señora, are of Cordova, I presume?""No.""You
         are Andalusian, at all events.  It seems to me that I can tell that by your soft speech.""If you observe everybody's speech
         so closely, you should be able to guess what I am.""I believe that you are from the land of Jesus, within two steps of paradise."(I
         had learned this metaphor, which designates Andalusia, from my friend Francisco Sevilla, a well-known picador.)"Bah! paradise—the
         people about here say that it wasn't made for us.""In that case you must be a Moor, or—"I checked myself, not daring to say
         "Jewess.""Nonsense! you see well enough that I am a gypsy; would you like me to tell your baji [fortune]?  Have you ever heard
         of La Carmencita?  I am she."I was such a ne'er-do-well in those days—fifteen years ago—that I did not recoil in horror when
         I found myself seated beside a sorceress."Pshaw!"  I said to myself, "last week I supped with a highway robber, to-day I will
         eat ices with a handmaid of the devil.  When one is travelling, one must see everything."I had still another motive for cultivating
         her acquaintance.  When I left school, I confess to my shame, I had wasted some time studying the occult sciences, and several
         times indeed I had been tempted to conjure up the spirits of darkness.  Long since cured of my fondness for such investigations,
         I still retained, nevertheless, a certain amount of curiosity concerning all kinds of superstition, and I rejoiced at the
         prospect of learning how far the art of magic had been carried among the gypsies.While talking together we had entered the
         neveria and had taken our seats at a small table lighted by a candle confined in a glass globe.  I had abundant opportunity
         to examine my gitana, while divers respectable folk who were eating ices there lost themselves in amazement at seeing me in
         such goodly company.I seriously doubt whether Señorita Carmen was of the pure breed; at all events, she was infinitely prettier
         than any of the women of her nation whom I had ever met.  No woman is beautiful, say the Spaniards, unless she combines thirty
         so's; or, if you prefer, unless she may be described by ten adjectives, each of which is applicable to three parts of her
         person.  For instance, she must have three black things:  eyes, lashes, and eyebrows, etc.  (See Brantôme for the rest.) My
         gypsy could make no pretension to so many perfections.  Her skin, albeit perfectly smooth, closely resembled the hue of copper.
         Her eyes were oblique, but of a beautiful shape; her lips a little heavy but well formed, and disclosed two rows of teeth
         whiter than almonds without their skins.  Her hair, which was possibly a bit coarse, was black with a blue reflection, like
         a crow's wing, and long and glossy.  To avoid fatiguing you with a too verbose description, I will say that for each defect
         she had some good point, which stood out the more boldly perhaps by the very contrast.  It was a strange, wild type of beauty,
         a face which took one by surprise at first, but which one could not forget.  Her eyes, especially, had an expression at once
         voluptuous and fierce, which I have never seen since in any mortal eye.  "A gypsy's eye is a wolf's eye" is a Spanish saying
         which denotes keen observation.  If you have not the time to go to the Jardin des Plantes to study the glance of a wolf, observe
         your cat when it is watching a sparrow.Of course it would have been absurd to have my fortune told in a café.  So I requested
         the pretty sorceress to allow me to accompany her home.  She readily consented, but she desired once more to know how the
         time was passing and asked me to make my watch strike again."Is it real gold?" she inquired, scrutinising it with extraordinary
         attention.When we left the café, it was quite dark; most of the shops were closed, and the streets almost deserted.  We crossed
         the Guadalquivir by the bridge, and at the very extremity of the suburb, we stopped in front of a house which bore no resemblance
         to a palace.  A child admitted us.  The gypsy said some words to him in a language entirely unknown to me, which I afterwards
         found was the rommani or chipe calli, the language of the gitanos.  The child at once disappeared, leaving us in a room of
         considerable size, furnished with a small table, two stools, and a chest.  I must not forget to mention a jar of water, a
         pile of oranges, and a bunch of onions.As soon as we were alone, the gypsy took from her chest a pack of cards which seemed
         to have seen much service, a magnet, a dried chameleon, and a number of other articles essential to her art.  Then she bade
         me make a cross in my left hand with a coin, and the magic ceremonies began.  It is unnecessary to repeat her predictions;
         and, as for her method of operation, it was evident that she was not a sorceress by halves.Unfortunately we were soon disturbed.
         The door was suddenly thrown open with violence, and a man wrapped to the eyes in a brown cloak entered the room, addressing
         the gypsy in a far from amiable fashion.  I did not understand what he said, but his tone indicated that he was in a very
         bad temper.  At sight of him the gitana exhibited neither surprise nor anger, but she ran to meet him, and, with extraordinary
         volubility, said several sentences in the mysterious tongue which she had already used in my presence.  The word payllo, repeated
         several times, was the only word that I understood.  I knew that the gypsies designated thus every man of another race than
         their own.  Assuming that I was the subject of the discussion, I looked forward to a delicate explanation; I already had my
         hand on one of the stools and was deliberating as to the precise moment when it would be well for me to hurl it at the intruder's
         head.  But he roughly pushed the gypsy aside and strode toward me; then recoiled a step, exclaiming:"What! is it you, señor?"I
         looked closely at him and recognised my friend Don José.  At that moment I was inclined to regret that I had not let him be
         hanged."Ah! is it you, my fine fellow?" I cried, laughing as heartily as I could manage to do; "you interrupted the señorita
         just as she was telling me some very interesting things.""Always the same!  This must come to an end," he said between his
         teeth, glaring savagely at the girl.She meanwhile continued to talk to him in her own language.  She became excited by degrees.
         Her eye became bloodshot and terrible to look at, her features contracted, and she stamped upon the floor.  It seemed to me
         that she was earnestly urging him to do something which he evidently hesitated to do.  What that something was, I fancied
         that I understood only too well, when I saw her draw her little hand swiftly back and forth under her chin.  I was tempted
         to believe that it was a matter of cutting a throat, and I had some suspicion that the throat in question was my own.To all
         this torrent of eloquence Don José replied only by two or three words uttered in a sharp tone.  Thereupon the gypsy bestowed
         on him a glance of supreme contempt; then seated herself Turkish fashion in a corner of the room, selected an orange, peeled
         it, and began to eat it.Don José seized my arm, opened the door and led me into the street.  We walked about two hundred yards
         in absolute silence.  Then he said, extending his hand:"Go straight ahead and you will come to the bridge."With that he turned
         his back on me and walked rapidly away.  I returned to my inn rather sheepishly and in a very bad temper.  The worst feature
         of the affair was that when I undressed I found my watch was missing. 
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>