<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="id">ls.00080</field>
      <field name="title">from "Augustus Egg's Triptych:  A Narrative of Victorian Adultery"</field>
      <field name="setting">publicspace</field>
      <field name="setting">parlor</field>
      <field name="setting">boudoir</field>
      <field name="category">commentary</field>
      <field name="theme">adultery</field>
      <field name="theme">prostitution</field>
      <field name="theme">divorce</field>
      <field name="text">1. 
         "In the corner of one painting exhibited in the Royal Academy of 1858, two young girls build a house of cards on top of a
         book whose spine is labelled 'Balzac.'  This fragile edifice is the most vivid symbol of the iconology of Augustus Egg's untitled
         narrative cycle of three paintings identified in the catalogue by the following passage: 'August the 4th.  Have just heard
         that B— has been dead more than a fortnight, so his poor children have now lost both their parents. I hear she was seen on
         Friday last near the Strand, evidently without a place to lay her head.  What a fall hers has been!'These paintings have often
         been classified in secondary literary as . . . depicting the theme of the fallen woman, in company with such images as William
         Holman Hunt's The Awakening Conscience" (202).2. 
         "The book which forms the foundation for the house of cards might seem to provide the literary basis for the series, since
         its spine is clearly labelled BALZAC.  It stands, however, not for a specific literary source, but for the very phenomenon
         of adultery. . . . In 1836, J.W. Crocker, describing countless
         incidents of adultery in Balzac, stated, 'A baser, meaner, filthier scoundrel
         never polluted society than M. de Balzac's [sic] standard of "public morals",'
         an opinion echoed in the Foreign Quarterly Review in 1844: 'Balzac, on the contrary, treats it [adultery]
         as a matter of course. From his works it would be concluded that all wives
         are unfaithful; and that their infidelity is looked upon as only an insult to their
         husbands, never as a crime against society; nay, well bred husbands do not even consider it an
         insult. We believe that he has written scarcely a story in which love forms the
         principal element, in which adultery is not introduced. . . .'The French themselves were aware of this English view of
         morality. Hippolyte Taine, in his Notes on England, made on a trip he
         took in 1861, remarked on the importance of the institution of marriage to the
         English and the supposed contrast with the French:'Marriage is encompassed with profound respect,
         and as regards this matter, opinion is unbending; it is quite sufficient to read books,
         newspapers, especially writing in which anonymous authors indulge in the greatest
         licence, for example, romances, comic journals; adultery is never excused; even in the
         latitude of intimate conversations between man and man, it is always held up as a crime''. . . C— — related to me that in
         a Parisian circle he heard a man of the world observe to another — 'Is it true, then, that your wife has got a lover?'  This
         remark he considers monstrous, and he is right.  A book like Balzac's Physiologie du Mariage would give great offence; perhaps
         the author would be prosecuted by the Society for the Suppression of Vice, and probably it would not have been accepted by
         any publisher.'
         By placing the volume in the centre of this Victorian drawing room, Egg pointedly compares the amorality of Balzac with the
         theme of his own narrative, that adultery destroys the home and family.  He suggests the extent to which adultery, that supposed
         mainstay of the French novel, has infiltrated English life.  
      </field>
   </doc>
</add>